The First Fifty

The Chapter on Impermanence

SN 35.1 The Interior as Impermanent Ajjhattāniccasutta

So I have heard.[1661] At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, the eye is impermanent.[1662] What’s impermanent is suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

The ear is impermanent. …

The nose is impermanent. …

The tongue is impermanent. …[1663]

The body is impermanent. …

The mind is impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.2 The Interior as Suffering Ajjhattadukkhasutta

“Mendicants, the eye is suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

The ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.3 The Interior as Not-Self Ajjhattānattasutta

“Mendicants, the eye is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

The ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.4 The Exterior as Impermanent Bāhirāniccasutta

“Mendicants, sights are impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

Sounds,[1664] smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.5 The Exterior as Suffering Bāhiradukkhasutta

“Mendicants, sights are suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ …”

SN 35.6 The Exterior as Not-Self Bāhirānattasutta

“Mendicants, sights are not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ …”

SN 35.7 The Interior as Impermanent in the Three Times Ajjhattāniccātītānāgatasutta

“Mendicants, the eye of the past and future is impermanent, let alone the present.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple is not concerned with the eye of the past, they don’t look forward to enjoying the eye in the future, and they practice for disillusionment, dispassion, and cessation regarding the eye in the present.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind of the past and future is impermanent, let alone the present.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple doesn’t worry about the mind of the past, they don’t look forward to enjoying the mind in the future, and they practice for disillusionment, dispassion, and cessation regarding the mind in the present.”

SN 35.8 The Interior as Suffering in the Three Times Ajjhattadukkhātītānāgatasutta

“Mendicants, the eye of the past and future is suffering, let alone the present.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple is not concerned with the eye of the past, they don’t look forward to enjoying the eye in the future, and they practice for disillusionment, dispassion, and cessation regarding the eye in the present. …”

SN 35.9 The Interior as Not-Self in the Three Times Ajjhattānattātītānāgatasutta

“Mendicants, the eye of the past and future is not-self, let alone the present.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple is not concerned with the eye of the past, they don’t look forward to enjoying the eye in the future, and they practice for disillusionment, dispassion, and cessation regarding the eye in the present. …”

SN 35.10 The Exterior as Impermanent in the Three Times Bāhirāniccātītānāgatasutta

“Mendicants, sights of the past and future are impermanent, let alone the present. …”

SN 35.11 The Exterior as Suffering in the Three Times Bāhiradukkhātītānāgatasutta

“Mendicants, sights of the past and future are suffering, let alone the present. …”

SN 35.12 The Exterior as Not-Self in the Three Times Bāhirānattātītānāgatasutta

“Mendicants, sights of the past and future are not-self, let alone the present. …”

The Chapter on All is Impermanent

SN 35.43–51 Nine on Impermanence, Etc. Aniccādisuttanavaka

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, all is impermanent. And what is the all that is impermanent? The eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact are impermanent. And the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact is also impermanent.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … The mind, ideas, mind consciousness, and mind contact are impermanent. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is also impermanent.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned …

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

“Mendicants, all is suffering. …”

“Mendicants, all is not-self. …”

“Mendicants, all is to be directly known. …”

“Mendicants, all is to be completely understood. …”

“Mendicants, all is to be given up. …”

“Mendicants, all is to be realized. …”

“Mendicants, all is to be directly known and completely understood. …”

“Mendicants, all is harried. …”

SN 35.52 Contaminated Upassaṭṭhasutta

“Mendicants, all is contaminated.[1679] And what is the all that is contaminated? The eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact are contaminated. And the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact is also contaminated.

The ear … nose … tongue … body …

The mind, ideas, mind consciousness, and mind contact are contaminated. And the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is also contaminated.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned …

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

The Chapter on the All

SN 35.23 All Sabbasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the all.[1666] Listen …

And what is the all? It’s just the eye and sights, the ear and sounds, the nose and smells, the tongue and tastes, the body and touches, and the mind and ideas. This is called the all.

Mendicants, suppose someone was to say:[1667] ‘I’ll deny this all and describe another all.’ They’d have no grounds for that claim, they’d be stumped by questions, and, in addition, they’d get frustrated. Why is that? Because they’re out of their element.”[1668]

SN 35.24 Giving Up Pahānasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the principle for giving up the all. Listen …

And what is the principle for giving up the all? The eye should be given up. Sights should be given up. Eye consciousness should be given up. Eye contact should be given up. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact should also be given up.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind should be given up. Ideas should be given up. Mind consciousness should be given up. Mind contact should be given up. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact should be given up.

This is the principle for giving up the all.”

SN 35.25 Giving Up By Direct Knowledge and Complete Understanding Abhiññāpariññāpahānasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the principle for giving up the all by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Listen …

And what is the principle for giving up the all by direct knowledge and complete understanding? The eye should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Sights should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Eye consciousness should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Eye contact should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Ideas should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Mind consciousness should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. Mind contact should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact should be given up by direct knowledge and complete understanding.

This is the principle for giving up the all by direct knowledge and complete understanding.”

SN 35.26 Without Completely Understanding (1st) Paṭhamaaparijānanasutta

“Mendicants, without directly knowing and completely understanding the all, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering. And what is the all, without directly knowing and completely understanding which, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering?[1669]

Without directly knowing and completely understanding the eye, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering. Without directly knowing and completely understanding sights … eye consciousness … eye contact … painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering.

Without directly knowing and completely understanding the ear … the nose … the tongue … the body … the mind, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering. Without directly knowing and completely understanding ideas … mind consciousness … mind contact … painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering.

This is the all, without directly knowing and completely understanding which, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering.

By directly knowing and completely understanding the all, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering. And what is the all, directly knowing and completely understanding which, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering?

By directly knowing and completely understanding the eye … the ear … the nose … the tongue … the body … the mind, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering. By directly knowing and completely understanding ideas … mind consciousness … mind contact … painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering.

This is the all, directly knowing and completely understanding which, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering.”

SN 35.27 Without Completely Understanding (2nd) Dutiyaaparijānanasutta

“Mendicants, without directly knowing and completely understanding the all, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering. And what is the all, without directly knowing and completely understanding which, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering?

The eye, sights, eye consciousness, and things knowable by eye consciousness.[1670]

The ear … nose … tongue … body …

The mind, ideas, mind consciousness, and things knowable by mind consciousness.

This is the all, without directly knowing and completely understanding which, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering.

By directly knowing and completely understanding the all, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering. And what is the all, directly knowing and completely understanding which, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering?

The eye, sights, eye consciousness, and things knowable by eye consciousness.

The ear … nose … tongue … body …

The mind, ideas, mind consciousness, and things knowable by mind consciousness.

This is the all, directly knowing and completely understanding which, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering.”

SN 35.28 Burning Ādittasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Gayā on Gayā Head together with a thousand mendicants.[1671] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, all is burning.[1672] And what is the all that is burning?

The eye is burning. Sights are burning. Eye consciousness is burning. Eye contact is burning. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact is also burning. Burning with what?[1673] Burning with the fires of greed, hate, and delusion. Burning with rebirth, old age, and death, with sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress.[1674]

The ear … nose … tongue … body …

The mind is burning. Ideas are burning. Mind consciousness is burning. Mind contact is burning. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is also burning. Burning with what? Burning with the fires of greed, hate, and delusion. Burning with rebirth, old age, and death, with sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress, I say.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact. And they grow disillusioned with the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact.

They grow disillusioned with the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind … painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact.

Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said. And while this discourse was being spoken, the minds of the thousand mendicants were freed from defilements by not grasping.

SN 35.29 Overcome Addhabhūtasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, all is overcome.[1675] And what is the all that is overcome?

The eye is overcome. Sights are overcome. Eye consciousness is overcome. Eye contact is overcome. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact is also overcome. Overcome by what? Overcome by the fires of greed, hate, and delusion. Overcome by rebirth, old age, and death, by sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress, I say.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is overcome. Ideas are overcome. Mind consciousness is overcome. Mind contact is overcome. The painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is also overcome. Overcome by what? Overcome by greed, hate, and delusion. Overcome by rebirth, old age, and death, by sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress, I say.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact. And they grow disillusioned with the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact.

They grow disillusioned with the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind … painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.30 The Practice Fit for Uprooting Samugghātasāruppasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the practice fit for uprooting all conceiving.[1676] Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. …

And what is the practice fit for uprooting all conceiving?

It’s when a mendicant does not conceive anything to be the eye, does not conceive it in the eye, does not conceive it as the eye, and does not conceive that ‘the eye is mine.’ They don’t conceive anything to be sights, they don’t conceive it in sights, they don’t conceive it as sights, and they don’t conceive that ‘sights are mine.’ They don’t conceive eye consciousness … eye contact … They don’t conceive anything to be the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact. They don’t conceive it in that, they don’t conceive it as that, and they don’t conceive that ‘that is mine.’

They don’t conceive anything to be the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind … They don’t conceive anything to be the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact. They don’t conceive it in that, they don’t conceive it as that, and they don’t conceive that ‘that is mine.’

They don’t conceive anything to be all, they don’t conceive it in all, they don’t conceive it as all, and they don’t conceive that ‘all is mine.’ Not conceiving, they don’t grasp at anything in the world. Not grasping, they’re not anxious. Not being anxious, they personally become extinguished.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

This is the practice fit for uprooting all conceiving.”

SN 35.31 The Practice Conducive to Uprooting (1st) Paṭhamasamugghātasappāyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the practice that’s conducive to uprooting all conceiving.[1677] Listen …

And what is the practice that’s conducive to uprooting all conceiving? It’s when a mendicant does not conceive anything to be the eye, does not conceive it in the eye, does not conceive it as the eye, and does not conceive that ‘the eye is mine.’ They don’t conceive anything to be sights … eye consciousness … eye contact. And they don’t conceive anything to be the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact. They don’t conceive it in that, they don’t conceive it as that, and they don’t conceive that ‘that is mine.’

For whatever you conceive it to be, whatever you conceive it in, whatever you conceive it as, and whatever you conceive to be ‘mine’: that becomes something else. The world is attached to being, taking pleasure only in being, yet it becomes something else.[1678]

They don’t conceive anything to be the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind … They don’t conceive anything to be the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact. They don’t conceive it in that, they don’t conceive it as that, and they don’t conceive that ‘that is mine.’

For whatever you conceive it to be, whatever you conceive it in, whatever you conceive it as, and whatever you conceive to be ‘mine’: that becomes something else. The world is attached to being, taking pleasure only in being, yet it becomes something else.

As far as the aggregates, elements, and sense fields extend, they don’t conceive anything to be that, they don’t conceive it in that, they don’t conceive it as that, and they don’t conceive that ‘that is mine.’ Not conceiving, they don’t grasp at anything in the world. Not grasping, they’re not anxious. Not being anxious, they personally become extinguished.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

This is the practice that’s conducive to uprooting all conceiving.”

SN 35.32 The Practice Conducive to Uprooting (2nd) Dutiyasamugghātasappāyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the practice that’s conducive to uprooting all conceiving. Listen …

And what is the practice that’s conducive to uprooting all conceiving?

What do you think, mendicants? Is the eye permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, is it fit to be regarded thus: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self’?”

“No, sir.”

“Are sights … eye consciousness … eye contact …

The pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact: is that permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, is it fit to be regarded thus: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self’?”

“No, sir.” …

“Is the ear … nose … tongue …

body … mind …

The pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact: is that permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, is it fit to be regarded thus: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self’?”

“No, sir.”

“Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact. And they grow disillusioned with the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact.

They grow disillusioned with the ear … nose … tongue … body … They grow disillusioned with the mind, ideas, mind consciousness, and mind contact. And they grow disillusioned with the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact.

Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’ This is the practice that’s conducive to uprooting all conceiving.”

The Chapter on the Sixes

SN 35.94 Untamed, Unguarded Adantaaguttasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these six fields of contact bring suffering when they’re untamed, unguarded, unprotected, and unrestrained. What six?

The field of eye contact brings suffering when it’s untamed, unguarded, unprotected, and unrestrained.

The field of ear contact … nose contact … tongue contact … body contact …

The field of mind contact brings suffering when it’s untamed, unguarded, unprotected, and unrestrained.

These six fields of contact bring suffering when they’re untamed, unguarded, unprotected, and unrestrained.

These six fields of contact bring happiness when they’re well tamed, well guarded, well protected, and well restrained. What six?

The field of eye contact brings happiness when it’s well tamed, well guarded, well protected, and well restrained.

The field of ear contact … nose contact … tongue contact … body contact …

The field of mind contact brings happiness when it’s well tamed, well guarded, well protected, and well restrained.

These six fields of contact bring happiness when they’re well tamed, well guarded, well protected, and well restrained.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Mendicants, it’s just the six fields of contact
that lead the unrestrained to suffering.
Those who understand how to restrain them
live with faith as partner, not festering.

When you’ve seen pleasant sights[1732]
and unpleasant ones, too,
dispel all manner of desire for the pleasant,
without hating what you don’t like.

When you’ve heard sounds both liked and disliked,
don’t fall under the thrall of sounds you like,
dispel hate for the unliked,
and don’t hurt your mind by thinking of what you don’t like.

When you’ve smelled a pleasant, fragrant scent,
and one that’s foul and unpleasant,
dispel aversion for the unpleasant,
while not yielding to desire for the pleasant.

When you’ve enjoyed a sweet, delicious taste,[1733]
and sometimes those that are bitter,
don’t be attached to enjoying sweet tastes,
and don’t despise the bitter.

Don’t be intoxicated by a pleasant touch,
and don’t tremble at a painful touch.
Look with equanimity at the duality of pleasant and painful contacts,[1734]
without favoring or opposing anything.

People generally let their perceptions proliferate;[1735]
perceiving and proliferating, they are attracted.[1736]
Casting aside all mental constructions of the domestic life,[1737]
wander intent on renunciation.

When the mind is well developed like this regarding the six,
it doesn’t waver at contacts at all.
Mendicants, those who have mastered greed and hate
go beyond birth and death.”

SN 35.95 Māluṅkyaputta Mālukyaputtasutta

Then Venerable Māluṅkyaputta went up to the Buddha … and asked him,[1738] “Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Well now, Māluṅkyaputta, what are we to say to the young monks, when even an old man like you, elderly and senior, advanced in years, having reached the final stage of life, asks for brief advice?”

“Sir, even though I’m an old man, elderly and senior, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief! May the Holy One please teach me in brief! Hopefully I can understand the meaning of what the Buddha says. Hopefully I can be an heir of the Buddha’s teaching!”

“What do you think, Māluṅkyaputta? Do you have any desire or greed or fondness for sights known by the eye that are unseen, unseen before, and which you neither see nor think might be seen?”[1739]

“No, sir.”

“Do you have any desire or greed or affection for sounds known by the ear …

smells known by the nose …

tastes known by the tongue …

touches known by the body …

ideas known by the mind that are unknown, unknown before, and which you neither know nor think might be known?”

“No, sir.”

“In that case, when it comes to things that ought be seen, heard, thought, and known: in the seen will be merely the seen; in the heard will be merely the heard; in the thought will be merely the thought; in the known will be merely the known.[1740] When this is the case, you won’t be ‘by that’.[1741] When you’re not ‘by that’, you won’t be ‘in that’.[1742] When you’re not ‘in that’, you won’t be in this life or the next or in between the two. Just this is the end of suffering.”

“This is how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement:

‘When you see a sight, mindfulness is lost
as you focus on a pleasant feature.
Experiencing it with a mind full of desire,
you keep clinging to it.

Many feelings grow
arising from sights.
The mind is damaged
by covetousness and cruelty.
Heaping up suffering like this,
you’re said to be far from extinguishment.

When you hear a sound, mindfulness is lost
as you focus on a pleasant feature.
Experiencing it with a mind full of desire,
you keep clinging to it.

Many feelings grow
arising from sounds.
The mind is damaged
by covetousness and cruelty.
Heaping up suffering like this,
you’re said to be far from extinguishment.

When you smell an odor, mindfulness is lost
as you focus on a pleasant feature.
Experiencing it with a mind full of desire,
you keep clinging to it.

Many feelings grow
arising from smells.
The mind is damaged
by covetousness and cruelty.
Heaping up suffering like this,
you’re said to be far from extinguishment.

When you enjoy a taste, mindfulness is lost
as you focus on a pleasant feature.
Experiencing it with a mind full of desire,
you keep clinging to it.

Many feelings grow
arising from tastes.
The mind is damaged
by covetousness and cruelty.
Heaping up suffering like this,
you’re said to be far from extinguishment.

When you sense a touch, mindfulness is lost
as you focus on a pleasant feature.
Experiencing it with a mind full of desire,
you keep clinging to it.

Many feelings grow
arising from touches.
The mind is damaged
by covetousness and cruelty.
Heaping up suffering like this,
you’re said to be far from extinguishment.

When you know an idea, mindfulness is lost
as you focus on a pleasant feature.
Experiencing it with a mind full of desire,
you keep clinging to it.

Many feelings grow
arising from ideas.
The mind is damaged
by covetousness and cruelty.
Heaping up suffering like this,
you’re said to be far from extinguishment.

There’s no desire for sights
when you see a sight with mindfulness.
Experiencing it with a mind free of desire,
you don’t keep clinging to it.

Even as you see a sight
and get familiar with how it feels,
you wear away, you don’t heap up:
that’s how to live mindfully.
Eroding suffering like this,
you’re said to be in the presence of extinguishment.

There’s no desire for sounds
when you hear a sound with mindfulness.
Experiencing it with a mind free of desire,
you don’t keep clinging to it.

Even as you hear a sound
and get familiar with how it feels,
you wear away, you don’t heap up:
that’s how to live mindfully.
Eroding suffering like this,
you’re said to be in the presence of extinguishment.

There’s no desire for odors
when you smell an odor with mindfulness.
Experiencing it with a mind free of desire,
you don’t keep clinging to it.

Even as you smell an odor
and get familiar with how it feels,
you wear away, you don’t heap up:
that’s how to live mindfully.
Eroding suffering like this,
you’re said to be in the presence of extinguishment.

There’s no desire for tastes
when you enjoy a taste with mindfulness.
Experiencing it with a mind free of desire,
you don’t keep clinging to it.

Even as you savor a taste
and get familiar with how it feels,
you wear away, you don’t heap up:
that’s how to live mindfully.
Eroding suffering like this,
you’re said to be in the presence of extinguishment.

There’s no desire for touches
when you sense a touch with mindfulness.
Experiencing it with a mind free of desire,
you don’t keep clinging to it.

Even as you sense a touch
and get familiar with how it feels,
you wear away, you don’t heap up:
that’s how to live mindfully.
Eroding suffering like this,
you’re said to be in the presence of extinguishment.

There’s no desire for ideas
when you know an idea with mindfulness.
Experiencing it with a mind free of desire,
you don’t keep clinging to it.

Even as you know an idea
and get familiar with how it feels,
you wear away, you don’t heap up:
that’s how to live mindfully.
Eroding suffering like this,
you’re said to be in the presence of extinguishment.’

That’s how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement.”

“Good, good, Māluṅkyaputta! It’s good that you understand the detailed meaning of what I’ve said in brief like this.” And he repeated the verses in full.

“This is how to see the detailed meaning of what I said in brief.”

And then Venerable Māluṅkyaputta approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving. Then Māluṅkyaputta, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Māluṅkyaputta became one of the perfected.

SN 35.96 Liable to Decline Parihānadhammasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you who is liable to decline, who is not liable to decline, and the six fields of mastery.[1743] Listen …

And how is someone liable to decline? When a mendicant sees a sight with their eyes, bad, unskillful phenomena arise: memories and thoughts that tighten the fetters. Suppose that mendicant tolerates them and doesn’t give them up, dispel them, eliminate them, and obliterate them. They should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are declining. For this is what the Buddha calls decline.’

Furthermore, when a mendicant hears a sound … smells an odor … tastes a flavor … encounters a touch … knows an idea with their mind, bad, unskillful phenomena arise: memories and thoughts that tighten the fetters. If that mendicant tolerates them and doesn’t give them up, dispel them, eliminate them, and obliterate them, they should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are declining. For this is what the Buddha calls decline.’ That’s how someone is liable to decline.

And how is someone not liable to decline? When a mendicant sees a sight with their eyes, bad, unskillful phenomena arise: memories and thoughts that tighten the fetters. Suppose that mendicant doesn’t tolerate them but gives them up, dispels them, eliminates them, and obliterates them. They should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are not declining. For this is what the Buddha calls non-decline.’

Furthermore, when a mendicant hears a sound … smells an odor … tastes a flavor … encounters a touch … knows an idea with their mind, bad, unskillful phenomena arise: memories and thoughts that tighten the fetters. Suppose that mendicant doesn’t tolerate them but gives them up, dispels them, eliminates them, and obliterates them. They should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are not declining. For this is what the Buddha calls non-decline.’ That’s how someone is not liable to decline.

And what are the six fields of mastery? When a mendicant sees a sight with their eyes, bad, unskillful phenomena don’t arise: memories and thoughts that tighten the fetters. They should understand: ‘This sense field has been mastered. For this is what the Buddha calls a field of mastery.’ … Furthermore, when a mendicant knows an idea with their mind, bad, unskillful phenomena don’t arise: memories and thoughts that tighten the fetters. They should understand: ‘This sense field has been mastered. For this is what the Buddha calls a field of mastery.’ These are the six fields of mastery.”

SN 35.97 One Who Lives Negligently Pamādavihārīsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you who lives negligently and who lives diligently.[1744] Listen …

And how does someone live negligently?

When you live with the eye faculty unrestrained, your mind becomes polluted when it comes to sights known by the eye. When the mind is polluted, there’s no joy.[1745] When there’s no joy, there’s no rapture. When there’s no rapture, there’s no tranquility. When there’s no tranquility, there’s suffering. When one is suffering, the mind does not become immersed in samādhi. When the mind is not immersed in samādhi, principles do not become clear.[1746] Because principles have not become clear, you’re reckoned to live negligently.

When you live with the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind faculty unrestrained, your mind becomes polluted when it comes to ideas known by the mind. When the mind is polluted, there’s no joy. When there’s no joy, there’s no rapture. When there’s no rapture, there’s no tranquility. When there’s no tranquility, there’s suffering. When one is suffering, the mind does not become immersed in samādhi. When the mind is not immersed in samādhi, principles do not become clear. Because principles have not become clear, you’re reckoned to live negligently.

That’s how someone lives negligently.

And how does someone live diligently?

When you live with the eye faculty restrained, your mind doesn’t become polluted when it comes to sights known by the eye. When the mind isn’t polluted, joy springs up. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, one feels bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. When the mind is immersed in samādhi, principles become clear. Because principles have become clear, you’re reckoned to live diligently.

When you live with the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind faculty restrained, your mind doesn’t become polluted when it comes to ideas known by the mind. When the mind isn’t polluted, joy springs up. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, one feels bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. When the mind is immersed in samādhi, principles become clear. Because principles have become clear, you’re reckoned to live diligently.

That’s how someone lives diligently.”

SN 35.98 Restraint Saṁvarasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you who is restrained and who is unrestrained. Listen …

And how is someone unrestrained?

There are sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant approves, welcomes, and keeps clinging to them, they should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are declining. For this is what the Buddha calls decline.’

There are sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant approves, welcomes, and keeps clinging to them, they should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are declining. For this is what the Buddha calls decline.’

This is how someone is unrestrained.

And how is someone restrained?

There are sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant doesn’t approve, welcome, and keep clinging to them, they should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are not declining. For this is what the Buddha calls non-decline.’

There are sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant doesn’t approve, welcome, and keep clinging to them, they should understand: ‘My skillful qualities are not declining. For this is what the Buddha calls non-decline.’

This is how someone is restrained.”

SN 35.99 Immersion Samādhisutta

“Mendicants, develop immersion.[1747] A mendicant who has immersion truly understands. What do they truly understand?

They truly understand that the eye is impermanent. They truly understand that sights … eye consciousness … eye contact … the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact is impermanent. …

They truly understand that the mind is impermanent. They truly understand that ideas … mind consciousness … mind contact … the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is impermanent.

Mendicants, develop immersion. A mendicant who has immersion truly understands.”

SN 35.100 Retreat Paṭisallānasutta

“Mendicants, meditate in retreat.[1748] A mendicant in retreat truly understands. What do they truly understand?

They truly understand that the eye is impermanent. They truly understand that sights … eye consciousness … eye contact … the pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is impermanent.

Mendicants, meditate in retreat. A mendicant in retreat truly understands.”

SN 35.101 It’s Not Yours (1st) Paṭhamanatumhākasutta

“Mendicants, give up what’s not yours. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness. And what isn’t yours?

The eye isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness. Sights … Eye consciousness … Eye contact … The pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness.

The ear … nose … tongue … body …

The mind isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness. Ideas … Mind consciousness … Mind contact … The pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness.

Suppose a person was to carry off the grass, sticks, branches, and leaves in this Jeta’s Grove, or burn them, or do what they want with them. Would you think: ‘This person is carrying us off, burning us, or doing what they want with us’?”

“No, sir. Why is that? Because to us that’s neither self nor belonging to self.”

“In the same way, the eye isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness. …

The pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness.”

SN 35.102 It’s Not Yours (2nd) Dutiyanatumhākasutta

“Mendicants, give up what’s not yours. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness. And what isn’t yours?

The eye isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness. Sights … Eye consciousness … Eye contact …

The pleasant, painful, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact isn’t yours: give it up. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness.

Give up what’s not yours. Giving it up will be for your welfare and happiness.”

SN 35.103 About Uddaka Udakasutta

“Mendicants, Uddaka son of Rāma used to say:[1749]

‘Hereupon, ever the knowledge master![1750]
Hereupon, ever the conqueror of all!
Hereupon, ever the undug[1751]
boil’s root was dug out by me!’[1752]

Even though Uddaka son of Rāma was no knowledge master, he said ‘I’m a knowledge master.’ Though he was no conqueror of all, he said ‘I’m conqueror of all.’ And though the boil’s root was not dug out, he said ‘I’ve dug out the boil’s root.’[1753]

A mendicant might rightly say here:

‘Hereupon, ever the knowledge master!
Hereupon, ever the conqueror of all!
Hereupon, ever the undug
boil’s root is dug out!’

And how is someone a knowledge master? It’s when a mendicant truly understands the six fields of contact’s origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. That’s how a mendicant is a knowledge master.

And how is a mendicant a conqueror of all? It’s when a mendicant comes to be freed by not grasping after truly understanding the six fields of contact’s origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. That’s how a mendicant is a conqueror of all.

And how has a mendicant dug out the undug boil’s root? ‘Boil’ is a term for this body made up of the four principal states, produced by mother and father, built up from rice and porridge, liable to impermanence, to wearing away and erosion, to breaking up and destruction.[1754] ‘Boil’s root’ is a term for craving. It’s when a mendicant has given up craving, cut it off at the root, made it like a palm stump, obliterated it, so it’s unable to arise in the future. That’s how a mendicant has dug out the undug boil’s root.

Uddaka son of Rāma used to say:

‘Hereupon, ever the knowledge master!
Hereupon, ever the conqueror of all!
Hereupon, ever the undug
boil’s root is dug out!’

Even though Uddaka son of Rāma was no knowledge master, he said ‘I’m a knowledge master.’ Though he was no conqueror of all, he said ‘I’m conqueror of all.’ And though the boil’s root was not dug out, he said ‘I’ve dug out the boil’s root.’

A mendicant might rightly say here:

‘Hereupon, ever the knowledge master!
Hereupon, ever the conqueror of all!
Hereupon, ever the undug
boil’s root is dug out!’”

The Chapter on the Ocean

SN 35.228 The Ocean (1st) Paṭhamasamuddasutta

“Mendicants, an unlearned ordinary person speaks of the ocean. But that’s not the ocean in the training of the Noble One. That’s just a large body of water, a large sea of water. For a person, the eye is an ocean, and its currents are made of sights.[1825]

Someone who can prevail over those currents is said to have crossed over the ocean of the eye, with its waves and whirlpools, its saltwater crocodiles and monsters.[1826] Crossed over, gone to the far shore, the brahmin stands on solid ground.

For a person, the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is an ocean, and its currents are made of ideas. Someone who can prevail over those currents is said to have crossed over the ocean of the mind, with its waves and whirlpools, its saltwater crocodiles and monsters. Crossed over, gone to the far shore, the brahmin stands on solid ground.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“A knowledge master who’s crossed the ocean so hard to cross,
with its saltwater crocodiles and monsters, its waves, whirlpools, and dangers;
they’ve completed the spiritual journey and gone to the end of the world,
they’re called ‘one who has gone beyond’.”

SN 35.229 The Ocean (2nd) Dutiyasamuddasutta

“Mendicants, an unlearned ordinary person speaks of the ocean. But that’s not the ocean in the training of the Noble One. That’s just a large body of water, a large sea of water.

There are sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. This is called the ocean in the training of the Noble One. And it’s here that this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, gods and humans—is for the most part sunk. It’s become tangled like string, knotted like a ball of thread, and matted like rushes and reeds, and it doesn’t escape the places of loss, the bad places, the underworld, transmigration.

There are sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. This is called the ocean in the training of the Noble One. And it’s here that this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, gods and humans—is for the most part sunk. It’s become tangled like string, knotted like a ball of thread, and matted like rushes and reeds, and it doesn’t escape the places of loss, the bad places, the underworld, transmigration.

Those in whom greed, hate, and ignorance[1827]
have faded away;
have crossed the ocean so hard to cross,
with its saltwater crocodiles and monsters, its waves and dangers.

They’ve slipped their chains, given up death, and have no attachments.
They’ve given up suffering, so there are no more future lives.
They’ve disappeared, and cannot be measured;
and they’ve confounded the King of Death, I say.”

SN 35.230 The Simile of the Angler Bāḷisikopamasutta

“Mendicants, suppose an angler was to cast a baited hook into a deep lake. Seeing the bait, a fish would swallow it. And so the fish that swallowed the hook would meet with tragedy and disaster, and the angler can do what he wants with it.

In the same way, there are these six hooks in the world that mean tragedy and slaughter for living creatures. What six?

There are sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant approves, welcomes, and keeps clinging to them, they’re called a mendicant who has swallowed Māra’s hook. They’ve met with tragedy and disaster, and the Wicked One can do with them what he wants.

There are sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant approves, welcomes, and keeps clinging to them, they’re called a mendicant who has swallowed Māra’s hook. They’ve met with tragedy and disaster, and the Wicked One can do with them what he wants.

There are sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant doesn’t approve, welcome, and keep clinging to them, they’re called a mendicant who hasn’t swallowed Māra’s hook. They’ve broken the hook, destroyed it. They haven’t met with tragedy and disaster, and the Wicked One cannot do with them what he wants.

There are sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. If a mendicant doesn’t approve, welcome, and keep clinging to them, they’re called a mendicant who hasn’t swallowed Māra’s hook. They’ve broken the hook, destroyed it. They haven’t met with tragedy and disaster, and the Wicked One cannot do with them what he wants.”

SN 35.231 The Simile of the Latex-Producing Tree Khīrarukkhopamasutta

“Mendicants, take any monk or nun who, when it comes to sights known by the eye, still has greed, hate, and delusion, and has not given them up. If even trivial sights come into their range of vision they overcome their mind, let alone those that are compelling.[1828] Why is that? Because they still have greed, hate, and delusion, and have not given them up.

When it comes to sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, they still have greed, hate, and delusion, and have not given them up. If even trivial thoughts come into the range of the mind they overcome their mind, let alone those that are compelling. Why is that? Because they still have greed, hate, and delusion, and have not given them up.

Suppose there was a latex-producing tree—such as a peepal, a banyan, a wavy leaf fig, or a cluster fig—that’s a tender young sapling.[1829] If a man were to chop it here and there with a sharp axe, would latex come out?”

“Yes, sir.

Why is that? Because it still has latex.”

“In the same way, take any monk or nun who, when it comes to sights known by the eye, still has greed, hate, and delusion, and has not given them up. If even trivial sights come into their range of vision they overcome their mind, let alone those that are compelling. Why is that? Because they still have greed, hate, and delusion, and have not given them up.

When it comes to sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, they still have greed, hate, and delusion, and have not given them up. If even trivial thoughts come into the range of the mind they overcome their mind, let alone those that are compelling. Why is that? Because they still have greed, hate, and delusion, and have not given them up.

Take any monk or nun who, when it comes to sights known by the eye, has no greed, hate, and delusion left, and has given them up. If even compelling sights come into their range of vision they don’t overcome their mind, let alone those that are trivial. Why is that? Because they have no greed, hate, and delusion left, and have given them up.

When it comes to sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, they have no greed, hate, and delusion left, and have given them up. If even compelling ideas come into the range of the mind they don’t overcome their mind, let alone those that are trivial. Why is that? Because they have no greed, hate, and delusion left, and have given them up.

Suppose there was a latex-producing tree—such as a peepal, a banyan, a wavy leaf fig, or a cluster fig—that’s dried up, withered, and decrepit. If a man were to chop it here and there with a sharp axe, would latex come out?”

“No, sir. Why is that? Because it has no latex left.”

“In the same way, take any monk or nun who, when it comes to sights known by the eye, has no greed, hate, and delusion left, and has given them up. If even compelling sights come into their range of vision they don’t overcome their mind, let alone those that are trivial. Why is that? Because they have no greed, hate, and delusion left, and have given them up.

When it comes to sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas known by the mind, they have no greed, hate, and delusion left, and have given them up. If even compelling thoughts come into the range of the mind they don’t overcome their mind, let alone those that are trivial. Why is that? Because they have no greed, hate, and delusion left, and have given them up.”

SN 35.232 With Koṭṭhita Koṭṭhikasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta and Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita were staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana. Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita came out of retreat, went to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Sāriputta:

“Reverend Sāriputta, which is it? Is the eye the fetter of sights, or are sights the fetter of the eye? Is the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind the fetter of ideas, or are ideas the fetter of the mind?”

“Reverend Koṭṭhita, the eye is not the fetter of sights, nor are sights the fetter of the eye. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them. The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the mind. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.

Suppose there was a black ox and a white ox yoked by a single harness or yoke. Would it be right to say that the black ox is the yoke of the white ox, or the white ox is the yoke of the black ox?”

“No, reverend.[1830] The black ox is not the yoke of the white ox, nor is the white ox the yoke of the black ox. The yoke there is the single harness or yoke that they’re yoked by.”

“In the same way, the eye is not the fetter of sights, nor are sights the fetter of the eye. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them. The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the mind. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.

If the eye were the fetter of sights, or if sights were the fetter of the eye, this living of the spiritual life for the complete ending of suffering would not be found. However, since this is not the case, but the fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them, this living of the spiritual life for the complete ending of suffering is found.

If the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind were the fetter of ideas, or if ideas were the fetter of the mind, this living of the spiritual life for the complete ending of suffering would not be found. However, since this is not the case, but the fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them, this living of the spiritual life for the complete ending of suffering is found.

This too is a way to understand how this is so.

The Buddha has an eye with which he sees a sight. But he has no desire and greed, for his mind is well freed. The Buddha has an ear … nose … tongue … The Buddha has a body with which he senses touch. But he has no desire and greed, for his mind is well freed. The Buddha has a mind

with which he knows ideas. But he has no desire and greed, for his mind is well freed.

This too is a way to understand how the eye is not the fetter of sights, nor are sights the fetter of the eye. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them. The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the mind. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.”

SN 35.233 With Kāmabhū Kāmabhūsutta

At one time the venerables Ānanda and Kāmabhū were staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery.[1831]

Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Kāmabhū came out of retreat, went to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him.[1832] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Ānanda:

“Reverend Ānanda, which is it? Is the eye the fetter of sights, or are sights the fetter of the eye? Is the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind the fetter of ideas, or are ideas the fetter of the mind?”

“Reverend Kāmabhū, the eye is not the fetter of sights, nor are sights the fetter of the eye. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them. The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the mind. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.

Suppose there was a black ox and a white ox yoked by a single harness or yoke. Would it be right to say that the black ox is the yoke of the white ox, or the white ox is the yoke of the black ox?”

“No, reverend. The black ox is not the yoke of the white ox, nor is the white ox the yoke of the black ox. The yoke there is the single harness or yoke that they’re yoked by.”

“In the same way, the eye is not the fetter of sights, nor are sights the fetter of the eye. The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the mind. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.”

SN 35.234 With Udāyī Udāyīsutta

At one time the venerables Ānanda and Udāyī were staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery.

Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Udāyī came out of retreat, went to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Ānanda:

“Reverend Ānanda, the Buddha has explained, opened, and revealed in many ways how this body is not-self. Is it possible to explain consciousness in the same way? To teach, assert, establish, clarify, analyze, and reveal how consciousness is not-self?”

“It is possible, Reverend Udāyī.

Does eye consciousness arise dependent on the eye and sights?”

“Yes, reverend.”

“If the cause and reason that gives rise to eye consciousness were to totally and utterly cease without remainder, would eye consciousness still be found?”

“No, reverend.”

“In this way, too, it can be understood how consciousness is not-self.

Does ear … nose … tongue … body … mind consciousness arise dependent on the mind and ideas?”

“Yes, reverend.”

“If the cause and reason that gives rise to mind consciousness were to totally and utterly cease without remainder, would mind consciousness still be found?”

“No, reverend.”

“In this way, too, it can be understood how consciousness is not-self.

Suppose there was a person in need of heartwood. Wandering in search of heartwood, they’d take a sharp axe and enter a forest. There they’d see a big banana trunk, straight and young and grown unskewed. They’d cut it down at the base, cut off the root, cut off the top, and unroll the coiled sheaths. But they wouldn’t even find sapwood, much less heartwood.

In the same way, a mendicant sees these six fields of contact as neither self nor belonging to self. So seeing, they don’t grasp anything in the world.[1833] Not grasping, they’re not anxious. Not being anxious, they personally become extinguished.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.235 The Exposition on Burning Ādittapariyāyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you an exposition of the teaching on burning. Listen …

And what is the exposition of the teaching on burning?

You’d be better off mutilating your eye faculty with a red-hot iron nail, burning, blazing, and glowing, than getting caught up in the features by way of the details in sights known by the eye.[1834] Should consciousness tied to gratification in the features or details continue to remain, and you were to die at that time, it’s possible you would go to one of two destinations: hell or the animal realm. I speak having seen this drawback.

You’d be better off mutilating your ear faculty with a sharp iron spike …

You’d be better off mutilating your nose faculty with a sharp nail cutter …

You’d be better off mutilating your tongue faculty with a sharp razor …

You’d be better off mutilating your body faculty with a sharp spear, burning, blazing, and glowing, than getting caught up in the features by way of the details in touches known by the body. Should consciousness tied to gratification in the features or details continue to remain, and you were to die at that time, it’s possible you would go to one of two destinations: hell or the animal realm. I speak having seen this drawback.

You’d be better off sleeping. For I say that sleep is useless, fruitless, and folly for the living. But while you’re asleep you won’t fall under the sway of such thoughts that would make you create a schism in the Saṅgha.[1835] I speak having seen this drawback.

A learned noble disciple reflects on this: ‘Forget mutilating the eye faculty with a red-hot iron nail, burning, blazing, and glowing! I’d better focus on the fact that the eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact are impermanent. And the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact is also impermanent.

Forget mutilating the ear faculty with a sharp iron spike, burning, blazing, and glowing! I’d better focus on the fact that the ear, sounds, ear consciousness, and ear contact are impermanent. And the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on ear contact is also impermanent.

Forget mutilating the nose faculty with a sharp nail cutter, burning, blazing, and glowing! I’d better focus on the fact that the nose, smells, nose consciousness, and nose contact are impermanent. And the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on nose contact is also impermanent.

Forget mutilating the tongue faculty with a sharp razor, burning, blazing, and glowing! I’d better focus on the fact that the tongue, tastes, tongue consciousness, and tongue contact are impermanent. And the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on tongue contact is also impermanent.

Forget mutilating the body faculty with a sharp spear, burning, blazing, and glowing! I’d better focus on the fact that the body, touches, body consciousness, and body contact are impermanent. And the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on body contact is also impermanent.

Forget sleeping! I’d better focus on the fact that the mind, ideas, mind consciousness, and mind contact are impermanent. And the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact is also impermanent.’

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, sights, eye consciousness, and eye contact. And they grow disillusioned with the painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on eye contact. They grow disillusioned with the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind … painful, pleasant, or neutral feeling that arises dependent on mind contact.

Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

This is the exposition of the teaching on burning.”

SN 35.236 The Simile of Hands and Feet (1st) Paṭhamahatthapādopamasutta

“Mendicants, when there are hands, picking up and putting down are found.[1836] When there are feet, coming and going are found. When there are joints, contracting and extending are found. When there’s a belly, hunger and thirst are found.

In the same way, when there’s an eye, pleasure and pain arise internally conditioned by eye contact. When there’s an ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, pleasure and pain arise internally conditioned by mind contact.

When there are no hands, picking up and putting down aren’t found. When there are no feet, coming and going aren’t found. When there are no joints, contracting and extending aren’t found. When there’s no belly, hunger and thirst aren’t found.

In the same way, when there’s no eye, pleasure and pain don’t arise internally conditioned by eye contact. When there’s no ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, pleasure and pain don’t arise internally conditioned by mind contact.”

SN 35.237 The Simile of Hands and Feet (2nd) Dutiyahatthapādopamasutta

“Mendicants, when there are hands, there’s picking up and putting down. When there are feet, there’s coming and going. When there are joints, there’s contracting and extending. When there’s a belly, there’s hunger and thirst.

In the same way, when there’s an eye, pleasure and pain arise internally conditioned by eye contact. When there’s an ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, pleasure and pain arise internally conditioned by mind contact.

When there are no hands, there’s no picking up and putting down. When there are no feet, there’s no coming and going. When there are no joints, there’s no contracting and extending. When there’s no belly, there’s no hunger and thirst.

In the same way, when there’s no eye, pleasure and pain don’t arise internally conditioned by eye contact. When there’s no ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, pleasure and pain don’t arise internally conditioned by mind contact.”

The Chapter on Sixty Abbreviated Texts

SN 35.168 Desire for the Impermanent Interior Ajjhattaaniccachandasutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire for what is impermanent.[1824] And what is impermanent?

The eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are impermanent: you should give up desire for them. You should give up desire for what is impermanent.”

SN 35.169 Greed for the Impermanent Interior Ajjhattaaniccarāgasutta

“Mendicants, you should give up greed for what is impermanent. And what is impermanent?

The eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are impermanent …”

SN 35.170 Desire and Greed for the Impermanent Interior Ajjhattaaniccachandarāgasutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire and greed for what is impermanent. And what is impermanent?

The eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are impermanent …”

SN 35.171–173 Desire, Etc. for the Suffering Interior Dukkhachandādisutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire … greed … desire and greed for what is suffering. And what is suffering?

The eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are suffering …”

SN 35.174–176 Desire, Etc. for the Not-Self Interior Anattachandādisutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire … greed … desire and greed for what is not-self. And what is not-self?

The eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are not-self …”

SN 35.177–179 Desire, Etc. for the Impermanent Exterior Bāhirāniccachandādisutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire … greed … desire and greed for what is impermanent. And what is impermanent?

Sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are impermanent …”

SN 35.180–182 Desire, Etc. for the Suffering Exterior Bāhiradukkhachandādisutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire … greed … desire and greed for what is suffering. And what is suffering?

Sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are suffering …”

SN 35.183–185 Desire, Etc. for the Not-Self Exterior Bāhirānattachandādisutta

“Mendicants, you should give up desire … greed … desire and greed for what is not-self. And what is not-self?

Sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are not-self …”

SN 35.186 The Interior Was Impermanent in the Past Ajjhattātītāniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the past the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind were impermanent.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.187 The Interior Will Be Impermanent in the Future Ajjhattānāgatāniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the future the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind will be impermanent …”

SN 35.188 The Interior is Impermanent in the Present Ajjhattapaccuppannāniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the present the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are impermanent …”

SN 35.189–191 The Interior as Suffering in the Three Times Ajjhattātītādidukkhasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are suffering …”

SN 35.192–194 The Interior as Not-Self in the Three Times Ajjhattātītādianattasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are not-self …”

SN 35.195–197 The Exterior as Impermanent in the Three Times Bāhirātītādianiccasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are impermanent …”

SN 35.198–200 The Exterior as Suffering in the Three Times Bāhirātītādidukkhasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are suffering …”

SN 35.201–203 The Exterior as Not-Self in the Three Times Bāhirātītādianattasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are not-self …”

SN 35.204 The Interior and What’s Impermanent in the Past Ajjhattātītayadaniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the past the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind were impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. What’s suffering is not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ …”

SN 35.205 The Interior and What’s Impermanent in the Future Ajjhattānāgatayadaniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the future the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind will be impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. …”

SN 35.206 The Interior and What’s Impermanent in the Present Ajjhattapaccuppannayadaniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the present the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. …”

SN 35.207–209 The Interior and What’s Suffering in the Three Times Ajjhattātītādiyaṁdukkhasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are suffering. What’s suffering is not-self …”

SN 35.210–212 The Interior and What’s Not-Self in the Three Times Ajjhattātītādiyadanattasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ …”

SN 35.213–215 The Exterior and What’s Impermanent in the Three Times Bāhirātītādiyadaniccasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are impermanent. What’s impermanent is suffering. …”

SN 35.216–218 The Exterior and What’s Suffering in the Three Times Bāhirātītādiyaṁdukkhasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are suffering. What’s suffering is not-self …”

SN 35.219–221 The Exterior and What’s Not-Self in the Three Times Bāhirātītādiyadanattasutta

“Mendicants, in the past … future … present sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are not-self. And what’s not-self should be truly seen with right understanding like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ …”

SN 35.222 The Interior as Impermanent Ajjhattāyatanaaniccasutta

“Mendicants, the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are impermanent.

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.223 The Interior as Suffering Ajjhattāyatanadukkhasutta

“Mendicants, the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are suffering.

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.224 The Interior as Not-Self Ajjhattāyatanaanattasutta

“Mendicants, the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind are not-self.

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.225 The Exterior as Impermanent Bāhirāyatanaaniccasutta

“Mendicants, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are impermanent.

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.226 The Exterior as Suffering Bāhirāyatanadukkhasutta

“Mendicants, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are suffering.

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.227 The Exterior as Not-Self Bāhirāyatanaanattasutta

“Mendicants, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are not-self.

Seeing this … They understand: ‘… there is nothing further for this place.’”

The Third Fifty

The Chapter on Sanctuary

SN 35.104 Sanctuary from the Yoke Yogakkhemisutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you an exposition of the teaching, an explanation of one who has found sanctuary from the yoke.[1755] Listen …

And what is an exposition of the teaching, an explanation of one who has found sanctuary from the yoke?

There are sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. The Realized One has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. He teaches yoking oneself to meditation for giving them up. That’s why the Realized One is called one who has found sanctuary from the yoke. …[1756]

There are ideas known by the mind, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. The Realized One has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. He teaches yoking oneself to meditation for giving them up. That’s why the Realized One is called one who has found sanctuary from the yoke.

This is an exposition of the teaching, an explanation of one who has found sanctuary from the yoke.”

SN 35.105 Because of Grasping Upādāyasutta

“Mendicants, when what exists, because of grasping what, do pleasure and pain arise in oneself?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“Mendicants, when there’s an eye, because of grasping the eye, pleasure and pain arise in oneself. … When there’s a mind, because of grasping the mind, pleasure and pain arise in oneself.

What do you think, mendicants? Is the eye permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But by not grasping what’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, would pleasure and pain arise in oneself?”

“No, sir.” …

“Is the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But by not grasping what’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, would pleasure and pain arise in oneself?”

“No, sir.”

“Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.106 The Origin of Suffering Dukkhasamudayasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the origin and disappearance of suffering. Listen …

And what, mendicants, is the origin of suffering? Eye consciousness arises dependent on the eye and sights. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. This is the origin of suffering …

Mind consciousness arises dependent on the mind and ideas. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. This is the origin of suffering.

And what is the disappearance of suffering? Eye consciousness arises dependent on the eye and sights. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. When that craving fades away and ceases with no residue left behind, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases, continued existence ceases. When continued existence ceases, rebirth ceases. When rebirth ceases, old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress cease. That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases. This is the disappearance of suffering. …

Mind consciousness arises dependent on the mind and ideas. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. When that craving fades away and ceases with no residue left behind, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases, continued existence ceases. When continued existence ceases, rebirth ceases. When rebirth ceases, old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress cease. That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases. This is the disappearance of suffering.”

SN 35.107 The Origin of the World Lokasamudayasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the origin and disappearance of the world. Listen …

And what, mendicants, is the origin of the world? Eye consciousness arises dependent on the eye and sights. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. Craving is a requirement for grasping. Grasping is a requirement for continued existence. Continued existence is a requirement for rebirth. Rebirth is a requirement for old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress to come to be. This is the origin of the world. …

Mind consciousness arises dependent on the mind and ideas. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. Craving is a requirement for grasping. Grasping is a requirement for continued existence. Continued existence is a requirement for rebirth. Rebirth is a requirement for old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress to come to be. This is the origin of the world.

And what is the disappearance of the world? Eye consciousness arises dependent on the eye and sights. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. When that craving fades away and ceases no residue left behind, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases, continued existence ceases. When continued existence ceases, rebirth ceases. When rebirth ceases, old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress cease. That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases. This is the disappearance of the world. …

Mind consciousness arises dependent on the mind and ideas. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. When that craving fades away and ceases no residue left behind, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases … That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases. This is the disappearance of the world.”

SN 35.108 I’m Better Seyyohamasmisutta

“Mendicants, when what exists, because of grasping what and insisting on what, do people think ‘I’m better’ or ‘I’m equal’ or ‘I’m worse’?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“When there’s an eye, because of grasping the eye and insisting on the eye, people think ‘I’m better’ or ‘I’m equal’ or ‘I’m worse’. …

When there’s a mind, because of grasping the mind and insisting on the mind, people think ‘I’m better’ or ‘I’m equal’ or ‘I’m worse’.

What do you think, mendicants? Is the eye permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But by not grasping what’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, would people think ‘I’m better’ or ‘I’m equal’ or ‘I’m worse’?”

“No, sir.” …

“Is the mind permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But by not grasping what’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, would people think ‘I’m better’ or ‘I’m equal’ or ‘I’m worse’?”

“No, sir.”

“Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

SN 35.109 Things That Tighten Fetters Saṁyojaniyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the things that tighten the fetters, and the fetter.[1757] Listen …

What are the things that tighten the fetters? And what is the fetter? The eye is something that tightens the fetters. The desire and greed for it is the fetter.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is something that tightens the fetters. The desire and greed for it is the fetter. These are called the things that tighten the fetters, and this is the fetter.”

SN 35.110 Things That Fuel Grasping Upādāniyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the things that fuel grasping, and the grasping. Listen …

What are the things that fuel grasping? And what is the grasping? The eye is something that fuels grasping. The desire and greed for it is the grasping.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is something that fuels grasping. The desire and greed for it is the grasping. These are called the things that fuel grasping, and this is the grasping.”

SN 35.111 Complete Understanding of the Interior Ajjhattikāyatanaparijānanasutta

“Mendicants, without directly knowing and completely understanding the eye, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering.[1758]

Without directly knowing and completely understanding the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, without dispassion for it and giving it up, you can’t end suffering.

By directly knowing and completely understanding the eye, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering.

By directly knowing and completely understanding the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, having dispassion for it and giving it up, you can end suffering.”

SN 35.112 Complete Understanding of the Exterior Bāhirāyatanaparijānanasutta

“Mendicants, without directly knowing and completely understanding sights … sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas, without dispassion for them and giving them up, you can’t end suffering.

By directly knowing and completely understanding sights … sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas, having dispassion for them and giving them up, you can end suffering.”

SN 35.113 Listening In Upassutisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying at Ñātika in the brick house.[1759] Then while the Buddha was in private retreat he spoke this exposition of the teaching:

“Eye consciousness arises dependent on the eye and sights. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. Craving is a requirement for grasping. Grasping is a requirement for continued existence. Continued existence is a requirement for rebirth. Rebirth is a requirement for old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress to come to be. That is how this entire mass of suffering originates.

Ear … nose … tongue … body …

Mind consciousness arises dependent on the mind and ideas. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. Craving is a requirement for grasping. Grasping is a requirement for continued existence. Continued existence is a requirement for rebirth. Rebirth is a requirement for old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress to come to be. That is how this entire mass of suffering originates.

Eye consciousness arises dependent on the eye and sights. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. When that craving fades away and ceases no residue left behind, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases, continued existence ceases. When continued existence ceases, rebirth ceases. When rebirth ceases, old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress cease. That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases.

Ear … nose … tongue … body …

Mind consciousness arises dependent on the mind and ideas. The meeting of the three is contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. When that craving fades away and ceases no residue left behind, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases … That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases.”

Now at that time a certain monk was standing listening in on the Buddha. The Buddha saw him and said, “Monk, did you hear that exposition of the teaching?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Learn that exposition of the teaching, memorize it, and remember it. That exposition of the teaching is beneficial and relevant to the fundamentals of the spiritual life.”

The Chapter on Pairs

SN 35.13 Before My Awakening (Interior) Paṭhamapubbesambodhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I thought: ‘What’s the gratification, the drawback, and the escape when it comes to the eye … ear … nose … tongue … body … and mind?’

Then it occurred to me: ‘The pleasure and happiness that arise from the eye: this is its gratification. That the eye is impermanent, suffering, and perishable: this is its drawback. Removing and giving up desire and greed for the eye: this is its escape.

The pleasure and happiness that arise from the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind: this is its gratification. That the mind is impermanent, suffering, and perishable: this is its drawback. Removing and giving up desire and greed for the mind: this is its escape.’

As long as I didn’t truly understand these six interior sense fields’ gratification, drawback, and escape in this way for what they are, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when I did truly understand these six interior sense fields’ gratification, drawback, and escape in this way for what they are, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

SN 35.14 Before My Awakening (Exterior) Dutiyapubbesambodhasutta

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I thought: ‘What’s the gratification, the drawback, and the escape when it comes to sights … sounds … smells … tastes … touches … and ideas?’ …”

SN 35.15 In Search of Gratification (Interior) Paṭhamaassādapariyesanasutta

“Mendicants, I went in search of the eye’s gratification, and I found it. I’ve seen clearly with wisdom the full extent of the eye’s gratification. I went in search of the eye’s drawback, and I found it. I’ve seen clearly with wisdom the full extent of the eye’s drawback. I went in search of escape from the eye, and I found it. I’ve seen clearly with wisdom the full extent of escape from the eye.

I went in search of the ear’s … nose’s … tongue’s … body’s …[1665] mind’s gratification, and I found it. I’ve seen clearly with wisdom the full extent of the mind’s gratification. I went in search of the mind’s drawback, and I found it. I’ve seen clearly with wisdom the full extent of the mind’s drawback. I went in search of escape from the mind, and I found it. I’ve seen clearly with wisdom the full extent of escape from the mind.

As long as I didn’t truly understand these six interior sense fields’ gratification, drawback, and escape for what they are, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening …

But when I did truly understand …

Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

SN 35.16 In Search of Gratification (Exterior) Dutiyaassādapariyesanasutta

“Mendicants, I went in search of the gratification of sights, and I found it. …”

SN 35.17 If There Were No Gratification (Interior) Paṭhamanoceassādasutta

“Mendicants, if there were no gratification in the eye, sentient beings wouldn’t be aroused by it. But since there is gratification in the eye, sentient beings are aroused by it. If the eye had no drawback, sentient beings wouldn’t grow disillusioned with it. But since the eye has a drawback, sentient beings do grow disillusioned with it. If there were no escape from the eye, sentient beings wouldn’t escape from it. But since there is an escape from the eye, sentient beings do escape from it.

If there were no gratification in the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, sentient beings wouldn’t be aroused by it. But since there is gratification in the mind, sentient beings are aroused by it. If the mind had no drawback, sentient beings wouldn’t grow disillusioned with it. But since the mind has a drawback, sentient beings do grow disillusioned with it. If there were no escape from the mind, sentient beings wouldn’t escape from it. But since there is an escape from the mind, sentient beings do escape from it.

As long as sentient beings don’t truly understand these six interior sense fields’ gratification, drawback, and escape for what they are, they haven’t escaped from this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—and they don’t live detached, liberated, with mind free of boundaries.

But when sentient beings truly understand these six interior sense fields’ gratification, drawback, and escape for what they are, they’ve escaped from this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—and they live detached, liberated, with mind free of boundaries.”

SN 35.18 If There Were No Gratification (Exterior) Dutiyanoceassādasutta

“Mendicants, if there were no gratification in sights, sentient beings wouldn’t be aroused by them. …”

SN 35.19 Taking Pleasure (Interior) Paṭhamābhinandasutta

“Mendicants, if you take pleasure in the eye, you take pleasure in suffering. If you take pleasure in suffering, you’re not free from suffering, I say.

If you take pleasure in the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, you take pleasure in suffering. If you take pleasure in suffering, you’re not free from suffering, I say.

If you don’t take pleasure in the eye, you don’t take pleasure in suffering. If you don’t take pleasure in suffering, you’re free from suffering, I say.

If you don’t take pleasure in the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind, you don’t take pleasure in suffering. If you don’t take pleasure in suffering, you’re free from suffering, I say.”

SN 35.20 Taking Pleasure (Exterior) Dutiyābhinandasutta

“Mendicants, if you take pleasure in sights, you take pleasure in suffering. If you take pleasure in suffering, you’re not free from suffering, I say. …”

SN 35.21 The Arising of Suffering (Interior) Paṭhamadukkhuppādasutta

“Mendicants, the arising, continuation, and manifestation and regeneration of the eye is the arising of suffering, the continuation of diseases, and the manifestation of old age and death. The arising, continuation, and manifestation and regeneration of the ear … nose … tongue … body … and mind is the arising of suffering, the continuation of diseases, and the manifestation of old age and death.

The cessation, settling, and disappearance of the eye is the cessation of suffering, the settling of diseases, and the disappearance of old age and death. The cessation, settling, and disappearance of the ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind is the cessation of suffering, the settling of diseases, and the disappearance of old age and death.”

SN 35.22 The Arising of Suffering (Exterior) Dutiyadukkhuppādasutta

“Mendicants, the arising, continuation, and manifestation and regeneration of sights is the arising of suffering, the continuation of diseases, and the manifestation of old age and death. The arising, continuation, and manifestation and regeneration of sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas is the arising of suffering, the continuation of diseases, and the manifestation of old age and death.

The cessation, settling, and disappearance of sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas is the cessation of suffering, the settling of diseases, and the disappearance of old age and death.”

The Chapter on the Explanation of the Hundred and Eight

SN 36.21 With Sīvaka Sīvakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground.

Then the wanderer Moḷiyasīvaka went up to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him.[1909] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, there are some ascetics and brahmins who have this doctrine and view:[1910] ‘Everything this individual person experiences—pleasurable, painful, or neutral—is because of past deeds.’[1911] What does the worthy Gotama say about this?”

“Sīvaka, some feelings stem from bile disorders.[1912] You can know this from your own personal experience, and it is generally deemed to be true. Since this is so, the ascetics and brahmins whose view is that everything an individual person experiences is because of past deeds go beyond personal experience and beyond what is generally deemed to be true. So those ascetics and brahmins are wrong, I say.

Some feelings stem from phlegm disorders … wind disorders … their conjunction … change in weather …[1913] not taking care of yourself …[1914] exertion …[1915] Some feelings are the result of past deeds.[1916] You can know this from your own personal experience, and it is generally deemed to be true.[1917] Since this is so, the ascetics and brahmins whose view is that everything an individual person experiences is because of past deeds go beyond personal experience and beyond what is generally deemed to be true. So those ascetics and brahmins are wrong, I say.”

When he said this, the wanderer Moḷiyasīvaka said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

“Bile, phlegm, and wind,
their conjunction, and the weather,
not taking care of yourself, exertion,
and the result of deeds is the eighth.”

SN 36.22 The Explanation of the Hundred and Eight Aṭṭhasatasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you an exposition of the teaching on the hundred and eight. Listen …

And what is the exposition of the teaching on the hundred and eight? Mendicants, in one explanation I’ve spoken of two feelings. In another explanation I’ve spoken of three feelings, or five, six, eighteen, thirty-six, or a hundred and eight feelings.

And what are the two feelings? Physical and mental. These are called the two feelings.

And what are the three feelings? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings. …

And what are the five feelings? The faculties of pleasure, pain, happiness, sadness, and equanimity. …[1918]

And what are the six feelings? Feeling born of eye contact … ear contact … nose contact … tongue contact … body contact … mind contact. …

And what are the eighteen feelings? There are six preoccupations with happiness, six preoccupations with sadness, and six preoccupations with equanimity. …[1919]

And what are the thirty-six feelings? Six kinds of domestic happiness and six kinds of renunciate happiness. Six kinds of domestic sadness and six kinds of renunciate sadness. Six kinds of domestic equanimity and six kinds of renunciate equanimity. …[1920]

And what are the hundred and eight feelings? Thirty six feelings in the past, future, and present. These are called the hundred and eight feelings.

This is the exposition of the teaching on the hundred and eight.”

SN 36.23 With a Mendicant Aññatarabhikkhusutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?”

“Mendicant, there are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings.

Feeling originates from contact. Craving is the practice that leads to the origin of feeling.

When contact ceases, feeling ceases. The practice that leads to the cessation of feelings is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

The pleasure and happiness that arise from feeling: this is its gratification.

That feeling is impermanent, suffering, and perishable: this is its drawback.

Removing and giving up desire and greed for feeling: this is its escape.”

SN 36.24 Before Pubbasutta

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I thought:[1921] ‘What is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?’

Then it occurred to me: ‘There are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings. Feeling originates from contact. Craving is the practice that leads to the origin of feeling … Removing and giving up desire and greed for feeling: this is its escape.’”

SN 36.25 Knowledge Ñāṇasutta

“‘These are the feelings.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.[1922]

‘This is the origin of feeling.’ …

‘This is the practice that leads to the origin of feeling.’ …

‘This is the cessation of feeling.’ …

‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling.’ …

‘This is the gratification of feeling.’ …

‘This is the drawback of feeling.’ …

‘This is the escape from feeling.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.”

SN 36.26 With Several Mendicants Sambahulabhikkhusutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?”

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings.

Feeling originates from contact. Craving is the practice that leads to the origin of feeling.

When contact ceases, feeling ceases. …

Removing and giving up desire and greed for feeling: this is its escape.”

SN 36.27 Ascetics and Brahmins (1st) Paṭhamasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling.

There are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand these three feelings’ gratification, drawback, and escape.[1923] I don’t deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables don’t realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and don’t live having realized it with their own insight in this very life.

There are ascetics and brahmins who do truly understand these three feelings’ gratification, drawback, and escape. I deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and live having realized it with their own insight.”

SN 36.28 Ascetics and Brahmins (2nd) Dutiyasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling.

There are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand these three feelings’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. …

There are ascetics and brahmins who do truly understand …”

SN 36.29 Ascetics and Brahmins (3rd) Tatiyasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t understand feeling, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. …

There are ascetics and brahmins who do understand …”

SN 36.30 Plain Version Suddhikasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings.[1924] What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings. These are the three feelings.”

SN 36.31 Not of the Flesh Nirāmisasutta

“Mendicants, there is rapture of the flesh, rapture not of the flesh, and rapture even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.[1925]

There is pleasure of the flesh, pleasure not of the flesh, and pleasure even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.

There is equanimity of the flesh, equanimity not of the flesh, and equanimity even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.

There is liberation of the flesh, liberation not of the flesh, and liberation even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.

And what is rapture of the flesh? There are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds … Smells … Tastes … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation. The rapture that arises from these five kinds of sensual stimulation is called rapture of the flesh.

And what is rapture not of the flesh? It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is called rapture not of the flesh.

And what is rapture even more spiritual than that not of the flesh?[1926] When a mendicant who has ended the defilements reviews their mind free from greed, hate, and delusion, rapture arises. This is called rapture even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.

And what is pleasure of the flesh? Mendicants, there are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds … Smells … Tastes … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation. The pleasure and happiness that arise from these five kinds of sensual stimulation is called pleasure of the flesh.

And what is pleasure not of the flesh? It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. And with the fading away of rapture, they enter and remain in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’ This is called pleasure not of the flesh.

And what is pleasure even more spiritual than that not of the flesh? When a mendicant who has ended the defilements reviews their mind free from greed, hate, and delusion, pleasure and happiness arises. This is called pleasure even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.

And what is equanimity of the flesh? There are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds … Smells … Tastes … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation. The equanimity that arises from these five kinds of sensual stimulation is called equanimity of the flesh.

And what is equanimity not of the flesh? It’s when, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, a mendicant enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. This is called equanimity not of the flesh.

And what is equanimity even more spiritual than that not of the flesh? When a mendicant who has ended the defilements reviews their mind free from greed, hate, and delusion, equanimity arises. This is called equanimity even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.

And what is liberation of the flesh? Liberation connected with form is liberation of the flesh.[1927]

And what is liberation not of the flesh? Liberation connected with the formless is liberation not of the flesh.

And what is liberation even more spiritual than that not of the flesh? When a mendicant who has ended the defilements reviews their mind free from greed, hate, and delusion, liberation arises. This is called liberation even more spiritual than that not of the flesh.”

The Linked Discourses on feelings are complete.

The Chapter on In Private

SN 36.11 In Private Rahogatasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Just now, sir, as I was in private retreat this thought came to mind. The Buddha has spoken of three feelings. Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings the Buddha has spoken of.

But the Buddha has also said: ‘Suffering includes whatever is felt.’ What was the Buddha referring to when he said this?”

“Good, good, mendicant![1897] I have spoken of these three feelings. Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings I have spoken of.

But I have also said: ‘Suffering includes whatever is felt.’

When I said this I was referring to the impermanence of conditions, to the fact that conditions are liable to end, vanish, fade away, cease, and perish.

But I have also explained the progressive cessation of activities.[1898] For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has ceased. For someone who has attained the second absorption, the placing of the mind and keeping it connected have ceased. For someone who has attained the third absorption, rapture has ceased. For someone who has attained the fourth absorption, breathing has ceased. For someone who has attained the dimension of infinite space, the perception of form has ceased. For someone who has attained the dimension of infinite consciousness, the perception of the dimension of infinite space has ceased. For someone who has attained the dimension of nothingness, the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness has ceased. For someone who has attained the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, the perception of the dimension of nothingness has ceased. For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have ceased. For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have ceased.

And I have also explained the progressive settling of activities. For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has stilled. For someone who has attained the second absorption, the placing of the mind and keeping it connected have stilled. … For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have stilled. For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have stilled.

There are these six levels of tranquility.[1899] For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the second absorption, the placing of the mind and keeping it connected have been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the third absorption, rapture has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the fourth absorption, breathing has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have been tranquilized. For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have been tranquilized.”

SN 36.12 In the Atmosphere (1st) Paṭhamaākāsasutta

“Mendicants, various winds blow in the atmosphere. Winds blow from the east, the west, the north, and the south. There are winds that are dusty and dustless, cool and warm, weak and strong.

In the same way, various feelings arise in this body: pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings.[1900]

There are many and various
winds that blow in the atmosphere.
From the east they come, also the west,
the north, and then the south.

They are dusty and dustless,
cool and sometimes warm,
strong and weak;
these are the different gales that blow.

So too, in this body
feelings arise,
pleasant and painful,
and those that are neutral.

But when a mendicant is keen,
not neglecting situational awareness,
that astute person
understands all feelings.

Completely understanding feelings,
they’re without defilements in this very life.
That knowledge master is firm in principle;
when their body breaks up, they can’t be reckoned.”

SN 36.13 In the Atmosphere (2nd) Dutiyaākāsasutta

“Mendicants, various winds blow in the atmosphere. Winds blow from the east, the west, the north, and the south. There are winds that are dusty and dustless, cool and warm, weak and strong.

In the same way, various feelings arise in this body: pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings.”

SN 36.14 A Guest House Agārasutta

“Mendicants, suppose there was a guest house. Lodgers come from the east, west, north, and south. Aristocrats, brahmins, peasants, and menials all stay there.

In the same way, various feelings arise in this body: pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings. Also pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings of the flesh arise.[1901] Also pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings not of the flesh arise.”

SN 36.15 With Ānanda (1st) Paṭhamaānandasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha … sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?”

“Ānanda, there are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings.

Feeling originates from contact. When contact ceases, feeling ceases.

The practice that leads to the cessation of feelings is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

The pleasure and happiness that arise from feeling: this is its gratification.

That feeling is impermanent, suffering, and perishable: this is its drawback.

Removing and giving up desire and greed for feeling: this is its escape.

But I have also explained the progressive cessation of activities. For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has ceased. … For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have ceased. For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have ceased.

And I have also explained the progressive settling of activities. For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has stilled. … For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have stilled. For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have stilled.

And I have also explained the progressive tranquilizing of activities. For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has been tranquilized. … For someone who has attained the dimension of infinite space, the perception of form has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the dimension of infinite consciousness, the perception of the dimension of infinite space has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the dimension of nothingness, the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, the perception of the dimension of nothingness has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have been tranquilized. For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have been tranquilized.”

SN 36.16 With Ānanda (2nd) Dutiyaānandasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Ānanda, what is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, Ānanda, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied. The Buddha said this:

“Ānanda, there are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings. …

For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have been tranquilized.”

SN 36.17 With Several Mendicants (1st) Paṭhamasambahulasutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?”

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings.

Feeling originates from contact. When contact ceases, feeling ceases.

The practice that leads to the cessation of feelings is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

The pleasure and happiness that arise from feeling: this is its gratification. That feeling is impermanent, suffering, and perishable: this is its drawback. Removing and giving up desire and greed for feeling: this is its escape.

But I have also explained the progressive cessation of activities. … For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has ceased. … For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have ceased. And I have also explained the progressive settling of activities. For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has stilled. … For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have stilled. There are these six levels of tranquility. For someone who has attained the first absorption, speech has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the second absorption, the placing of the mind and keeping it connected have been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the third absorption, rapture has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the fourth absorption, breathing has been tranquilized. For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have been tranquilized.

For a mendicant who has ended the defilements, greed, hate, and delusion have been tranquilized.”

SN 36.18 With Several Mendicants (2nd) Dutiyasambahulasutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha … The Buddha said to them:

“Mendicants, what is feeling? What’s the origin of feeling? What’s the cessation of feeling? What’s the practice that leads to the cessation of feeling? And what is feeling’s gratification, drawback, and escape?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. These are called feelings. …”

(Tell in full as in the previous discourse.)

SN 36.19 With Pañcakaṅga Pañcakaṅgasutta

Then the chamberlain Pañcakaṅga went up to Venerable Udāyī, bowed, sat down to one side, and asked him,[1902] “Sir, how many feelings has the Buddha spoken of?”

“Chamberlain, the Buddha has spoken of three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral. The Buddha has spoken of these three feelings.”

When he said this, Pañcakaṅga said to Udāyī, “Sir, Udāyī, the Buddha hasn’t spoken of three feelings. He’s spoken of two feelings: pleasant and painful. The Buddha said that neutral feeling is included as a peaceful and subtle kind of pleasure.”

For a second time, Udāyī said to him, “The Buddha hasn’t spoken of two feelings, he’s spoken of three.”

For a second time, Pañcakaṅga said to Udāyī, “The Buddha hasn’t spoken of three feelings, he’s spoken of two.”

And for a third time, Udāyī said to him, “The Buddha hasn’t spoken of two feelings, he’s spoken of three.”

And for a third time, Pañcakaṅga said to Udāyī, “The Buddha hasn’t spoken of three feelings, he’s spoken of two.”

But neither was able to persuade the other.

Venerable Ānanda heard this discussion between Udāyī and Pañcakaṅga. He went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side,[1903] and informed the Buddha of all they had discussed.

“Ānanda, the explanation by the mendicant Udāyī, which the chamberlain Pañcakaṅga didn’t agree with, was quite correct. But the explanation by Pañcakaṅga, which Udāyī didn’t agree with, was also quite correct.

In one explanation I’ve spoken of two feelings. In another explanation I’ve spoken of three feelings, or five, six, eighteen, thirty-six, or a hundred and eight feelings.[1904]

I’ve explained the teaching in all these different ways. This being so, you can expect that those who don’t concede, approve, or agree with what has been well spoken will fight, quarrel, and dispute, continually wounding each other with barbed words.

I’ve explained the teaching in all these different ways. This being so, you can expect that those who do concede, approve, or agree with what has been well spoken will live in harmony, appreciating each other, without dispute, blending like milk and water, and regarding each other with kindly eyes.

There are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation. The pleasure and happiness that arise from these five kinds of sensual stimulation is called sensual pleasure. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience.[1905] But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.[1906]

And what is that pleasure? It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, a mendicant enters and remains in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when, with the fading away of rapture, a mendicant enters and remains in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’ This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, a mendicant enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.[1907] This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the ending of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enters and remains in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. This is a pleasure that is finer than that. There are those who might say that this is the highest pleasure and happiness that sentient beings experience. But I don’t grant them that. Why is that? Because there is another pleasure that is finer than that.

And what is that pleasure? It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. This is a pleasure that is finer than that.[1908]

It’s possible that wanderers of other religions might say: ‘The ascetic Gotama spoke of the cessation of perception and feeling, and he includes it in happiness. What’s up with that?’

When wanderers of other religions say this, you should say to them: ‘Reverends, when the Buddha describes what’s included in happiness, he’s not just referring to pleasant feeling. The Realized One describes pleasure as included in happiness wherever it is found, and in whatever context.’”

SN 36.20 A Mendicant Bhikkhusutta

“Mendicants, in one explanation I’ve spoken of two feelings. In another explanation I’ve spoken of three feelings, or five, six, eighteen, thirty-six, or a hundred and eight feelings.

I’ve taught the Dhamma with all these explanations. This being so, you can expect that those who don’t concede, approve, or agree with what has been well spoken will fight, quarrel, and dispute, continually wounding each other with barbed words.

I’ve taught the Dhamma with all these explanations. This being so, you can expect that those who do concede, approve, or agree with what has been well spoken will live in harmony, appreciating each other, without dispute, blending like milk and water, and regarding each other with kindly eyes.

There are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. …

It’s possible that wanderers of other religions might say: ‘The ascetic Gotama spoke of the cessation of perception and feeling, and he includes it in happiness. What’s up with that?’

Mendicants, when wanderers of other religions say this, you should say to them: ‘Reverends, when the Buddha describes what’s included in happiness, he’s not just referring to pleasant feeling. The Realized One describes pleasure as included in happiness wherever it is found, and in whatever context.’”

The Chapter with Verses

SN 36.1 Immersion Samādhisutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings.[1883] What three?

Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings.

Stilled, aware,[1884]
a mindful disciple of the Buddha
understands feelings,
the cause of feelings,

where they cease,
and the path that leads to their ending.
With the ending of feelings, a mendicant
is hungerless, quenched.”[1885]

SN 36.2 Pleasure Sukhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three?

Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings.

Whether it’s pleasant or painful,
as well as what’s neutral,
whatever there is that is felt
internally and externally:

having known, ‘this is suffering,
deceptive, breaking apart’,[1886]
seeing feelings vanish with every contact,
that’s how they become free of desire for them.”

SN 36.3 Giving Up Pahānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three?

Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling.

The underlying tendency to greed should be given up when it comes to pleasant feeling. The underlying tendency to aversion should be given up when it comes to painful feeling. The underlying tendency to ignorance should be given up when it comes to neutral feeling.[1887]

When a mendicant has given up these underlying tendencies, they’re called a mendicant without underlying tendencies, who sees rightly, has cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit has made an end of suffering.

When you feel pleasure
without understanding feeling,
the underlying tendency to greed is there,
if you don’t see the escape.

When you feel pain
without understanding feeling,
the underlying tendency to aversion is there,
if you don’t see the escape.

As for that peaceful, neutral feeling:
he of vast wisdom has taught
that if you relish it,
you’re still not released from suffering.

But when a mendicant is keen,
not neglecting situational awareness,
that astute person
understands all feelings.

Completely understanding feelings,
they’re without defilements in this very life.
That knowledge master is firm in principle;
when their body breaks up, they can’t be reckoned.”

SN 36.4 The Abyss Pātālasutta

“Mendicants, when an unlearned ordinary person says that there’s an abyss under the ocean,[1888] they’re speaking of something that doesn’t exist.

‘Abyss’ is a term for painful physical feelings.

When an unlearned ordinary person experiences painful physical feelings they sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion. They’re called an unlearned ordinary person who hasn’t stood up in the abyss and has found no footing.

When a learned noble disciple experiences painful physical feelings they don’t sorrow or wail or lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion. They’re called a learned noble disciple who has stood up in the abyss and found a footing.

If you can’t abide
those painful physical feelings
that arise and sap your vitality;
if you tremble at their touch,

weeping and wailing,
a weakling lacking strength—
you won’t stand up in the abyss
and find a footing.

If you can endure
those painful physical feelings
that arise and sap your vitality;
if you don’t tremble at their touch—
you stand up in the abyss
and find a footing.”

SN 36.5 Should Be Seen Daṭṭhabbasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three?

Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling.

Pleasant feeling should be seen as suffering. Painful feeling should be seen as a dart. Neutral feeling should be seen as impermanent.

When a mendicant has seen these three feelings in this way, they’re called a mendicant who sees rightly, has cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit has made an end of suffering.

A mendicant who sees pleasure as pain,
and suffering as a dart,
and that peaceful, neutral feeling
as impermanent

sees rightly;
they completely understand feelings.
Completely understanding feelings,
they’re without defilements in this very life.
That knowledge master is firm in principle;
when their body breaks up, they can’t be reckoned.”

SN 36.6 An Arrow Sallasutta

“Mendicants, an unlearned ordinary person feels pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings. A learned noble disciple also feels pleasant, painful, and neutral feelings. What, then, is the difference between a learned noble disciple and an ordinary unlearned person?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“When an unlearned ordinary person experiences painful physical feelings they sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion. They experience two feelings: physical and mental.

It’s like a person who is struck with an arrow, only to be struck with a second arrow. That person experiences the feeling of two arrows.

In the same way, when an unlearned ordinary person experiences painful physical feelings they sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion. They experience two feelings: physical and mental.

When they’re touched by painful feeling, they resist it. The underlying tendency for aversion toward painful feeling underlies that.

When touched by painful feeling they look forward to enjoying sensual pleasures. Why is that? Because an unlearned ordinary person doesn’t understand any escape from painful feeling apart from sensual pleasures. Since they look forward to enjoying sensual pleasures, the underlying tendency to greed for pleasant feeling underlies that.

They don’t truly understand feelings’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. The underlying tendency to ignorance about neutral feeling underlies that.

If they feel a pleasant feeling, they feel it attached. If they feel a painful feeling, they feel it attached. If they feel a neutral feeling, they feel it attached.

They’re called an unlearned ordinary person who is attached to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They are attached to suffering, I say.[1889]

When a learned noble disciple experiences painful physical feelings they don’t sorrow or wail or lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion. They experience one feeling: physical, not mental.

It’s like a person who is struck with an arrow, but was not struck with a second arrow. That person would experience the feeling of one arrow.

In the same way, when a learned noble disciple experiences painful physical feelings they don’t sorrow or wail or lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion. They experience one feeling: physical, not mental.

When they’re touched by painful feeling, they don’t resist it. There’s no underlying tendency for aversion toward painful feeling underlying that.

When touched by painful feeling they don’t look forward to enjoying sensual pleasures. Why is that? Because a learned noble disciple understands an escape from painful feeling apart from sensual pleasures. Since they don’t look forward to enjoying sensual pleasures, there’s no underlying tendency to greed for pleasant feeling underlying that.

They truly understand feelings’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. There’s no underlying tendency to ignorance about neutral feeling underlying that.

If they feel a pleasant feeling, they feel it detached. If they feel a painful feeling, they feel it detached. If they feel a neutral feeling, they feel it detached.

They’re called a learned noble disciple who is detached from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They are detached from suffering, I say.

This is the difference between a learned noble disciple and an unlearned ordinary person.

A wise and learned person does not not feel[1890]
the feeling of pleasure and pain.
This is the great difference of skill
between the attentive one and the ordinary.

A learned person who has appraised the teaching
discerns this world and the next.
Desirable things don’t disturb their mind,
nor are they repelled by the undesirable.

Both favoring and opposing
are cleared and ended, and are no more.
Knowing the stainless, sorrowless state,
they who have gone beyond rebirth understand rightly.”

SN 36.7 The Infirmary (1st) Paṭhamagelaññasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.[1891]

Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat and went to the infirmary, where he sat down on the seat spread out,[1892] and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, a mendicant should await their time mindful and aware.[1893] This is my instruction to you.

And how is a mendicant mindful?[1894] It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[1895] They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … They meditate observing an aspect of the mind … They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant is mindful.

And how is a mendicant aware? It’s when a mendicant acts with situational awareness when going out and coming back; when looking ahead and aside; when bending and extending the limbs; when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes; when eating, drinking, chewing, and tasting; when urinating and defecating; when walking, standing, sitting, sleeping, waking, speaking, and keeping silent. That’s how a mendicant acts with situational awareness. A mendicant should await their time mindful and aware. This is my instruction to you.

While a mendicant is meditating like this—mindful, aware, diligent, keen, and resolute—if pleasant feelings arise, they understand: ‘A pleasant feeling has arisen in me. That’s dependent, not independent. Dependent on what? Dependent on my own body. But this body is impermanent, conditioned, dependently originated. So how could a pleasant feeling be permanent, since it has arisen dependent on a body that is impermanent, conditioned, and dependently originated?’ They meditate observing impermanence, vanishing, dispassion, cessation, and letting go in the body and pleasant feeling. As they do so, they give up the underlying tendency to greed for the body and pleasant feeling.

While a mendicant is meditating like this—mindful, aware, diligent, keen, and resolute—if painful feelings arise, they understand: ‘A painful feeling has arisen in me. That’s dependent, not independent. Dependent on what? Dependent on my own body. But this body is impermanent, conditioned, dependently originated. So how could a painful feeling be permanent, since it has arisen dependent on a body that is impermanent, conditioned, and dependently originated?’ They meditate observing impermanence, vanishing, dispassion, cessation, and letting go in the body and painful feeling. As they do so, they give up the underlying tendency to aversion toward the body and painful feeling.

While a mendicant is meditating like this—mindful, aware, diligent, keen, and resolute—if neutral feelings arise, they understand: ‘A neutral feeling has arisen in me. That’s dependent, not independent. Dependent on what? Dependent on my own body. But this body is impermanent, conditioned, dependently originated. So how could a neutral feeling be permanent, since it has arisen dependent on a body that is impermanent, conditioned, and dependently originated?’ They meditate observing impermanence, vanishing, dispassion, cessation, and letting go in the body and neutral feeling. As they do so, they give up the underlying tendency to ignorance toward the body and neutral feeling.

If they feel a pleasant feeling, they understand that it’s impermanent, that they’re not attached to it, and that they don’t take pleasure in it. If they feel a painful feeling, they understand that it’s impermanent, that they’re not attached to it, and that they don’t take pleasure in it. If they feel a neutral feeling, they understand that it’s impermanent, that they’re not attached to it, and that they don’t take pleasure in it.

If they feel a pleasant feeling, they feel it detached. If they feel a painful feeling, they feel it detached. If they feel a neutral feeling, they feel it detached.

Feeling the end of the body draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of the body draw close.’ Feeling the end of life draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of life draw close.’ They understand: ‘When my body breaks up and my life has come to an end, everything that’s felt, since I no longer take pleasure in it, will become cool right here.’

Suppose an oil lamp depended on oil and a wick to burn. As the oil and the wick are used up, it would be extinguished due to not being fed.

In the same way, feeling the end of the body draw close, a mendicant understands: ‘I feel the end of the body draw close.’ Feeling the end of life draw close, a mendicant understands: ‘I feel the end of life draw close.’ They understand: ‘When my body breaks up and my life is over, everything that’s felt, since I no longer take pleasure in it, will become cool right here.’”

SN 36.8 The Infirmary (2nd) Dutiyagelaññasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.

Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat and went to the infirmary, where he sat down on the seat spread out, and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, a mendicant should await their time mindful and aware. This is my instruction to you.

And how is a mendicant mindful? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … They meditate observing an aspect of the mind … They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant is mindful.

And how is a mendicant aware? It’s when a mendicant acts with situational awareness when going out and coming back; when looking ahead and aside; when bending and extending the limbs; when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes; when eating, drinking, chewing, and tasting; when urinating and defecating; when walking, standing, sitting, sleeping, waking, speaking, and keeping silent. That’s how a mendicant is aware.

A mendicant should await their time mindful and aware. This is my instruction to you.

While a mendicant is meditating like this—mindful, aware, diligent, keen, and resolute—if pleasant feelings arise, they understand: ‘A pleasant feeling has arisen in me. That’s dependent, not independent. Dependent on what? Dependent on this very contact. But this contact is impermanent, conditioned, dependently originated. So how could a pleasant feeling be permanent, since it has arisen dependent on contact that is impermanent, conditioned, and dependently originated?’ They meditate observing impermanence, vanishing, dispassion, cessation, and letting go in contact and pleasant feeling. As they do so, they give up the underlying tendency for greed for contact and pleasant feeling.

While a mendicant is meditating like this—mindful, aware, diligent, keen, and resolute—if painful feelings arise … if neutral feelings arise, they understand: ‘A neutral feeling has arisen in me. That’s dependent, not independent. Dependent on what? Dependent on this very contact.’

(Tell in full as in the previous discourse.)

They understand: ‘When my body breaks up and my life is over, everything that’s felt, since I no longer take pleasure in it, will become cool right here.’

Suppose an oil lamp depended on oil and a wick to burn. As the oil and the wick are used up, it would be extinguished due to not being fed.

In the same way, feeling the end of the body draw close, a mendicant understands: ‘I feel the end of the body draw close.’ Feeling the end of life draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of life draw close.’ They understand: ‘When my body breaks up and my life is over, everything that’s felt, since I no longer take pleasure in it, will become cool right here.’”

SN 36.9 Impermanent Aniccasutta

“Mendicants, these three feelings are impermanent, conditioned, dependently originated, liable to end, vanish, fade away, and cease. What three?

Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings that are impermanent, conditioned, dependently originated, liable to end, vanish, fade away, and cease.”

SN 36.10 Rooted in Contact Phassamūlakasutta

“Mendicants, these three feelings are born, rooted, sourced, and dependent on contact. What three?

Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling.

Pleasant feeling arises dependent on a contact to be experienced as pleasant.[1896] With the cessation of that contact to be experienced as pleasant, the corresponding pleasant feeling ceases and stops. Painful feeling arises dependent on a contact to be experienced as painful. With the cessation of that contact to be experienced as painful, the corresponding painful feeling ceases and stops. Neutral feeling arises dependent on a contact to be experienced as neutral. With the cessation of that contact to be experienced as neutral, the corresponding neutral feeling ceases and stops.

When you rub two sticks together, heat is generated and fire is produced. But when you part the sticks and lay them aside, any corresponding heat ceases and stops.

In the same way, these three feelings are born, rooted, sourced, and dependent on contact. The appropriate feeling arises dependent on the corresponding contact. When the corresponding contact ceases, the appropriate feeling ceases.”

The Chapter on Powers

SN 37.25 Assured Visāradasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five powers of a lady. What five? Attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior. These are the five powers of a lady. A lady living at home with these five qualities is self-assured.”[1934]

SN 37.26 Under Her Thumb Pasayhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five powers of a lady. What five? Attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior. These are the five powers of a lady. A lady living at home with these five powers has her husband under her thumb.”[1935]

SN 37.27 Mastered Abhibhuyyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five powers of a lady. What five? Attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior. These are the five powers of a lady. A lady with these five powers lives having mastered her husband.”[1936]

SN 37.28 One Ekasutta

“Mendicants, by means of one power a man lives having mastered a lady. By means of what one power? When a lady has been mastered by the power of authority, her powers of attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior do not avail her.”[1937]

SN 37.29 In That Respect Aṅgasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five powers of a lady. What five?

Attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior.

A lady who has the power of attractiveness but not the power of wealth is incomplete in that respect. But when she has the power of attractiveness and the power of wealth she’s complete in that respect.

A lady who has the powers of attractiveness and wealth, but not the power of relatives is incomplete in that respect. But when she has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, and relatives she’s complete in that respect.

A lady who has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, and relatives, but not the power of children is incomplete in that respect. But when she has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, relatives, and children she’s complete in that respect.

A lady who has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, relatives, and children, but not the power of ethical behavior is incomplete in that respect. But when she has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior she’s complete in that respect.

These are the five powers of a lady.”

SN 37.30 They Send Her Away Nāsentisutta

“Mendicants, there are these five powers of a lady. What five?

Attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior.

If a lady has the power of attractiveness but not that of ethical behavior, the family will send her away, they won’t accommodate her.

If a lady has the powers of attractiveness and wealth but not that of ethical behavior, the family will send her away, they won’t accommodate her.

If a lady has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, and relatives, but not that of ethical behavior, the family will send her away, they won’t accommodate her.

If a lady has the powers of attractiveness, wealth, relatives, and children, but not that of ethical behavior, the family will send her away, they won’t accommodate her.

If a lady has the power of ethical behavior but not that of attractiveness, the family will accommodate her, they won’t send her away.

If a lady has the power of ethical behavior but not that of wealth, the family will accommodate her, they won’t send her away.

If a lady has the power of ethical behavior but not that of relatives, the family will accommodate her, they won’t send her away.

If a lady has the power of ethical behavior but not that of children, the family will accommodate her, they won’t send her away.

These are the five powers of a lady.”

SN 37.31 Cause Hetusutta

“Mendicants, there are these five powers of a lady. What five? Attractiveness, wealth, relatives, children, and ethical behavior.

It is not because of the powers of attractiveness, wealth, relatives, or children that ladies, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It is because of the power of ethical behavior that ladies, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

These are the five powers of a lady.”

SN 37.32 Things Ṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, there are five things that are hard to get for ladies who have not made merit. What five?

‘May I be born into a suitable family!’ This is the first thing.

‘Having been born in a suitable family, may I marry into a suitable family!’ This is the second thing.

‘Having been born in a suitable family and married into a suitable family, may I live at home without a co-wife!’[1938] This is the third thing.

‘Having been born in a suitable family, and married into a suitable family, and living at home without a co-wife, may I have children!’ This is the fourth thing.

‘Having been born in a suitable family, and married into a suitable family, and living at home without a co-wife, and having had children, may I live having mastered my husband!’ This is the fifth thing.

These are the five things that are hard to get for ladies who have not made merit.

There are five things that are easy to get for ladies who have made merit. What five?

‘May I be born into a suitable family!’ This is the first thing.

‘Having been born into a suitable family, may I marry into a suitable family!’ This is the second thing.

‘Having been born into a suitable family and married into a suitable family, may I live at home without a co-wife!’ This is the third thing.

‘Having been born into a suitable family, and married into a suitable family, and living at home without a co-wife, may I have children!’ This is the fourth thing.

‘Having been born into a suitable family, and married into a suitable family, and living at home without a co-wife, and having had children, may I live having mastered my husband!’ This is the fifth thing.

These are the five things that are easy to get for ladies who have made merit.”

SN 37.33 Living With Self-Assurance Pañcasīlavisāradasutta

“Mendicants, a lady living at home with five qualities is self-assured. What five? She doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lady living at home with these five qualities is self-assured.”

SN 37.34 Growth Vaḍḍhīsutta

“Mendicants, a female noble disciple who grows in five ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life. What five? She grows in faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. A female noble disciple who grows in these five ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life.

When she grows in faith and ethics,
wisdom, and both generosity and learning—
a virtuous laywoman such as she
takes on what is essential for herself in this life.”

The Linked Discourses on ladies are complete.

First Chapter of Abbreviated Texts

SN 37.1 A Lady Mātugāmasutta

“Mendicants, when a lady has five factors she is extremely undesirable to a man.[1928] What five? She’s not attractive, wealthy, or ethical; she’s idle, and she doesn’t beget children. When a lady has these five factors she is extremely undesirable to a man.

When a lady has five factors she is extremely desirable to a man. What five? She’s attractive, wealthy, and ethical; she’s deft and tireless, and she begets children. When a lady has these five factors she is extremely desirable to a man.”[1929]

SN 37.2 A Man Purisasutta

“Mendicants, when a man has five factors he is extremely undesirable to a lady. What five? He’s not attractive, wealthy, or ethical; he’s idle, and he doesn’t beget children. When a man has these five factors he is extremely undesirable to a lady.

When a man has five factors he is extremely desirable to a lady. What five? He’s attractive, wealthy, and ethical; he’s deft and tireless, and he begets children. When a man has these five factors he is extremely desirable to a lady.”

SN 37.3 Particular Suffering Āveṇikadukkhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five kinds of suffering that particularly apply to ladies. They’re undergone by ladies and not by men.[1930] What five?

Firstly, a lady, while still young, goes to live with her husband’s family and is separated from her relatives.[1931] This is the first kind of suffering that particularly applies to ladies.

Furthermore, a lady undergoes the menstrual cycle.[1932] This is the second kind of suffering that particularly applies to ladies.

Furthermore, a lady undergoes pregnancy. This is the third kind of suffering that particularly applies to ladies.

Furthermore, a lady gives birth. This is the fourth kind of suffering that particularly applies to ladies.

Furthermore, a lady provides services for a man.[1933] This is the fifth kind of suffering that particularly applies to ladies.

These are the five kinds of suffering that particularly apply to ladies. They’re undergone by ladies and not by men.”

SN 37.4 Three Qualities Tīhidhammehisutta

“Mendicants, when ladies have three qualities, when their body breaks up, after death, they are mostly reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. What three?

A lady lives at home with heart full of the stain of stinginess in the morning, jealousy in the afternoon, and sexual desire in the evening.

When ladies possess these three qualities, when their body breaks up, after death, they are mostly reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.”

SN 37.5 Irritable Kodhanasutta

Then Venerable Anuruddha went up to the Buddha, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sometimes, sir, with my clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, I see that a female—when her body breaks up, after death—is reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. How many qualities do ladies have so that they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell?”

“Anuruddha, when ladies have five qualities, when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. What five?

They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, irritable, and witless.

When ladies possess these five qualities, when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.”

SN 37.6 Acrimony Upanāhīsutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, acrimonious, and witless. …”

SN 37.7 Jealous Issukīsutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, jealous, and witless. …”

SN 37.8 Stingy Maccharīsutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, stingy, and witless. …”

SN 37.9 Adultery Aticārīsutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, adulterous, and witless. …”

SN 37.10 Unethical Dussīlasutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, unethical, and witless. …”

SN 37.11 Unlearned Appassutasutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, unlearned, and witless. …”

SN 37.12 Lazy Kusītasutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, lazy, and witless. …”

SN 37.13 Unmindful Muṭṭhassatisutta

“… They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, unmindful, and witless. …”

SN 37.14 Five Threats Pañcaverasutta

“Anuruddha, when ladies have five qualities, when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. When ladies possess these five qualities, when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.”

The Chapter with Jambukhādaka

SN 38.1 A Question About Extinguishment Nibbānapañhāsutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta was staying in the land of the Magadhans near the little village of Nālaka.[1939] Then the wanderer Jambukhādaka went up to Venerable Sāriputta and exchanged greetings with him.[1940] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Sāriputta:

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘extinguishment’.[1941] What is extinguishment?”

“Reverend, the ending of greed, hate, and delusion is called extinguishment.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for realizing this extinguishment?”

“There is, reverend.”

“Well, what is it?”

“It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the path, the practice, for realizing this extinguishment.”

“Reverend, this is a fine path, a fine practice, for realizing this extinguishment. Just this much is enough for diligence.”

SN 38.2 A Question About Perfection Arahattapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘perfection’. What is perfection?”[1942]

“Reverend, the ending of greed, hate, and delusion is called perfection.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for realizing this perfection?”

“There is, reverend.”

“Well, what is it?”

“It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the path, the practice, for realizing this perfection.”

“Reverend, this is a fine path, a fine practice, for realizing this perfection. Just this much is enough for diligence.”

SN 38.3 Principled Speech Dhammavādīpañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, who in the world have principled speech? Who in the world practice well? Who are the holy ones in the world?”

“Reverend, those who teach principles for giving up greed, hate, and delusion have principled speech in the world.[1943] Those who practice for giving up greed, hate, and delusion are practicing well in the world. Those who have given up greed, hate, and delusion—so they’re cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, obliterated, and unable to arise in the future—are holy ones in the world.”[1944]

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for giving up that greed, hate, and delusion?”

“There is, reverend.”

“Well, what is it?”

“It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the path, this is the practice for giving up that greed, hate, and delusion.”

“This is a fine path, a fine practice, for giving up greed, hate, and delusion. Just this much is enough for diligence.”

SN 38.4 What’s the Goal? Kimatthiyasutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, what’s the goal of leading the spiritual life under the ascetic Gotama?”

“The goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha is to completely understand suffering.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding this suffering?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.5 Solace Assāsappattasutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘gaining solace’.[1945] At what point do you gain solace?”

“When a mendicant truly understands the six fields of contact’s origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape, at that point they’ve gained solace.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for realizing this solace?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.6 Ultimate Solace Paramassāsappattasutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘gaining ultimate solace’. At what point do you gain ultimate solace?”

“When a mendicant is freed by not grasping after truly understanding the six fields of contact’s origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape, at that point they’ve gained ultimate solace.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for realizing this ultimate solace?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.7 A Question About Feeling Vedanāpañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘feeling’.[1946] What is feeling?”

“Reverend, there are three feelings. What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings.”

“But reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these three feelings?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.8 A Question About Defilements Āsavapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘defilement’.[1947] What is defilement?”

“Reverend, there are three defilements. The defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. These are the three defilements.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these three defilements?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.9 A Question About Ignorance Avijjāpañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘ignorance’. What is ignorance?”

“Not knowing about suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. This is called ignorance.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for giving up that ignorance?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.10 A Question About Craving Taṇhāpañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘craving’. What is craving?”

“Reverend, there are these three cravings. Craving for sensual pleasures, craving for continued existence, and craving for nonexistence. These are the three cravings.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these cravings?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.11 A Question About Floods Oghapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘a flood’.[1948] What is a flood?”

“Reverend, there are these four floods. The floods of sensuality, desire to be reborn, views, and ignorance. These are the four floods.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these floods?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.12 A Question About Grasping Upādānapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘grasping’. What is grasping?”

“Reverend, there are these four kinds of grasping. Grasping at sensual pleasures, views, precepts and observances, and theories of a self. These are the four kinds of grasping.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these four kinds of grasping?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.13 A Question About States of Existence Bhavapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘continued existence’. What is continued existence?”

“Reverend, there are these three states of continued existence. Existence in the sensual realm, the realm of luminous form, and the formless realm. These are the three states of continued existence.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these three states of existence?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.14 A Question About Suffering Dukkhapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘suffering’. What is suffering?”

“Reverend, there are these three forms of suffering. The suffering inherent in painful feeling; the suffering inherent in conditions; and the suffering inherent in perishing.[1949] These are the three forms of suffering.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding these forms of suffering?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.15 A Question About Substantial Reality Sakkāyapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, they speak of this thing called ‘substantial reality’.[1950] What is substantial reality?”

“Reverend, the Buddha said that these five grasping aggregates are substantial reality. That is, form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness. The Buddha said that these five grasping aggregates are substantial reality.”

“But, reverend, is there a path and a practice for completely understanding this substantial reality?”

“There is.” …

SN 38.16 A Question About What’s Hard to Do Dukkarapañhāsutta

“Reverend Sāriputta, in this teaching and training, what is hard to do?”[1951]

“Going forth, reverend, is hard to do in this teaching and training.”

“But what’s hard to do for someone who has gone forth?”

“When you’ve gone forth it’s hard to be satisfied.”

“But what’s hard to do for someone who is satisfied?”

“When you’re satisfied, it’s hard to practice in line with the teaching.”

“But if a mendicant practices in line with the teaching, will it take them long to become a perfected one?”

“Not long, reverend.”

The Linked Discourses with Jambukhādaka are complete.

The Chapter with Moggallāna

SN 40.1 A Question About the First Absorption Paṭhamajhānapañhāsutta

At one time Venerable Mahāmoggallāna was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.[1953] There Venerable Mahāmoggallāna addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahāmoggallāna said this:

“Just now, reverends, as I was in private retreat this thought came to mind: ‘They speak of this thing called the “first absorption”. What is the first absorption?’ It occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is called the first absorption.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the first absorption.[1954] While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by sensual pleasures beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the first absorption, brahmin! Settle your mind in the first absorption; unify your mind and immerse it in the first absorption.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the first absorption.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.2 A Question About the Second Absorption Dutiyajhānapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘second absorption’. What is the second absorption? It occurred to me: ‘As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, a mendicant enters and remains in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is called the second absorption.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the second absorption. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by placing the mind beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the second absorption, brahmin! Settle your mind in the second absorption; unify your mind and immerse it in the second absorption.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the second absorption.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.3 A Question About the Third Absorption Tatiyajhānapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘third absorption’. What is the third absorption? It occurred to me: ‘With the fading away of rapture, a mendicant enters and remains in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, “Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.” This is called the third absorption.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the third absorption. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by rapture beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the third absorption, brahmin! Settle your mind in the third absorption; unify your mind and immerse it in the third absorption.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the third absorption. So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.4 A Question About the Fourth Absorption Catutthajhānapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘fourth absorption’. What is the fourth absorption? It occurred to me: ‘It’s when, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, a mendicant enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. This is called the fourth absorption.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the fourth absorption. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by pleasure beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the fourth absorption, brahmin! Settle your mind in the fourth absorption; unify your mind and immerse it in the fourth absorption.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the fourth absorption.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.5 A Question About the Dimension of Infinite Space Ākāsānañcāyatanapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘dimension of infinite space’. What is the dimension of infinite space? It occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that “space is infinite”, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. This is called the dimension of infinite space.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the dimension of infinite space. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by forms beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the dimension of infinite space, brahmin! Settle your mind in the dimension of infinite space; unify your mind and immerse it in the dimension of infinite space.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the dimension of infinite space.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.6 A Question About the Dimension of Infinite Consciousness Viññāṇañcāyatanapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘dimension of infinite consciousness’. What is the dimension of infinite consciousness? It occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that “consciousness is infinite”, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. This is called the dimension of infinite consciousness.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the dimension of infinite consciousness. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite space beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the dimension of infinite consciousness, brahmin! Settle your mind in the dimension of infinite consciousness; unify your mind and immerse it in the dimension of infinite consciousness.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the dimension of infinite consciousness.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.7 A Question About the Dimension of Nothingness Ākiñcaññāyatanapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘dimension of nothingness’. What is the dimension of nothingness? It occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that “there is nothing at all”, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. This is called the dimension of nothingness.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the dimension of nothingness. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite consciousness beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the dimension of nothingness, brahmin! Settle your mind in the dimension of nothingness; unify your mind and immerse it in the dimension of nothingness.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the dimension of nothingness.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.8 A Question About the Dimension of Neither Perception Nor Non-Perception Nevasaññānāsaññāyatanapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘dimension of neither perception nor non-perception’. What is the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception? It occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enters and remains in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. This is called the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of nothingness beset me.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, brahmin! Settle your mind in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception; unify your mind and immerse it in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.9 A Question About the Signless Animittapañhāsutta

“They speak of this thing called the ‘signless immersion of the heart’. What is the signless immersion of the heart? It occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant, not focusing on any signs, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart. This is called the signless immersion of the heart.’

And so … I was entering and remaining in the signless immersion of the heart. While I was in that meditation, my consciousness followed after signs.

Then the Buddha came up to me with his psychic power and said, ‘Moggallāna, Moggallāna! Don’t neglect the signless immersion of the heart, brahmin! Settle your mind in the signless immersion of the heart; unify your mind and immerse it in the signless immersion of the heart.’

And so, after some time … I entered and remained in the signless immersion of the heart.

So if anyone should be rightly called a disciple who attained to great direct knowledge with help from the Teacher, it’s me.”

SN 40.10 With Sakka Sakkasutta

And then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from Jeta’s Grove and reappeared among the gods of the thirty-three.[1955] Then Sakka, lord of gods, with five hundred deities came up to Mahāmoggallāna, bowed, and stood to one side. Mahāmoggallāna said to him:

“Lord of gods, it’s good to go for refuge to the Buddha. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It’s good to go for refuge to the teaching. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It’s good to go for refuge to the Saṅgha. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“My good Moggallāna, it’s good to go for refuge to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with six hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with seven hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eight hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eighty thousand deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with five hundred deities came up to Mahāmoggallāna, bowed, and stood to one side. Mahāmoggallāna said to him:

“Lord of gods, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

It’s good to have experiential confidence in the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

It’s good to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“My good Moggallāna, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with six hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with seven hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eight hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eighty thousand deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with five hundred deities came up to Mahāmoggallāna, bowed, and stood to one side. Mahāmoggallāna said to him:

“Lord of gods, it’s good to go for refuge to the Buddha. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. They surpass other gods in ten respects: heavenly lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, sovereignty, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches.

It’s good to go for refuge to the teaching …

It’s good to go for refuge to the Saṅgha. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. They surpass other gods in ten respects: heavenly lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, sovereignty, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches.”

“My good Moggallāna, it’s good to go for refuge to the Buddha …”

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with six hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with seven hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eight hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eighty thousand deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with five hundred deities came up to Mahāmoggallāna, bowed, and stood to one side. Mahāmoggallāna said to him:

“Lord of gods, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha … teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. They surpass other gods in ten respects: heavenly lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, sovereignty, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches.

It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching …

It’s good to have experiential confidence in the Saṅgha …

It’s good to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones …”

“My good Moggallāna, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha …”

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with six hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with seven hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eight hundred deities …

Then Sakka, lord of gods, with eighty thousand deities …

SN 40.11 With Candana, Etc. Candanasutta

Then the godling Candana …[1956]

the godling Suyāma …[1957]

the godling Santusita …

the godling Sunimmita …

the godling Vasavatti …

(Tell in full as in the Discourse With Sakka.)

The Linked Discourses on Moggallāna are complete.

The Chapter with Citta

SN 41.1 The Fetter Saṁyojanasutta

At one time several senior mendicants were staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove.[1958] Now at that time, after the meal, on return from almsround, several senior mendicants sat together in the pavilion and this discussion came up among them:

“Reverends, the ‘fetter’ and the ‘things that tighten the fetters’: do these things differ in both meaning and phrasing? Or do they mean the same thing, and differ only in the phrasing?”

Some senior mendicants answered like this: “Reverends, the ‘fetter’ and the ‘things that tighten the fetters’: these things differ in both meaning and phrasing.”

But some senior mendicants answered like this: “Reverends, the ‘fetter’ and the ‘things that tighten the fetters’ mean the same thing; they differ only in the phrasing.”

Now at that time the householder Citta had arrived at Migapathaka on some business.[1959] He heard about what those senior mendicants were discussing.[1960]

So he went up to them, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to them, “Sirs, I heard that you were discussing whether the ‘fetter’ and the ‘things that tighten the fetters’ differ in both meaning and phrasing, or whether they mean the same thing, and differ only in the phrasing.”

“That’s right, householder.”

“Sirs, the ‘fetter’ and the ‘things that tighten the fetters’: these things differ in both meaning and phrasing.

Well then, sirs, I shall give you a simile. For by means of a simile some sensible people understand the meaning of what is said.

Suppose there was a black ox and a white ox yoked by a single harness or yoke. Would it be right to say that the black ox is the yoke of the white ox, or the white ox is the yoke of the black ox?”[1961]

“No, householder. The black ox is not the yoke of the white ox, nor is the white ox the yoke of the black ox. The yoke there is the single harness or yoke that they’re yoked by.”

“In the same way, the eye is not the fetter of sights, nor are sights the fetter of the eye. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.

The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the mind. The fetter there is the desire and greed that arises from the pair of them.”

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate, to traverse the Buddha’s deep teachings with the eye of wisdom.”

SN 41.2 With Isidatta (1st) Paṭhamaisidattasutta

At one time several senior mendicants were staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove.

Then Citta the householder went up to them, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to them, “Sirs, would the senior monks please accept tomorrow’s meal from me?”

They consented with silence. Knowing that the senior mendicants had consented, Citta rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled them, keeping them on his right, before leaving.

Then when the night had passed, the senior mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, went to Citta’s home, and sat down on the seats spread out.

Then Citta went up to them, bowed, sat down to one side, and asked the senior venerable, “Honorable Senior, they speak of ‘the diversity of elements’.[1962] In what way did the Buddha speak of the diversity of elements?”[1963]

When he said this, the senior venerable kept silent.[1964]

For a second time …

And for a third time, Citta asked him, “Honorable Senior, they speak of ‘the diversity of elements’. In what way did the Buddha speak of the diversity of elements?”

And a second time and a third time the senior venerable kept silent.

Now at that time Venerable Isidatta was the most junior mendicant in that Saṅgha.[1965] He said to the senior venerable, “Honorable Senior, may I answer Citta’s question?”

“Answer it, Reverend Isidatta.”

“Householder, is this your question: ‘They speak of “the diversity of elements”. In what way did the Buddha speak of the diversity of elements?’”

“Yes, sir.”

“This is the diversity of elements spoken of by the Buddha.[1966]

The eye element, the sights element, the eye consciousness element …

The mind element, the idea element, the mind consciousness element.

This is how the Buddha spoke of the diversity of elements.”

Then Citta, having approved and agreed with what Isidatta said, served and satisfied the senior mendicants with his own hands with delicious fresh and cooked foods. When the senior mendicants had eaten and washed their hands and bowls, they rose from their seats and left.

Then the senior venerable said to Venerable Isidatta, “Isidatta, it’s good that you felt inspired to answer that question, because I didn’t. So when a similar question comes up, you should also answer it as you feel inspired.”

SN 41.3 With Isidatta (2nd) Dutiyaisidattasutta

At one time several senior mendicants were staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove.

Then Citta the householder went up to them, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to them, “Sirs, would the senior monks please accept tomorrow’s meal from me?”

They consented with silence. Then, knowing that the senior mendicants had consented, Citta rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled them, keeping them on his right, before leaving.

Then when the night had passed, the senior mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, went to Citta’s home, and sat down on the seats spread out.

So he went up to them, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to the senior venerable:

“Honorable Senior, there are many different views that arise in the world. For example: the cosmos is eternal, or not eternal, or finite, or infinite; the soul and the body are one and the same, or the soul is one thing, the body another; after death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists. And also the sixty-two misconceptions spoken of in ‘The Divine Net’.[1967] When what exists do these views come to be? When what doesn’t exist do these views not come to be?”

When he said this, the senior venerable kept silent.

For a second time …

And for a third time, Citta said to him:

“Honorable Senior, there are many different views that arise in the world. … When what exists do these views come to be? When what doesn’t exist do these views not come to be?”

And a second time and a third time the senior venerable kept silent.

Now at that time Venerable Isidatta was the most junior mendicant in that Saṅgha. He said to the senior venerable, “Honorable Senior, may I answer Citta’s question?”

“Answer it, Reverend Isidatta.”

“Householder, is this your question: ‘There are many different views that arise in the world … When what exists do these views come to be? When what doesn’t exist do these views not come to be?’” “Yes, sir.”

“Householder, there are many different views that arise in the world. For example: the cosmos is eternal, or not eternal, or finite, or infinite; the soul and the body are one and the same, or the soul is one thing, the body another; after death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists. And also the sixty-two misconceptions spoken of in ‘The Divine Net’.

These views come to be when substantialist view exists. When substantialist view does not exist they do not come to be.”[1968]

“But sir, how does substantialist view come about?”

“It’s when an unlearned ordinary person has not seen the noble ones, and is neither skilled nor trained in the teaching of the noble ones. They’ve not seen true persons, and are neither skilled nor trained in the teaching of the true persons.

They regard form as self, self as having form, form in self, or self in form. They regard feeling … perception … choices … consciousness as self, self as having consciousness, consciousness in self, or self in consciousness.

That’s how substantialist view comes about.”

“But sir, how does substantialist view not come about?”

“It’s when a learned noble disciple has seen the noble ones, and is skilled and trained in the teaching of the noble ones. They’ve seen true persons, and are skilled and trained in the teaching of the true persons.

They don’t regard form as self, self as having form, form in self, or self in form. They don’t regard feeling … perception … choices … consciousness as self, self as having consciousness, consciousness in self, or self in consciousness.

That’s how substantialist view does not come about.”

“Sir, where has Master Isidatta come from?”[1969]

“I come from Avanti, householder.”[1970]

“Sir, there’s a friend of mine named Isidatta who I’ve never met. He’s gone forth from a good family in Avanti. Have you met him?”

“Yes, householder.”

“Sir, where is that venerable now staying?” When he said this, Isidatta kept silent.

“Sir, are you that Isidatta?”

“Yes, householder.”

“Sir, I hope Master Isidatta is happy here in Macchikāsaṇḍa, for the Wild Mango Grove is lovely. I’ll make sure that Master Isidatta is provided with robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.”

“That’s nice of you to say, householder.”

Then Citta, having approved and agreed with what Isidatta said, served and satisfied the senior mendicants with his own hands with delicious fresh and cooked foods. When the senior mendicants had eaten and washed their hands and bowls, they rose from their seats and left.

Then the senior venerable said to Venerable Isidatta, “Isidatta, it’s good that you felt inspired to answer that question, because I didn’t. So when a similar question comes up, you should also answer it as you feel inspired.”

But Isidatta set his lodgings in order and, taking his bowl and robe, left Macchikāsaṇḍa, never to return.[1971]

SN 41.4 Mahaka’s Demonstration Mahakapāṭihāriyasutta

At one time several senior mendicants were staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove.

Then Citta the householder went up to them, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to them, “Sirs, would the senior monks please accept tomorrow’s meal from me in my milkshed?”[1972]

They consented with silence. Then, knowing that the senior mendicants had consented, Citta rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled them, keeping them on his right, before leaving.

Then when the night had passed, the senior mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, went to Citta’s milkshed, and sat down on the seats spread out.

Then Citta served and satisfied the senior mendicants with his own hands with delicious milk-rice made with ghee. When the senior mendicants had eaten and washed their hands and bowls, they rose from their seats and left. Citta instructed that the leftovers of the food be distributed, then followed behind the senior mendicants.[1973]

Now at that time it was boiling hot. And those senior mendicants walked along as if their bodies were melting, as happens after a meal.

Now at that time Venerable Mahaka was the most junior mendicant in that Saṅgha.[1974] Then Venerable Mahaka said to the senior venerable, “Wouldn’t it be nice, Honorable Senior, if a cool wind blew, a cloud canopy formed, and a gentle rain drizzled down?”

“It would indeed be nice, Reverend Mahaka.” Then Mahaka used his psychic power to will that a cool wind would blow, a cloud canopy would form, and a gentle rain would drizzle down.

Then Citta thought, “The most junior mendicant in this Saṅgha has such psychic power!”

When they reached the monastery, Mahaka said to the senior venerable, “Honorable Senior, is that sufficient?”

“That’s sufficient, Reverend Mahaka, you’ve done enough and offered enough.” Then the senior mendicants entered their dwellings, and Mahaka entered his own dwelling.

Then Citta went up to Mahaka, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, please show me a superhuman demonstration of psychic power.”

“Well, then, householder, place your upper robe on the porch and spread a handful of grass on it.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Citta, and did as he was asked.

Mahaka entered his dwelling and latched the door. Then he used his psychic power to will that a flame shoot out through the keyhole and the chink in the door-panel, and it burned up the grass but not the upper robe.[1975] Then Citta shook out his upper robe and stood to one side, shocked and awestruck.

Mahaka left his dwelling and said to Citta, “Is that sufficient, householder?”

“That’s sufficient, sir, you’ve done enough and offered enough. I hope Master Mahaka is happy here in Macchikāsaṇḍa, for the Wild Mango Grove is lovely. I’ll make sure that Master Mahaka is provided with robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.”

“That’s nice of you to say, householder.”

But Mahaka set his lodgings in order and, taking his bowl and robe, left Macchikāsaṇḍa, never to return.[1976]

SN 41.5 With Kāmabhū (1st) Paṭhamakāmabhūsutta

At one time Venerable Kāmabhū was staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove.[1977]

Then Citta the householder went up to Venerable Kāmabhū, bowed, and sat down to one side. Kāmabhū said to him,[1978] “Householder, there is this saying:

‘With faultless parts and white canopy,
the one-spoked chariot rolls on.
See it come, untroubled,
with stream cut, unbound.’

How should we see the detailed meaning of this brief statement?”

“Sir, was this spoken by the Buddha?”

“Yes, householder.”[1979]

“Well then, sir, please wait a while as I consider the meaning of this.” Then after staying silent for a while, Citta said to Kāmabhū:

“Sir, ‘faultless parts’ is a term for ethics.[1980]

‘White canopy’ is a term for freedom.[1981]

‘One spoke’ is a term for mindfulness.[1982]

‘Rolls on’ is a term for going forward and coming back.[1983]

‘Chariot’ is a term for this body made up of the four principal states, produced by mother and father, built up from rice and porridge, liable to impermanence, to wearing away and erosion, to breaking up and destruction.[1984]

Greed, hate, and delusion are troubles.[1985] A mendicant who has ended the defilements has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. That’s why a mendicant who has ended the defilements is called ‘untroubled’.

‘The one who comes’ is a term for the perfected one.

‘Stream’ is a term for craving.[1986] A mendicant who has ended the defilements has given this up, cut it off at the root, made it like a palm stump, and obliterated it, so it’s unable to arise in the future. That’s why a mendicant who has ended the defilements is said to have ‘cut the stream’.

Greed, hate, and delusion are bonds. A mendicant who has ended the defilements has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. That’s why a mendicant who has ended the defilements is called ‘unbound’.

So, sir, that’s how I understand the detailed meaning of what the Buddha said in brief:

‘With faultless parts and white canopy,
the one-spoked chariot rolls on.
See it come, untroubled,
with stream cut, unbound.’”

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate, to traverse the Buddha’s deep teachings with the eye of wisdom.”

SN 41.6 With Kāmabhū (2nd) Dutiyakāmabhūsutta

At one time Venerable Kāmabhū was staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove. Then Citta the householder went up to Venerable Kāmabhū, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, how many processes are there?”[1987]

“Householder, there are three processes. The physical process, the verbal process, and the mental process.”[1988]

Saying “Good, sir,” Citta approved and agreed with what Kāmabhū said. Then he asked another question:

“But sir, what is the physical process? What’s the verbal process? What’s the mental process?”

“Breathing is a physical process. Placing the mind and keeping it connected are a verbal process. Perception and feeling are a mental process.”

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, why is breathing a physical process? Why are placing the mind and keeping it connected a verbal process? Why are perception and feeling a mental process?”

“Breathing is physical. It’s tied up with the body, that’s why breathing is a physical process.[1989] First you place the mind and keep it connected, then you break into speech. That’s why placing the mind and keeping it connected are a verbal process.[1990] Perception and feeling are mental. They’re tied up with the mind, that’s why perception and feeling are a mental process.”[1991]

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, how does someone attain the cessation of perception and feeling?”

“A mendicant who is entering such an attainment does not think: ‘I will enter the cessation of perception and feeling’ or ‘I am entering the cessation of perception and feeling’ or ‘I have entered the cessation of perception and feeling.’ Rather, their mind has been previously developed so as to lead to such a state.”[1992]

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, which cease first for a mendicant who is entering the cessation of perception and feeling: the physical, verbal, or mental process?”

“The verbal process ceases first, then physical, then mental.”[1993]

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“What’s the difference between someone who has passed away and a mendicant who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling?”

“When someone dies, their physical, verbal, and mental processes have ceased and stilled; their vitality is spent; their warmth is dissipated; and their faculties have disintegrated. When a mendicant has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, their physical, verbal, and mental processes have ceased and stilled. But their vitality is not spent; their warmth is not dissipated; and their faculties are very clear. That’s the difference between someone who has passed away and a mendicant who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling.”

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, how does someone emerge from the cessation of perception and feeling?”

“A mendicant who is emerging from such an attainment does not think: ‘I will emerge from the cessation of perception and feeling’ or ‘I am emerging from the cessation of perception and feeling’ or ‘I have emerged from the cessation of perception and feeling.’ Rather, their mind has been previously developed so as to lead to such a state.”

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, which arise first for a mendicant who is emerging from the cessation of perception and feeling: the physical, verbal, or mental process?”

“The mental process arises first, then physical, then verbal.”

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, when a mendicant has emerged from the attainment of the cessation of perception and feeling, how many kinds of contact do they experience?”

“They experience three kinds of contact: emptiness, signless, and undirected contacts.”[1994]

Saying “Good, sir,” he asked another question:

“But sir, when a mendicant has emerged from the attainment of the cessation of perception and feeling, what does their mind slant, slope, and incline to?”

“Their mind slants, slopes, and inclines to seclusion.”[1995]

Saying “Good, sir,” Citta approved and agreed with what Kāmabhū said. Then he asked another question:

“But sir, how many things are helpful for attaining the cessation of perception and feeling?”[1996]

“Well, householder, you’ve finally asked what you should have asked first! Nevertheless, I will answer you. Two things are helpful for attaining the cessation of perception and feeling: serenity and discernment.”

SN 41.7 With Godatta Godattasutta

At one time Venerable Godatta was staying near Macchikāsaṇḍa in the Wild Mango Grove. Then Citta the householder went up to Venerable Godatta, bowed, and sat down to one side. Godatta said to him:

“Householder, the limitless release of the heart, and the release of the heart through nothingness, and the release of the heart through emptiness, and the signless release of the heart: do these things differ in both meaning and phrasing? Or do they mean the same thing, and differ only in the phrasing?”[1997]

“Sir, there is a way in which these things differ in both meaning and phrasing. But there’s also a way in which they mean the same thing, and differ only in the phrasing.[1998]

And what’s the way in which these things differ in both meaning and phrasing?

It’s when a mendicant meditates spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. They meditate spreading a heart full of compassion … They meditate spreading a heart full of rejoicing … They meditate spreading a heart full of equanimity to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of equanimity to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. This is called the limitless release of the heart.

And what is the release of the heart through nothingness? It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. This is called the release of the heart through nothingness.

And what is the release of the heart through emptiness? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, and reflects like this: ‘This is empty of a self or what belongs to a self.’ This is called the release of the heart through emptiness.

And what is the signless heart’s release? It’s when a mendicant, not focusing on any signs, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart.[1999] This is called the signless release of the heart.

This is the way in which these things differ in both meaning and phrasing.

And what’s the way in which they mean the same thing, and differ only in the phrasing?

Greed, hate, and delusion are makers of limits. A mendicant who has ended the defilements has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. The unshakable release of the heart is said to be the best kind of limitless release of the heart. That unshakable release of the heart is empty of greed, hate, and delusion.

Greed is something, hate is something, and delusion is something. A mendicant who has ended the defilements has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. The unshakable release of the heart is said to be the best kind of release of the heart through nothingness. That unshakable release of the heart is empty of greed, hate, and delusion.

Greed, hate, and delusion are makers of signs. A mendicant who has ended the defilements has given these up, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, and obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future. The unshakable release of the heart is said to be the best kind of signless release of the heart. That unshakable release of the heart is empty of greed, hate, and delusion.

This is the way in which they mean the same thing, and differ only in the phrasing.”

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate, to traverse the Buddha’s deep teachings with the eye of wisdom.”

SN 41.8 The Jain Ascetic of the Ñātika Clan Nigaṇṭhanāṭaputtasutta

Now at that time the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan had arrived at Macchikāsaṇḍa together with a large assembly of Jain ascetics.[2000]

Citta the householder heard that they had arrived. Together with several lay followers, he went up to the Jain Ñātika and exchanged greetings with him.[2001]

When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side. The Jain Ñātika said to him, “Householder, do you have faith in the ascetic Gotama’s claim that there is a state of immersion without placing the mind and keeping it connected; that there is the cessation of placing the mind and keeping it connected?”

“Sir, in this case I don’t rely on faith in the Buddha’s claim that there is a state of immersion without placing the mind and keeping it connected; that there is the cessation of placing the mind and keeping it connected.”

When he said this, the Jain Ñātika looked up at his assembly and said, “See, good sirs, how straightforward this householder Citta is! He’s not devious or deceitful at all. To imagine that you can stop placing the mind and keeping it connected would be like imagining that you can catch the wind in a net, or dam the Ganges River with your own hand.”[2002]

“What do you think, sir? Which is better—knowledge or faith?”

“Knowledge is definitely better than faith, householder.”[2003]

“Well sir, whenever I want, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, I enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. And whenever I want, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled … I enter and remain in the second absorption. And whenever I want, with the fading away of rapture … I enter and remain in the third absorption. And whenever I want, giving up pleasure and pain … I enter and remain in the fourth absorption.

And so, sir, since I know and see like this, why should I rely on faith in another ascetic or brahmin who claims that there is a state of immersion without placing the mind and keeping it connected; that there is the cessation of placing the mind and keeping it connected?”

When he said this, the Jain Ñātika looked askance at his own assembly and said, “See, good fellows, how crooked this householder Citta is! He’s so devious and deceitful!”

“Sir, just now I understood you to say: ‘See, good fellows, how straightforward this householder Citta is! He’s not devious or deceitful at all.’ But then I understood you to say: ‘See, good fellows, how crooked this householder Citta is! He’s so devious and deceitful!’ If your first statement is true, the second is wrong. If your first statement is wrong, the second is true.

And also, sir, these ten legitimate questions are relevant. When you understand what they mean, then, together with your assembly of Jain ascetics, you can rebut me. ‘One thing: question, summary, and answer.[2004] Two … Three … Four … Five … Six … Seven … Eight … Nine … Ten things: question, summary, and answer.’”

Then Citta rose from his seat and left without asking the Jain Ñātika these ten legitimate questions.[2005]

SN 41.9 With Kassapa, the Naked Ascetic Acelakassapasutta

Now at that time the naked ascetic Kassapa, an old friend of Citta in the lay life, had arrived at Macchikāsaṇḍa.[2006]

Citta the householder heard that he had arrived. So he went up to him, and they exchanged greetings.

When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the naked ascetic Kassapa, “Honorable Kassapa, how long has it been since you went forth?”

“It’s been thirty years, householder.”

“But sir, in these thirty years have you achieved any superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones, a comfortable meditation?”

“I have no such achievement, householder, only nudity, baldness, and pokes in the buttocks.”[2007]

Citta said to him, “Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing, how well explained the teaching is. For in thirty years you have achieved no superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones, no comfortable meditation, only nudity, baldness, and pokes in the buttocks.”

“But householder, how long have you been a lay follower?”

“It’s been thirty years, sir.”

“But householder, in these thirty years have you achieved any superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones, a comfortable meditation?”

“How, sir, could I not?[2008] For whenever I want, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, I enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. And whenever I want, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled … I enter and remain in the second absorption. And whenever I want, with the fading away of rapture … I enter and remain in the third absorption. And whenever I want, giving up pleasure and pain … I enter and remain in the fourth absorption.

If I pass away before the Buddha, it would be no wonder if the Buddha declares of me: ‘The householder Citta is bound by no fetter that might return him to this world.’”[2009]

When this was said, Kassapa said to Citta, “Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing, how well explained the teaching is. For a white-clothed layperson can achieve such a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones, a comfortable meditation. Householder, may I receive the going forth, the ordination in this teaching and training?”

Then Citta the householder took the naked ascetic Kassapa to see the senior mendicants, and said to them:

“Sirs, this is the naked ascetic Kassapa, who in lay life was an old friend of mine. May the senior monks give him the going forth, the ordination. I’ll make sure that he’s provided with robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.”

And the naked ascetic Kassapa received the going forth, the ordination in this teaching and training. Not long after his ordination, Venerable Kassapa, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Kassapa became one of the perfected.

SN 41.10 Seeing the Sick Gilānadassanasutta

Now at that time the householder Citta was sick, suffering, gravely ill.

Then several deities of the parks, forests, trees, and those who haunt the herbs, grass, and big trees came together and said to Citta, “Householder, make a wish to become a wheel-turning monarch in the future!”

When they said this, Citta said to them, “That too is impermanent! That too will pass! That too will be left behind!”

When he said this, his friends and colleagues, relatives and kin said, “Be mindful, master! Don’t babble.”

“What have I said that makes you say that?”

“It’s because you said: ‘That too is impermanent! That too will pass! That too will be left behind!’”

“Oh, well, that’s because the deities of the parks, forests, trees, and those who haunt the herbs, grass, and big trees said to me: ‘Householder, make a wish to become a wheel-turning monarch in the future!’ So I said to them: ‘That too is impermanent! That too will pass! That too will be left behind!’”

“But what reason do they see for saying that to you?”

“They think: ‘This householder Citta is ethical, of good character. If he makes a wish to become a wheel-turning monarch in the future, his heart’s wish will succeed because of the purity of his ethics. And then as a proper, principled king he will provide proper spirit-offerings.’ That’s the reason they see for saying to me: ‘Householder, make a wish to become a wheel-turning monarch in the future!’ So I said to them: ‘That too is impermanent! That too will pass! That too will be left behind!’”

“Then, master, advise us!”

“So you should train like this:

We will have experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’

We will have experiential confidence in the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’

We will have experiential confidence in the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’

And we will share without reservation all the gifts available to give in our family with those who are ethical and of good character.”

Then, after Citta had encouraged his friends and colleagues, relatives and kin in the Buddha, the teaching, the Saṅgha, and generosity, he passed away.

The Linked Discourses on Citta the Householder are complete.

The Chapter on Chiefs

SN 42.1 Fury Caṇḍasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Fury the chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2010]

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason why some people are regarded as furious, while others are regarded as gentle?”

“Take someone who hasn’t given up greed. So they get annoyed by others, and they show it. They’re regarded as furious. They haven’t given up hate. So they get annoyed by others, and they show it. They’re regarded as furious. They haven’t given up delusion. So they get annoyed by others, and they show it. They’re regarded as furious. This is the cause, this is the reason why some people are regarded as furious.

But take someone who has given up greed. So they don’t get annoyed by others, and don’t show it. They’re regarded as gentle. They’ve given up hate. So they don’t get annoyed by others, and don’t show it. They’re regarded as gentle. They’ve given up delusion. So they don’t get annoyed by others, and don’t show it. They’re regarded as gentle. This is the cause, this is the reason why some people are regarded as gentle.”

When he said this, Fury the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! As if he were righting the overturned, or revealing the hidden, or pointing out the path to the lost, or lighting a lamp in the dark so people with clear eyes can see what’s there, the Buddha has made the teaching clear in many ways. I go for refuge to the Buddha, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.2 With Tālapuṭa Tālapuṭasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. Then Tālapuṭa the dancing chief came up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2011]

“Sir, I have heard that the dancers of the past who were tutors of tutors said: ‘Suppose a dancer entertains and amuses people on a stage or at a festival with mixed truth and lies. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of laughing gods.’ What does the Buddha say about this?”

“Enough, chief, let it be. Don’t ask me that.”

For a second time …

And for a third time Tālapuṭa said to the Buddha:

“Sir, I have heard that the dancers of the past who were tutors of tutors said: ‘Suppose a dancer entertains and amuses people on a stage or at a festival with mixed truth and lies. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of laughing gods.’ What does the Buddha say about this?”

“Clearly, chief, I’m not getting through to you when I say: ‘Enough, chief, let it be. Don’t ask me that.’ Nevertheless, I will answer you.

When sentient beings are still not free of greed, and are still bound by greed, a dancer in a stage or festival presents them with even more arousing things. When sentient beings are still not free of hate, and are still bound by hate, a dancer in a stage or festival presents them with even more hateful things. When sentient beings are still not free of delusion, and are still bound by delusion, a dancer in a stage or festival presents them with even more delusory things. And so, being heedless and negligent themselves, they’ve encouraged others to be heedless and negligent. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the hell called ‘Laughter’.

But if you have such a view: ‘Suppose a dancer entertains and amuses people on a stage or at a festival with mixed truth and lies. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of laughing gods.’ This is your wrong view. An individual with wrong view is reborn in one of two places, I say:[2012] hell or the animal realm.”

When he said this, Tālapuṭa cried and burst out in tears.

“This is what I didn’t get through to you when I said: ‘Enough, chief, let it be. Don’t ask me that.’”

“Sir, I’m not crying because of what the Buddha said. But sir, for a long time I’ve been cheated, tricked, and deceived by the dancers of the past who were tutors of tutors, who said: ‘Suppose a dancer entertains and amuses people on a stage or at a festival with mixed truth and lies. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of laughing gods.’

Excellent, sir! Excellent! As if he were righting the overturned, or revealing the hidden, or pointing out the path to the lost, or lighting a lamp in the dark so people with clear eyes can see what’s there, the Buddha has made the teaching clear in many ways. I go for refuge to the Buddha, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. Sir, may I receive the going forth, the ordination in the Buddha’s presence?”

And Tālapuṭa the dancing chief received the going forth, the ordination in the Buddha’s presence. Not long after his ordination, Venerable Tālapuṭa became one of the perfected.

SN 42.3 A Warrior Yodhājīvasutta

Then Dustin the warrior chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2013]

“Sir, I have heard that the warriors of the past who were tutors of tutors said: ‘Suppose a warrior, while striving and struggling in battle, is killed and finished off by his foes. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in the company of the gods of the fallen.’ What does the Buddha say about this?”

“Enough, chief, let it be. Don’t ask me that.”

For a second time …

And for a third time Dustin the warrior chief said to the Buddha:

“Sir, I have heard that the warriors of the past who were tutors of tutors said: ‘Suppose a warrior, while striving and struggling in battle, is killed and finished off by his foes. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in the company of the gods of the fallen.’ What does the Buddha say about this?”

“Clearly, chief, I’m not getting through to you when I say: ‘Enough, chief, let it be. Don’t ask me that.’ Nevertheless, I will answer you.

When a warrior strives and struggles in battle, their mind is already low, degraded, and misdirected as they think: ‘May these sentient beings be killed, slaughtered, slain, destroyed, or annihilated!’ His foes kill him and finish him off, and when his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in the hell called ‘The Fallen’.[2014]

But if you have such a view: ‘Suppose a warrior, while striving and struggling in battle, is killed and finished off by his foes. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in the company of the gods of the fallen.’ This is your wrong view. An individual with wrong view is reborn in one of two places, I say: hell or the animal realm.”

When he said this, Dustin the warrior chief cried and burst out in tears.

“This is what I didn’t get through to you when I said: ‘Enough, chief, let it be. Don’t ask me that.’”

“Sir, I’m not crying because of what the Buddha said. But sir, for a long time I’ve been cheated, tricked, and deceived by the warriors of the past who were tutors of tutors, who said: ‘Suppose a warrior, while striving and struggling in battle, is killed and finished off by his foes. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in the company of the gods of the fallen.’

Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.4 An Elephant Marshal Hatthārohasutta

Then an elephant marshal chief went up to the Buddha …[2015] “From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.5 A Cavalryman Assārohasutta

Then a cavalry chief went up to the Buddha …

“From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.6 With Asibandhaka’s Son Asibandhakaputtasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Nāḷandā in Pāvārika’s Mango Grove.[2016]

Then Asibandhaka’s son the chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2017]

“Sir, there are western brahmins garlanded with aquatic flowers who carry pitchers, immerse themselves in water, and serve the sacred flame.[2018] When someone has passed away, oh! they lift them up, send them well, and convey them to heaven.[2019] But what about the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha: is he able to ensure that the whole world will be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm when their body breaks up, after death?”

“Well then, chief, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like.

What do you think, chief? Take a person who kills living creatures, steals, and commits sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re covetous, malicious, and have wrong view. A large crowd were to come together to offer up supplication and entreaty, circumambulating them with cupped palms and saying:[2020] ‘When this person’s body breaks up, after death, may they be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm!’ What do you think, chief? Would that person be reborn in heaven because of their supplications?”[2021]

“No, sir.”

“Chief, suppose a person were to throw a broad rock into a deep lake. And a large crowd were to come together to offer up supplication and entreaty, circumambulating it with cupped palms, and saying: ‘Rise, good rock! Float, good rock! Float to shore, good rock!’ What do you think, chief? Would that broad rock rise up or float because of their supplications?”

“No, sir.”

“In the same way, take a person who kills living creatures, steals, and commits sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re covetous, malicious, and have wrong view. Even though a large crowd were to come together to offer up supplication and entreaty … when their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, chief? Take a person who doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. And a large crowd were to come together to offer up supplication and entreaty, circumambulating them with cupped palms and saying: ‘When this person’s body breaks up, after death, may they be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell!’ What do you think, chief? Would that person be reborn in hell because of their supplications?”

“No, sir.”

“Chief, suppose a person were to sink a pot of ghee or oil into a deep lake and break it open. Its shards and chips would sink down, while the ghee or oil in it would rise up.[2022] And a large crowd were to come together to offer up supplication and entreaty, circumambulating it with cupped palms and saying: ‘Sink, good ghee or oil! Descend, good ghee or oil! Go down, good ghee or oil!’ What do you think, chief? Would that ghee or oil sink and descend because of their supplications?”

“No, sir.”

“In the same way, take a person who doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. Even though a large crowd were to come together to offer up supplication and entreaty … when their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

When he said this, Asibandhaka’s son the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.7 The Simile of the Field Khettūpamasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Nāḷandā in Pāvārika’s Mango Grove. Then Asibandhaka’s son the chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, doesn’t the Buddha live full of sympathy for all living beings?”

“Yes, chief.”

“So why then, sir, do you teach some people thoroughly and others less thoroughly?”

“Well then, chief, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like. What do you think? Suppose a farmer has three fields: one is good, one is average, and one is poor—bad ground of sand and salt. What do you think? When that farmer wants to plant seeds, where would he plant them first: the good field, the average one, or the poor one?”

“Sir, he’d plant them first in the good field, then the average, then he may or may not plant seed in the poor field. Why is that? Because at least it can be fodder for the cattle.”

“To me, the monks and nuns are like the good field. I teach them the Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And I reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. Why is that? Because they live with me as their island, asylum, shelter, and refuge.[2023]

To me, the laymen and laywomen are like the average field. I also teach them the Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And I reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure.[2024] Why is that? Because they live with me as their island, asylum, shelter, and refuge.

To me, the ascetics, brahmins, and wanderers of other religions are like the poor field, the bad ground of sand and salt. I also teach them the Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And I reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. Why is that? Hopefully they might understand even a single sentence, which would be for their lasting welfare and happiness.

Suppose a person had three water jars: one that’s uncracked and nonporous; one that’s uncracked but porous; and one that’s cracked and porous. What do you think? When that person wants to store water, where would they store it first: in the jar that’s uncracked and nonporous, the one that’s uncracked but porous, or the one that’s cracked and porous?”

“Sir, they’d store water first in the jar that’s uncracked and nonporous, then the one that’s uncracked but porous, then they may or may not store water in the one that’s cracked and porous. Why is that? Because at least it can be used for washing the dishes.”

“To me, the monks and nuns are like the water jar that’s uncracked and nonporous. I teach them the Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And I reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. Why is that? Because they live with me as their island, asylum, shelter, and refuge.

To me, the laymen and laywomen are like the water jar that’s uncracked but porous. I also teach them the Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And I reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure.[2025] Why is that? Because they live with me as their island, asylum, shelter, and refuge.

To me, the ascetics, brahmins, and wanderers of other religions are like the water jar that’s cracked and porous. I also teach them the Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And I reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. Why is that? Hopefully they might understand even a single sentence, which would be for their lasting welfare and happiness.”

When he said this, Asibandhaka’s son the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.8 A Horn Blower Saṅkhadhamasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Nāḷandā in Pāvārika’s Mango Grove.

Then Asibandhaka’s son the chief, who was a disciple of the Jains, went up to the Buddha, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Chief, how does the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan teach his disciples?”

“Sir, this is how the Jain Ñātika teaches his disciples: ‘Everyone who kills a living creature, steals, commits sexual misconduct, or lies goes to a place of loss, to hell. You’re led on by what you frequently live by.’[2026] This is how the Jain Ñātika teaches his disciples.”

“‘You’re led on by what you usually live by’: if this were true, then, according to what the Jain Ñātika says, no one would go to a place of loss, to hell.

What do you think, chief? Take a person who kills living creatures. If we compare periods of time during the day and night, which is more frequent: the occasions when they’re killing or when they’re not killing?”

“The occasions when they’re killing are less frequent, while the occasions when they’re not killing are more frequent.”

“‘You’re led on by what you usually live by’: if this were true, then, according to what the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan says, no one would go to a place of loss, to hell.

What do you think, chief? Take a person who steals …

Take a person who commits sexual misconduct …

Take a person who lies. If we compare periods of time during the day and night, which is more frequent: the occasions when they’re lying or when they’re not lying?”

“The occasions when they’re lying are less frequent, while the occasions when they’re not lying are more frequent.”

“‘You’re led on by what you usually live by’: if this were true, then, according to what the Jain Ñātika says, no one would go to a place of loss, to hell.

Take some teacher who has this doctrine and view: ‘Everyone who kills a living creature, steals, commits sexual misconduct, or lies goes to a place of loss, to hell.’ And there’s a disciple who is devoted to that teacher. They think: ‘My teacher has this doctrine and view: “Everyone who kills a living creature, steals, commits sexual misconduct, or lies goes to a place of loss, to hell.” But I’ve killed living creatures … stolen … committed sexual misconduct … or lied.’ They get the view: ‘I too am going to a place of loss, to hell.’ Unless they give up that speech and that thought, and let go of that view, they will be placed in hell as if delivered there.

But consider when a Realized One arises in the world, perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed. In many ways he criticizes and denounces killing living creatures, saying: ‘Stop killing living creatures!’ He criticizes and denounces stealing … sexual misconduct … lying, saying: ‘Stop lying!’ And there’s a disciple who is devoted to that teacher.[2027] Then they reflect: ‘In many ways the Buddha criticizes and denounces killing living creatures, saying: “Stop killing living creatures!” But I have killed living creatures to a certain extent. That’s not right, it’s not good, and I feel remorseful because of it. But I can’t undo what I have done.’ Reflecting like this, they give up killing living creatures, and in future they don’t kill living creatures. That’s how to give up this bad deed and get past it.

‘In many ways the Buddha criticizes and denounces stealing …’

‘In many ways the Buddha criticizes and denounces sexual misconduct …’

‘In many ways the Buddha criticizes and denounces lying, saying: “Stop lying!” But I have lied to a certain extent. That’s not right, it’s not good, and I feel remorseful because of it. But I can’t undo what I have done.’ Reflecting like this, they give up lying, and in future they refrain from lying. That’s how to give up this bad deed and get past it.

They give up killing living creatures.[2028] They give up stealing. They give up sexual misconduct. They give up lying. They give up backbiting. They give up harsh speech. They give up talking nonsense. They give up covetousness. They give up ill will and malevolence. They give up wrong view and have right view.

That noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.[2029] Suppose there was a powerful horn blower. They’d easily make themselves heard in the four quarters.[2030] In the same way, when the heart’s release by love has been developed and cultivated like this, any limited deeds they’ve done don’t remain or persist there.[2031]

Then that noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of compassion …[2032] They meditate spreading a heart full of rejoicing …[2033] They meditate spreading a heart full of equanimity to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of equanimity to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.[2034] Suppose there was a powerful horn blower. They’d easily make themselves heard in the four quarters. In the same way, when the heart’s release by equanimity has been developed and cultivated like this, any limited deeds they’ve done don’t remain or persist there.”

When he said this, Asibandhaka’s son the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.9 Families Kulasutta

At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants when he arrived at Nāḷandā.[2035] There he stayed near Nāḷandā in Pāvārika’s Mango Grove.

Now at that time Nāḷandā was undergoing famine and scarcity, with crops blighted and turned to straw.[2036] At that time the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan was residing at Nāḷandā together with a large assembly of Jain ascetics.[2037] Then Asibandhaka’s son the chief, who was a disciple of the Jains, went up to the Jain Ñātika, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Jain Ñātika said to him:

“Come, chief, refute the ascetic Gotama’s doctrine. Then you will get a good reputation: ‘Asibandhaka’s son the chief refuted the doctrine of the ascetic Gotama, so mighty and powerful!’”

“But sir, how am I to do this?”

“Here, brahmin, go to the ascetic Gotama and say to him: ‘Sir, don’t you in many ways praise kindness, protection, and sympathy for families?’ When he’s asked this, if he answers: ‘Indeed I do, chief,’ say this to him: ‘So what then are you doing, wandering together with this large Saṅgha of mendicants during a time of famine and scarcity, with crops blighted and turned to straw?[2038] The Buddha is practicing to annihilate, collapse, and ruin families!’[2039] When you put this dilemma to him, the Buddha won’t be able to either spit it out or swallow it down.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Asibandhaka’s son. He rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Jain Ñātika, keeping him on his right. Then he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, don’t you in many ways praise kindness, protection, and sympathy for families?”

“Indeed I do, chief.”

“So what then are you doing, wandering together with this large Saṅgha of mendicants during a time of famine and scarcity, with crops blighted and turned to straw? The Buddha is practicing to annihilate, collapse, and ruin families!”

“Well, chief, I recollect ninety-one eons back but I’m not aware of any family that’s been ruined merely by offering some cooked almsfood.[2040] Rather, rich, affluent, and wealthy families—with lots of gold and silver, lots of property and assets, and lots of money and grain—all acquired their wealth because of giving, truth, and restraint.[2041]

Chief, there are eight causes and reasons for the ruin of families. Their ruin stems from rulers, bandits, fire, or flood. Or they lose their savings. Or their business fails due to not applying themselves to work. Or a wastrel is born into the family who squanders and fritters away their wealth. And impermanence is the eighth.[2042] These are the eight causes and reasons for the ruin of families.

Given that these eight reasons are found, suppose someone says this: ‘The Buddha is practicing to annihilate, collapse, and ruin families!’ Unless they give up that speech and that thought, and let go of that view, they will be placed in hell as if delivered there.”

When he said this, Asibandhaka’s son the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.10 With Maṇicūḷaka Maṇicūḷakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground.[2043] Now at that time while the king’s retinue was sitting together in the royal compound this discussion came up among them, “Gold and currency are proper for ascetics who follow the Sakyan. They accept and receive gold and currency.”[2044]

Now at that time the chief Maṇicūḷaka was sitting in that assembly.[2045] He said to that retinue, “Good masters, don’t say that. Gold and currency are not proper for ascetics who follow the Sakyan. They neither accept nor receive gold and currency. They have set aside gems and gold, and quit using gold and currency.” He was able to persuade that assembly.

Then Maṇicūḷaka went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened. He then said, “Answering this way, I trust that I repeat what the Buddha has said, and don’t misrepresent him with an untruth. I trust my explanation is in line with the teaching, and that there are no legitimate grounds for rebuttal or criticism.”

“Indeed, in answering this way you repeat what I’ve said, and don’t misrepresent me with an untruth. Your explanation is in line with the teaching, and there are no legitimate grounds for rebuttal or criticism.

Gold and currency are not proper for ascetics who follow the Sakyan. They neither accept nor receive gold and currency. They have set aside gems and gold, and quit using gold and currency.

If gold and currency were proper for them, then the five kinds of sensual stimulation would also be proper. And if the five kinds of sensual stimulation are proper for them, you should categorically regard them as not having the qualities of an ascetic or a follower of the Sakyan.

Rather, chief, I say this: Straw may be looked for by one needing straw; wood may be looked for by one needing wood; a cart may be looked for by one needing a cart; a workman may be looked for by one needing a workman.[2046] But in any case, there is no way they can accept or look for gold and currency, I say.”

SN 42.11 With Bhadraka Bhadrakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Mallas, near the Mallian town named Uruvelakappa.[2047] Then Bhadraka the village chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2048]

“Please, sir, let the Blessed One teach me the origin and disappearance of suffering.”[2049]

“Chief, if I were to teach you about the origin and disappearance of suffering in connection with the past, saying ‘this is how it was in the past,’ you might have doubts or uncertainties about that.[2050] If I were to teach you about the origin and disappearance of suffering in connection with the future, saying ‘this is how it will be in the future,’ you might have doubts or uncertainties about that. Rather, chief, I will teach you about the origin and disappearance of suffering as I am sitting right here and you are sitting right there. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Bhadraka replied. The Buddha said this:

“What do you think, chief? Are there any people here in Uruvelakappa who, if they were executed, imprisoned, fined, or condemned, it would cause you sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress?”[2051]

“There are, sir.”

“But are there any people here in Uruvelakappa who, if they were executed, imprisoned, fined, or condemned, it would not cause you sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress?”

“There are, sir.”

“What’s the cause, chief, what’s the reason why, if this was to happen to some people it could cause you sorrow, while if it happens to others it does not?”

“The people regarding whom this would give rise to sorrow are those I have desire and passion.[2052] The people regarding whom this would not give rise to sorrow are those I don’t have desire and passion.”

“With this present phenomenon that you have seen, understood, immediately attained, and fathomed, you can apply the same method to the past and future:[2053] ‘All the suffering that arose in the past was rooted and sourced in desire. For desire is the root of suffering. All the suffering that will arise in the future will be rooted and sourced in desire. For desire is the root of suffering.’”

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How well said this was by the Buddha! ‘All the suffering that arises is rooted and sourced in desire.[2054] For desire is the root of suffering.’[2055]

I have a boy called Ciravāsi, who resides in a house away from here. I rise early and dispatch someone, saying: ‘Go, lad, and check on my boy Ciravāsi.’ Until they get back I worry: ‘I hope nothing’s wrong with Ciravāsi!’”

“What do you think, chief? If Ciravāsi was executed, imprisoned, fined, or condemned, would it cause you sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress?”

“How could it not, sir?”

“This too is a way to understand: ‘All the suffering that arises is rooted and sourced in desire. For desire is the root of suffering.’

What do you think, chief? Before you’d seen or heard of Ciravāsi’s mother, did you have any desire or passion or fondness for her?”

“No, sir.”

“Then was it because you saw or heard of her that you had desire or passion or fondness for her?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, chief? If Ciravāsi’s mother was executed, imprisoned, fined, or condemned, would it cause you sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress?”

“How could it not, sir?”

“This too is a way to understand: ‘All the suffering that arises is rooted and sourced in desire. For desire is the root of suffering.’”

SN 42.12 With Rāsiya Rāsiyasutta

Then Rāsiya the chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2056]

“Sir, I have heard this: ‘The ascetic Gotama criticizes all forms of mortification. He categorically condemns and denounces those fervent mortifiers who live rough.’[2057] I trust those who say this repeat what the Buddha has said, and do not misrepresent him with an untruth? Is their explanation in line with the teaching? Are there any legitimate grounds for rebuttal and criticism?”

“Chief, those who say this do not repeat what I have said. They misrepresent me with what is false, hollow, and untrue.

These two extremes should not be cultivated by one gone forth.[2058] Indulgence in sensual pleasures, which is low, crude, ordinary, ignoble, and pointless. And indulgence in self-mortification, which is painful, ignoble, and pointless.

Avoiding these two extremes, the Realized One understood the middle way of practice, which gives vision and knowledge, and leads to peace, direct knowledge, awakening, and extinguishment.

And what is that middle way of practice? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

This, chief, is the middle way of practice that was understood by the Realized One, which gives vision and knowledge, and leads to peace, direct knowledge, awakening, and extinguishment.

There are these three pleasure seekers in the world.[2059] What three? Take a pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using illegitimate, coercive means, and who doesn’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. They make themselves happy and pleased, but don’t share it and make merit. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. They make themselves happy and pleased, and they share it and make merit.

Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using means both legitimate and illegitimate, and coercive and non-coercive. They don’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using means both legitimate and illegitimate, and coercive and non-coercive. They don’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using means both legitimate and illegitimate, and coercive and non-coercive. They make themselves happy and pleased, and they share it and make merit.

Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. They don’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. They make themselves happy and pleased, but don’t share it and make merit. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. They make themselves happy and pleased, and they share it and make merit. They enjoy that wealth tied, infatuated, attached, blind to the drawbacks, and not understanding the escape. Next, a pleasure seeker seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. They make themselves happy and pleased, and they share it and make merit. And they enjoy that wealth untied, uninfatuated, unattached, seeing the drawbacks, and understanding the escape.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using illegitimate, coercive means, and who doesn’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. They may be criticized on three grounds. What three? They seek wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for criticism. They don’t share it and make merit. This is the third ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be criticized on these three grounds.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using illegitimate, coercive means, and who makes themselves happy and pleased, but doesn’t share it and make merit. This pleasure seeker may be criticized on two grounds, and praised on one. What are the two grounds for criticism? They seek wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t share it and make merit. This is the second ground for criticism. What is the one ground for praise? They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the one ground for praise. This pleasure seeker may be criticized on these two grounds, and praised on this one.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using illegitimate, coercive means, and who makes themselves happy and pleased, and shares it and makes merit. This pleasure seeker may be criticized on one ground, and praised on two. What is the one ground for criticism? They seek wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. This is the one ground for criticism. What are the two grounds for praise? They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the first ground for praise. They share it and make merit. This is the second ground for praise. This pleasure seeker may be criticized on this one ground, and praised on these two.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using means both legitimate and illegitimate, and coercive and non-coercive, and who doesn’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. They may be praised on one ground, and criticized on three. What is the one ground for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the one ground for praise. What are the three grounds for criticism? They seek wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for criticism. They don’t share it and make merit. This is the third ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be praised on this one ground, and criticized on these three.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using means both legitimate and illegitimate, and coercive and non-coercive, and makes themselves happy and pleased, but doesn’t share it and make merit. They may be praised on two grounds, and criticized on two. What are the two grounds for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the first ground for praise. They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for praise. What are the two grounds for criticism? They seek wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t share it and make merit. This is the second ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be praised on these two grounds, and criticized on these two.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using means both legitimate and illegitimate, and coercive and non-coercive, and who makes themselves happy and pleased, and shares it and makes merit. They may be praised on three grounds, and criticized on one. What are the three grounds for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the first ground for praise. They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for praise. They share it and make merit. This is the third ground for praise. What is the one ground for criticism? They seek wealth using illegitimate, coercive means. This is the one ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be praised on these three grounds, and criticized on this one.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means, but who doesn’t make themselves happy and pleased, or share it and make merit. They may be praised on one ground, and criticized on two. What is the one ground for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the one ground for praise. What are the two grounds for criticism? They don’t make themselves happy and pleased. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t share it and make merit. This is the second ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be praised on this one ground, and criticized on these two.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means, and who makes themselves happy and pleased, but doesn’t share it and make merit. This pleasure seeker may be praised on two grounds, and criticized on one. What are the two grounds for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the first ground for praise. They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for praise. What is the one ground for criticism? They don’t share it and make merit. This is the one ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be praised on these two grounds, and criticized on this one.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means, and who makes themselves happy and pleased, and shares it and makes merit. But they enjoy that wealth tied, infatuated, attached, blind to the drawbacks, and not understanding the escape. They may be praised on three grounds and criticized on one. What are the three grounds for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the first ground for praise. They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for praise. They share it and make merit. This is the third ground for praise. What is the one ground for criticism? They enjoy that wealth tied, infatuated, attached, blind to the drawbacks, and not understanding the escape. This is the one ground for criticism. This pleasure seeker may be praised on these three grounds, and criticized on this one.

Now, consider the pleasure seeker who seeks wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means, and who makes themselves happy and pleased, and shares it and makes merit. And they enjoy that wealth untied, uninfatuated, unattached, seeing the drawbacks, and understanding the escape. This pleasure seeker may be praised on four grounds. What are the four grounds for praise? They seek wealth using legitimate, non-coercive means. This is the first ground for praise. They make themselves happy and pleased. This is the second ground for praise. They share it and make merit. This is the third ground for praise. They enjoy that wealth untied, uninfatuated, unattached, seeing the drawbacks, and understanding the escape. This is the fourth ground for praise. This pleasure seeker may be praised on these four grounds.

These three fervent mortifiers who live rough are found in the world.[2060] What three?

Take a fervent mortifier who has gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness, thinking: ‘Hopefully I will achieve a skillful quality! Hopefully I will realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones!’[2061] They mortify and torment themselves. But they don’t achieve any skillful quality, or realize any superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones.

Take another fervent mortifier who has gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness, thinking: ‘Hopefully I will achieve a skillful quality! Hopefully I will realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones!’ They mortify and torment themselves. And they achieve a skillful quality, but don’t realize any superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones.

Take another fervent mortifier who has gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness, thinking: ‘Hopefully I will achieve a skillful quality! Hopefully I will realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones!’ They mortify and torment themselves. And they achieve a skillful quality, and they realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones.

In this case, the first fervent mortifier may be criticized on three grounds. What three? They mortify and torment themselves. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t achieve a skillful quality. This is the second ground for criticism. They don’t realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones. This is the third ground for criticism. This fervent mortifier may be criticized on these three grounds.

In this case, the second fervent mortifier may be criticized on two grounds, and praised on one. What are the two grounds for criticism? They mortify and torment themselves. This is the first ground for criticism. They don’t realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones. This is the second ground for criticism. What is the one ground for praise? They achieve a skillful quality. This is the one ground for praise. This fervent mortifier may be criticized on these two grounds, and praised on one.

In this case, the third fervent mortifier may be criticized on one ground, and praised on two. What is the one ground for criticism? They mortify and torment themselves. This is the one ground for criticism. What are the two grounds for praise? They achieve a skillful quality. This is the first ground for praise. They realize a superhuman distinction in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones. This is the second ground for praise. This fervent mortifier may be criticized on this one ground, and praised on two.

There are these three kinds of wearing away that are apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know them for themselves.[2062] What three?

A greedy person, because of greed, intends to hurt themselves, hurt others, and hurt both. When they’ve given up greed they don’t have such intentions. This wearing away is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.

A hateful person, because of hate, intends to hurt themselves, hurt others, and hurt both. When they’ve given up hate they don’t have such intentions. This wearing away is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.

A deluded person, because of delusion, intends to hurt themselves, hurt others, and hurt both. When they’ve given up delusion they don’t have such intentions. This wearing away is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.

These are the three kinds of wearing away that are apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know them for themselves.”

When he said this, Rāsiya the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 42.13 With Pāṭaliya Pāṭaliyasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Koliyans, where they have a town named Uttarakā.[2063] Then Pāṭaliya the chief went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2064]

“Sir, I have heard this: ‘The ascetic Gotama knows deceit.’[2065] I trust those who say this repeat what the Buddha has said, and do not misrepresent him with an untruth? Is their explanation in line with the teaching? Are there any legitimate grounds for rebuttal and criticism? For we don’t want to misrepresent the Blessed One.”

“Chief, those who say this repeat what I have said, and don’t misrepresent me with an untruth. Their explanation is in line with the teaching, and there are no legitimate grounds for rebuttal and criticism.”

“Sir, we didn’t believe that what those ascetics and brahmins said was really true. But it seems the ascetic Gotama is deceitful!”

“Chief, does someone who says ‘I know deceit’ also say ‘I am deceitful’?”

“That’s right, Blessed One! That’s right, Holy One!”

“Well then, chief, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like.

What do you think, chief? Do you know the Koliyan officers with drooping headdresses?”

“I know them, sir.”

“And what’s their job?”

“To put a stop to bandits and to deliver messages for the Koliyans.”

“What do you think, chief? Are the Koliyan officers with drooping headdresses moral or immoral?”

“I know that they’re immoral, of bad character, sir. They are among those in the world who are immoral and of bad character.”[2066]

“Would it be right to say that Pāṭaliya knows the Kolyian officers with drooping headdresses who are immoral, of bad character, so he too must be immoral and of bad character?”

“No, sir. I’m quite different from the Koliyan officers with drooping headdresses; we have quite different characters.”

“So if you can know those officers of bad character while you are not of bad character, why can’t the Realized One know deceit, without being deceitful?

I understand deceit and its result. And I understand how the deceitful practice so that when their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

I understand killing living creatures and its result. And I understand how those who kill living creatures practice so that when their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. I understand stealing … sexual misconduct … lying … backbiting … harsh speech … talking nonsense … covetousness … ill will … wrong view and its result. And I understand how those who have wrong view practice so that when their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

There are some ascetics and brahmins who have this doctrine and view: ‘Everyone who kills living creatures experiences pain and sadness in this very life.[2067] Everyone who steals … commits sexual misconduct … lies experiences pain and sadness in this very life.’

But you can see someone, garlanded and adorned, nicely bathed and anointed, hair and beard dressed, taking his pleasure with women as if he were a king. You might ask someone: ‘My man, what did that man do?’[2068] And they’d reply: ‘My man, that man attacked the king’s enemy and killed them. The king was delighted and gave him this reward. That’s why he’s garlanded and adorned, nicely bathed and anointed, hair and beard dressed, taking his pleasure with women as if he were a king.’

And you can see someone else, his arms tied tightly behind his back with a strong rope. His head is shaven and he’s marched from street to street and from square to square to the beating of a harsh drum. Then he’s taken out the south gate and there, to the south of the city, they chop off his head. You might ask someone: ‘My man, what did that man do?’ And they’d reply: ‘My man, that man is an enemy of the king, and he has murdered a man or a woman. That’s why the rulers arrested him and inflicted such punishment.’

What do you think, chief? Have you seen or heard of such a thing?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“Since this is so, the ascetics and brahmins whose view is that everyone who kills living creatures experiences pain and sadness in this very life: are they right or wrong?”

“They’re wrong, sir.”

“But those who speak hollow, false nonsense: are they moral or immoral?”

“Immoral, sir.”

“And are those who are immoral, of bad character practicing wrongly or rightly?”

“They’re practicing wrongly, sir.”

“And do those who are practicing wrongly have wrong view or right view?”

“They have wrong view, sir.”

“But is it appropriate to have confidence in those of wrong view?”

“No, sir.”

“You can see someone, garlanded and adorned … ‘My man, that man attacked the king’s enemy and took their valuables. The king was delighted and gave him this reward. …’ …

And you can see someone else, his arms tied tightly behind his back … ‘My man, that man took something from a village or wilderness, with the intention to commit theft. That’s why the rulers arrested him and inflicted such punishment.’ What do you think, chief? Have you seen or heard of such a thing?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“Since this is so, the ascetics and brahmins whose view is that everyone who steals experiences pain and sadness in this very life: are they right or wrong? … Is it appropriate to have confidence in them?”

“No, sir.”

“You can see someone, garlanded and adorned … ‘My friend, that man had relations with the wives of an enemy king. The king was delighted and gave him this reward. …’ …

And you can see someone else, his arms tied tightly behind his back … ‘My friend, that man had relations with women and maidens of good families. That’s why the rulers arrested him and inflicted such punishment.’ What do you think, chief? Have you seen or heard of such a thing?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“Since this is so, the ascetics and brahmins whose view is that everyone who commits sexual misconduct experiences pain and sadness in this very life: are they right or wrong? … Is it appropriate to have confidence in them?”

“No, sir.”

“And you can see someone, garlanded and adorned … ‘My man, that man amused the king with lies. The king was delighted and gave him this reward. …’ …

And you can see someone else, his arms tied tightly behind his back … ‘My man, that man has ruined a householder or householder’s child by lying.[2069] That’s why the rulers arrested him and inflicted such punishment.’ What do you think, chief? Have you seen or heard of such a thing?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“Since this is so, the ascetics and brahmins whose view is that everyone who lies experiences pain and sadness in this very life: are they right or wrong?”

“They’re wrong, sir.”

“But those who speak hollow, false nonsense: are they moral or immoral?”

“Immoral, sir.”

“And are those who are immoral, of bad character practicing wrongly or rightly?”

“They’re practicing wrongly, sir.”

“And do those who are practicing wrongly have wrong view or right view?”

“They have wrong view, sir.”

“But is it appropriate to have confidence in those of wrong view?”

“No, sir.

It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! I have a guest house, where there are cots, seats, water jars, and oil lamps. Whenever an ascetic or brahmin comes to stay, I share what I have as best I can. Once it so happened, sir, that four teachers of different views, beliefs, and opinions came to stay at my guest house.[2070]

One teacher had this doctrine and view:[2071] ‘There’s no meaning in giving, sacrifice, or offerings. There’s no fruit or result of good and bad deeds. There’s no afterlife. There’s no such thing as mother and father, or beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there’s no ascetic or brahmin who is rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describes the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’

One teacher had this doctrine and view: ‘There is meaning in giving, sacrifice, and offerings. There are fruits and results of good and bad deeds. There is an afterlife. There are such things as mother and father, and beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there are ascetics and brahmins who are rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describe the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’

One teacher had this doctrine and view: ‘The one who acts does nothing wrong when they punish, mutilate, torture, aggrieve, oppress, intimidate, or when they encourage others to do the same. Nothing bad is done when they kill, steal, break into houses, plunder wealth, steal from isolated buildings, commit highway robbery, commit adultery, and lie.[2072] If you were to reduce all the living creatures of this earth to one heap and mass of flesh with a razor-edged chakram, no evil comes of that, and no outcome of evil. If you were to go along the south bank of the Ganges killing, mutilating, and torturing, and encouraging others to do the same, no evil comes of that, and no outcome of evil. If you were to go along the north bank of the Ganges giving and sacrificing and encouraging others to do the same, no merit comes of that, and no outcome of merit. In giving, self-control, restraint, and truthfulness there is no merit or outcome of merit.’

One teacher had this doctrine and view: ‘The one who acts does a bad deed when they punish, mutilate, torture, aggrieve, oppress, intimidate, or when they encourage others to do the same. A bad deed is done when they kill, steal, break into houses, plunder wealth, steal from isolated buildings, commit highway robbery, commit adultery, and lie. If you were to reduce all the living creatures of this earth to one heap and mass of flesh with a razor-edged chakram, evil comes of that, and an outcome of evil. If you were to go along the south bank of the Ganges killing, mutilating, and torturing, and encouraging others to do the same, evil comes of that, and an outcome of evil. If you were to go along the north bank of the Ganges giving and sacrificing and encouraging others to do the same, merit comes of that, and an outcome of merit. In giving, self-control, restraint, and truthfulness there is merit and outcome of merit.’

I had doubt and uncertainty about that: ‘I wonder who of these respected ascetics and brahmins speaks the truth, and who speaks falsehood?’”

“Chief, no wonder you’re doubting and uncertain. Doubt has come up in you about an uncertain matter.”

“I am quite confident that the Buddha is capable of teaching me so that I can give up this state of uncertainty.”

“Chief, there is immersion based on understanding of principle.[2073] If you gain such mental immersion, you can give up that state of uncertainty.[2074]

And what is immersion based on understanding of principle? It’s when a noble disciple has given up killing living creatures, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, backbiting, harsh speech, talking nonsense, covetousness, ill will, and wrong view.

Then that noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They reflect thus: ‘That teacher who had this doctrine and view: “There’s no meaning in giving, sacrifice, or offerings. There’s no fruit or result of good and bad deeds. There’s no afterlife. There’s no such thing as mother and father, or beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there’s no ascetic or brahmin who is rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describes the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.” If what this good teacher says is true, it’s a sure bet for me to not hurt any creature firm or frail.[2075] I hold a winning hand on both counts, since I’m restrained in body, speech, and mind, and when my body breaks up, after death, I’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’[2076]

Joy springs up in them. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is that immersion based on understanding of principle. If you gain such mental immersion, you can give up that state of uncertainty.

Then that noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They reflect thus: ‘That teacher who had this doctrine and view: “There is meaning in giving, sacrifice, and offerings. There are fruits and results of good and bad deeds. There is an afterlife. There are such things as mother and father, and beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there are ascetics and brahmins who are rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describe the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.” If what this good teacher says is true, it’s a sure bet for me to not hurt any creature firm or frail. I hold a winning hand on both counts, since I’m restrained in body, speech, and mind, and when my body breaks up, after death, I’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’

Joy springs up in them. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is that immersion based on understanding of principle. If you gain such mental immersion, you can give up that state of uncertainty.

Then that noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They reflect thus: ‘That teacher who had this doctrine and view: “The one who acts does nothing wrong when they punish, mutilate, torture, aggrieve, oppress, intimidate, or when they encourage others to do the same. Nothing bad is done when they kill, steal, break into houses, plunder wealth, steal from isolated buildings, commit highway robbery, commit adultery, and lie. If you were to reduce all the living creatures of this earth to one heap and mass of flesh with a razor-edged chakram, no evil comes of that, and no outcome of evil. If you were to go along the south bank of the Ganges killing, mutilating, and torturing, and encouraging others to do the same, no evil comes of that, and no outcome of evil. If you were to go along the north bank of the Ganges giving and sacrificing and encouraging others to do the same, no merit comes of that, and no outcome of merit. In giving, self-control, restraint, and truthfulness there is no merit or outcome of merit.” If what this good teacher says is true, it’s a sure bet for me to not hurt any creature firm or frail. I hold a winning hand on both counts, since I’m restrained in body, speech, and mind, and when my body breaks up, after death, I’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’

Joy springs up in them. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is that immersion based on understanding of principle. If you gain such mental immersion, you can give up that state of uncertainty.

Then that noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They reflect thus: ‘That teacher who had this doctrine and view: “The one who acts does a bad deed when they punish, mutilate, torture, aggrieve, oppress, intimidate, or when they encourage others to do the same. A bad deed is done when they kill, steal, break into houses, plunder wealth, steal from isolated buildings, commit highway robbery, commit adultery, and lie. If you were to reduce all the living creatures of this earth to one heap and mass of flesh with a razor-edged chakram, evil comes of that, and an outcome of evil. If you were to go along the south bank of the Ganges killing, mutilating, and torturing, and encouraging others to do the same, evil comes of that, and an outcome of evil. If you were to go along the north bank of the Ganges giving and sacrificing and encouraging others to do the same, merit comes of that, and an outcome of merit. In giving, self-control, restraint, and truthfulness there is merit and outcome of merit.” If what this good teacher says is true, it’s a sure bet for me to not hurt any creature firm or frail. I hold a winning hand on both counts, since I’m restrained in body, speech, and mind, and when my body breaks up, after death, I’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’

Joy springs up in them. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is that immersion based on understanding of principle. If you gain such mental immersion, you can give up that state of uncertainty.

Then that noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of compassion … rejoicing … equanimity to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of equanimity to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They reflect thus: ‘If what this good teacher says is true, it’s a sure bet for me to not hurt any creature firm or frail. I hold a winning hand on both counts, since I’m restrained in body, speech, and mind, and when my body breaks up, after death, I’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’

Joy springs up in them. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is that immersion based on understanding of principle. If you gain such mental immersion, you can give up that state of uncertainty.”

When he said this, Pāṭaliya the chief said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

The Linked Discourses on chiefs are complete.

Chapter Two

SN 43.12 The Unconditioned Asaṅkhatasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the unconditioned and the path that leads to the unconditioned.[2091] Listen …

And what is the unconditioned? The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called the unconditioned.

And what is the path that leads to the unconditioned? Serenity. This is called the path that leads to the unconditioned.

So, mendicants, I’ve taught you the unconditioned and the path that leads to the unconditioned.

Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicants! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

“Mendicants, I will teach you the unconditioned and the path that leads to the unconditioned. Listen …

And what is the unconditioned? The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called the unconditioned.

And what is the path that leads to the unconditioned? Discernment. This is called the path that leads to the unconditioned. …”

“And what is the path that leads to the unconditioned?

Immersion with placing the mind and keeping it connected. … Immersion without placing the mind, merely keeping it connected. … Immersion without placing the mind or keeping it connected. …

Emptiness immersion. … Signless immersion. … Undirected immersion. …

A mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. … A mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of feelings … A mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the mind … A mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of principles …

A mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. … A mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities are given up. … A mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that skillful qualities arise. … A mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. …

A mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. … A mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … immersion due to mental development … immersion due to inquiry, and active effort. …

A mendicant develops the faculty of faith, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. … A mendicant develops the faculty of energy … mindfulness … immersion … wisdom, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. …

A mendicant develops the power of faith … energy … mindfulness … immersion … wisdom, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. …

A mendicant develops the awakening factor of mindfulness … investigation of principles … energy … rapture … tranquility … immersion … equanimity, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. …

A mendicant develops right view … right purpose … right speech … right action … right livelihood … right effort … right mindfulness … right immersion, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go.

This is called the path that leads to the unconditioned.

So, mendicants, I’ve taught you the unconditioned and the path that leads to the unconditioned.

Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicants! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

SN 43.13 Uninclined Anatasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the uninclined …”[2092]

(Tell in full as in the unconditioned in the previous chapter.)

SN 43.14–43 Undefiled, Etc. Anāsavādisutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the undefiled …”

“the truth …”[2093]

“the far shore …”[2094]

“the subtle …”[2095]

“the very hard to see …”

“the undecrepit …”[2096]

“the everlasting …”[2097]

“the not worn out …”[2098]

“the invisible …”[2099]

“the unproliferated …”[2100]

“the peaceful …”

“freedom from death …”

“the sublime …”

“the state of grace …”[2101]

“the sanctuary …”[2102]

“the ending of craving …”

“the incredible …”[2103]

“the amazing …”

“the untroubled …”[2104]

“the not liable to trouble …”

“extinguishment …”

“the unafflicted …”[2105]

“dispassion …”

“purity …”

“release …”

“not clinging …”[2106]

“the island …”[2107]

“the asylum …”

“the shelter …”

“the refuge …”

SN 43.44 The Final Haven Parāyanasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the final haven and the path that leads to the final haven.[2108] Listen …

And what is the final haven? The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called the final haven.

And what is the path that leads to the final haven? Mindfulness of the body. This is called the path that leads to the final haven.

So, mendicants, I’ve taught you the final haven and the path that leads to the final haven. Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicants! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

(Tell in full as in the unconditioned.)

The Linked Discourses on the unconditioned are complete.

The Chapter on the Undeclared Points

SN 44.1 With Khemā Khemāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.[2109]

Now at that time the nun Khemā was wandering in the land of the Kosalans between Sāvatthī and Sāketa when she took up residence in Toraṇavatthu.[2110] Then King Pasenadi was traveling from Sāketa to Sāvatthī, and he too stayed in Toraṇavatthu for a single night.

Then King Pasenadi addressed a man, “Please, my man, check if there’s a suitable (male) ascetic or brahmin in Toraṇavatthu to whom I can pay homage.”[2111]

“Yes, Your Majesty,” replied that man. He searched all over Toraṇavatthu, but he couldn’t see a suitable ascetic or brahmin for the king to pay homage to.

But he saw that the nun Khemā was staying there, so he went to the king and said to him, “Your Majesty, there’s no (male) ascetic or brahmin in Toraṇavatthu for the king to pay homage to. But there is the nun Khemā, who’s a disciple of the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha. She has a good reputation as being astute, competent, intelligent, learned, a brilliant speaker, and eloquent. Your Majesty may pay homage to her.”[2112]

Then King Pasenadi of Kosala went up to the nun Khemā, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to her:[2113]

“Ma’am, does a realized one still exist after death?”[2114]

“Great king, this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one no longer exist after death?”[2115]

“This too has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one both still exist and no longer exist after death?”[2116]

“This has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one neither still exist nor no longer exist after death?”[2117]

“This too has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Ma’am, when asked these questions, you say that this has not been declared by the Buddha. What’s the cause, what’s the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha?”

“Well then, Great King, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like. What do you think, Great King?

Do you have any accountant or finger-tallier or reckoner who can count the grains of sand in the Ganges, that is,[2118] how many grains of sand there are, how many hundreds or thousands or hundreds of thousands of grains of sand?”

“No, ma’am.”

“Do you have any accountant or finger-tallier or reckoner who can count the water in the ocean, that is, how many gallons of water there are, how many hundreds or thousands or hundreds of thousands of gallons of water?”

“No, ma’am. Why is that? Because the ocean is deep, immeasurable, and hard to fathom.”

“In the same way, Great King, any form by which a realized one might be described has been cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, obliterated, and unable to arise in the future. A realized one is freed from reckoning in terms of form. They’re deep, immeasurable, and hard to fathom, like the ocean. To say that after death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists: none of these apply.

Any feeling … perception … choices … consciousness by which a realized one might be described has been cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, obliterated, and unable to arise in the future. A realized one is freed from reckoning in terms of consciousness. They’re deep, immeasurable, and hard to fathom, like the ocean. To say that after death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists: none of these apply.”

Then King Pasenadi approved and agreed with what the nun Khemā said. Then he rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled her, keeping her on his right, before leaving.

Then on a later occasion King Pasenadi of Kosala went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. He asked the Buddha exactly the same questions he had asked the nun Khemā, and received the same answers.

He said, “It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without contradiction when it comes to the chief matter![2119] This one time I went to the nun Khemā and asked her about this matter. And she explained it to me with these words and phrases, just like the Buddha. It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without contradiction when it comes to the chief matter!

Well, now, sir, I must go. I have many duties, and much to do.”

“Please, Great King, go at your convenience.”

Then King Pasenadi approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. Then he rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled him, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

SN 44.2 With Anurādha Anurādhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.[2120]

Now at that time Venerable Anurādha was staying not far from the Buddha in a wilderness hut. Then several wanderers of other religions went up to Venerable Anurādha and exchanged greetings with him.

When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side and said to him:

“Reverend Anurādha, when a realized one is describing a realized one—a supreme person, highest of people, who has reached the highest point—they describe them in these four ways: After death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists.”

“Reverends, when a realized one is describing a realized one—a supreme person, highest of people, who has reached the highest point—they describe them other than these four ways: After death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists.”

When he said this, the wanderers said to him, “This mendicant must be junior, recently gone forth, or else a foolish, incompetent senior mendicant.” Then, after rebuking Venerable Anurādha by calling him “junior” and “foolish”, the wanderers rose from their seats and left.

Soon after they had left, Anurādha thought, “If those wanderers were to inquire further, how should I answer them so as to repeat what the Buddha has said, and not misrepresent him with an untruth? How should I explain in line with his teaching, so that there would be no legitimate grounds for rebuttal and criticism?”

Then Venerable Anurādha went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“What do you think, Anurādha? Is form permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, is it fit to be regarded thus: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self’?”

“No, sir.”

“Is feeling … perception … choices … consciousness permanent or impermanent?”

“Impermanent, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, is it suffering or happiness?”

“Suffering, sir.”

“But if it’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable, is it fit to be regarded thus: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self’?”

“No, sir.”

“So, Anurādha, you should truly see any kind of form at all—past, future, or present; internal or external; solid or subtle; inferior or superior; far or near: all form—with right understanding: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ Any kind of feeling … perception … choices … consciousness at all—past, future, or present; internal or external; solid or subtle; inferior or superior; far or near: all consciousness—with right understanding: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness. Being disillusioned, desire fades away. When desire fades away they’re freed. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

What do you think, Anurādha? Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies to form?”[2121]

“No, sir.”

“Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies to feeling?” … “… perception?” … “… choices?” … “… consciousness?”

“No, sir.”

“What do you think, Anurādha? Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies in relation to form?”

“No, sir.”

“Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies apart from form?”

“No, sir.”

“Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies in relation to feeling?” “… apart from feeling?” … “… in relation to perception?” … “… apart from perception?” … “… in relation to choices?” … “… apart from choices?” … “… in relation to consciousness?” … “… apart from consciousness?”

“No, sir.”

“What do you think, Anurādha? Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies to one who has form?” … “… feeling?” … “… perception?” … “… choices?” … “… consciousness?”[2122]

“No, sir.”

“What do you think, Anurādha? Do you consider that the label ‘realized one’ applies to that one who is without form?” … “… feeling?” … “… perception?” … “… choices?” … “… consciousness?”

“No, sir.”

“In that case, Anurādha, since a realized one is not found by you as a genuine fact in this very life, is it cogent for you to declare: ‘Reverends, when a realized one is describing a realized one—a supreme person, highest of people, who has reached the highest point—they describe them other than these four ways: After death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists’?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, good, Anurādha! In the past, as today, what I describe is suffering and the cessation of suffering.”

SN 44.3 With Sāriputta and Koṭṭhita (1st) Paṭhamasāriputtakoṭṭhikasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta and Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita were staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana.

Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita came out of retreat, went to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side, and said to Sāriputta:

“Reverend Sāriputta, does a realized one still exist after death?”

“Reverend, this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one no longer exist after death? …

Does a realized one both still exist and no longer exist after death? …

Does a realized one neither still exist nor no longer exist after death?”

“This too has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Reverend, when asked these questions, you say that they have not been declared by the Buddha. What’s the cause, what’s the reason why they have not been declared by the Buddha?”

“Reverend, ‘Does a realized one still exist after death?’ is included in form. ‘Does a realized one no longer exist after death?’ is included in form. ‘Does a realized one both still exist and no longer exist after death?’ is included in form. ‘Does a realized one neither still exist nor no longer exist after death?’ is included in form.

‘Does a realized one still exist after death?’ is included in feeling … perception … choices … consciousness. ‘Does a realized one no longer exist after death?’ is included in consciousness. ‘Does a realized one both still exist and no longer exist after death?’ is included in consciousness. ‘Does a realized one neither still exist nor no longer exist after death?’ is included in consciousness.

This is the cause, this is the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

SN 44.4 With Sāriputta and Koṭṭhita (2nd) Dutiyasāriputtakoṭṭhikasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta and Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita were staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana. …

(The same down as far as:)

“What’s the cause, reverend, what’s the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha?”

“Reverend, not truly knowing and seeing form, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation, one thinks ‘a realized one still exists after death’ or ‘a realized one no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

Not truly knowing or seeing feeling … perception … choices … consciousness, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation, one thinks ‘a realized one still exists after death’ or ‘a realized one no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

Truly knowing and seeing form … feeling … perception … choices … consciousness, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation, one doesn’t think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ or ‘a realized one no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

This is the cause, this is the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

SN 44.5 With Sāriputta and Koṭṭhita (3rd) Tatiyasāriputtakoṭṭhikasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta and Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita were staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana. …

(The same down as far as:)

“What’s the cause, reverend, what’s the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha?”

“Reverend, if you’re not rid of greed, desire, fondness, thirst, passion, and craving for form … feeling … perception … choices … consciousness, you think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

If you are rid of greed for form … feeling … perception … choices … consciousness, you don’t think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

This is the cause, this is the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

SN 44.6 With Sāriputta and Koṭṭhita (4th) Catutthasāriputtakoṭṭhikasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta and Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita were staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana.

Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Sāriputta came out of retreat, went to Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita, and they greeted each other. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Mahākoṭṭhita:

“Reverend Koṭṭhita, does a realized one still exist after death?” …

“Reverend, when asked these questions, you say that this has not been declared by the Buddha. What’s the cause, what’s the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha?”

“Reverend, if you like, love, and enjoy form, and don’t truly see the cessation of form, you think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ or ‘a realized one no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’ or ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

If you like, love, and enjoy feeling … perception … choices … consciousness, and don’t truly see the cessation of consciousness, you think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

If you don’t like, love, and enjoy form … feeling … perception … choices … consciousness, and you truly see the cessation of consciousness, you don’t think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

This is the cause, this is the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“But reverend, could there be another way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha?”

“There could, reverend. If you like, love, and enjoy existence, and don’t truly see the cessation of continued existence, you think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’ If you don’t like, love, and enjoy existence, and you truly see the cessation of continued existence, you don’t think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’ This too is a way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha.”

“But reverend, could there be another way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha?”

“There could, reverend.

If you like, love, and enjoy grasping, and don’t truly see the cessation of grasping, you think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

If you don’t like, love, and enjoy grasping, and you truly see the cessation of grasping, you don’t think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

This too is a way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha.”

“But reverend, could there be another way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha?”

“There could, reverend.

If you like, love, and enjoy craving, and don’t truly see the cessation of craving, you think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

If you don’t like, love, and enjoy craving, and you truly see the cessation of craving, you don’t think ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’

This too is a way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha.”

“But reverend, could there be another way of explaining why this was not declared by the Buddha?”

“Seriously, reverend, what more could you want? For one who is freed due to the ending of craving, there is no cycle of rebirths to be found.”

SN 44.7 With Moggallāna Moggallānasutta

Then the wanderer Vacchagotta went up to Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, and exchanged greetings with him.[2123] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side, and said to Mahāmoggallāna:

“Worthy Moggallāna, is this right: ‘the cosmos is eternal’?”[2124]

“Vaccha, this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Then is this right: ‘the cosmos is not eternal’ … ‘the cosmos is finite’ …[2125] ‘the cosmos is infinite’ … ‘the soul and the body are one and the same’ …[2126] ‘the soul is one thing, the body another’ … ‘a realized one still exists after death’ … ‘a realized one no longer exists after death’ … ‘a realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’ … ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death’?”

“This too has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“What’s the cause, worthy Moggallāna, what’s the reason why, when the wanderers of other religions are asked these questions, they declare one of these to be true? And what’s the reason why, when the ascetic Gotama is asked these questions, he does not declare one of these to be true?”

“Vaccha, the wanderers of other religions regard the eye like this: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self.’ They regard the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind like this: ‘This is mine, I am this, this is my self.’

That’s why, when asked, they declare one of those answers to be true.

The Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha regards the eye like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’ He regards the ear … nose … tongue … body … mind like this: ‘This is not mine, I am not this, this is not my self.’

That’s why, when asked, he does not declare one of those answers to be true.”

Then the wanderer Vacchagotta rose from his seat and went to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side. He asked the Buddha the same questions, and received the same answers.

He said, “It’s incredible, worthy Gotama, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without contradiction when it comes to the chief matter! Just now I went to the ascetic Mahāmoggallāna and asked him about this matter. And he explained it to me with these words and phrases, just like the worthy Gotama. It’s incredible, worthy Gotama, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without contradiction when it comes to the chief matter!”

SN 44.8 With Vacchagotta Vacchagottasutta

Then the wanderer Vacchagotta went up to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side, and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, is this right: ‘the cosmos is eternal’?”

“This has not been declared by me, Vaccha.” …

“Then is this right: ‘a realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death’?”

“This too has not been declared by me.”

“What’s the cause, worthy Gotama, what’s the reason why, when the wanderers of other religions are asked these questions, they declare one of these to be true? And what’s the reason why, when the worthy Gotama is asked these questions, he does not declare one of these to be true?”

“Vaccha, the wanderers of other religions regard form as self, self as having form, form in self, or self in form. They regard feeling … perception … choices … consciousness as self, self as having consciousness, consciousness in self, or self in consciousness.

That’s why, when asked, they declare one of those answers to be true.

The Realized One doesn’t regard form as self, self as having form, form in self, or self in form. He doesn’t regard feeling … perception … choices … consciousness as self, self as having consciousness, consciousness in self, or self in consciousness.

That’s why, when asked, he does not declare one of those answers to be true.”

Then the wanderer Vacchagotta rose from his seat and went to Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side. He asked Mahāmoggallāna the same questions, and received the same answers.

He said, “It’s incredible, worthy Moggallāna, it’s amazing. How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without contradiction when it comes to the chief matter! Just now I went to the ascetic Gotama and asked him about this matter. And he explained it to me with these words and phrases, just like the worthy Moggallāna. It’s incredible, worthy Moggallāna, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without contradiction when it comes to the chief matter!”

SN 44.9 The Debating Hall Kutūhalasālāsutta

Then the wanderer Vacchagotta went up to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side, and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, a few days ago several ascetics, brahmins, and wanderers who follow various other religions were sitting together in the debating hall, and this discussion came up among them:[2127] ‘This Pūraṇa Kassapa leads an order and a community, and tutors a community. He’s a well-known and famous religious founder, deemed holy by many people. When a disciple passes away, he declares that this one is reborn here, while that one is reborn there. And as for a disciple who is a supreme person, highest of people, having reached the highest point, when they pass away he also declares that this one is reborn here, while that one is reborn there.

This bamboo-staffed ascetic Gosāla … the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan … Sañjaya Belaṭṭhiputta … Pakudha Kaccāyana … Ajita of the hair blanket leads an order and a community, and tutors a community. He’s a well-known and famous religious founder, deemed holy by many people. When a disciple passes away, he declares that this one is reborn here, while that one is reborn there. And as for a disciple who is a supreme person, highest of people, having reached the highest point, when they pass away he also declares that this one is reborn here, while that one is reborn there.

This ascetic Gotama leads an order and a community, and tutors a community. He’s a well-known and famous religious founder, deemed holy by many people. When a disciple passes away, he declares that this one is reborn here, while that one is reborn there.

But as for a disciple who is a supreme person, highest of people, having reached the highest point, when they pass away he doesn’t declare that this one is reborn here, while that one is reborn there. Rather, he declares that they have cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit have made an end of suffering.’ I had doubt and uncertainty about that: ‘How on earth can I understand the ascetic Gotama’s teaching?’”

“Vaccha, no wonder you’re doubting and uncertain. Doubt has come up in you about an uncertain matter.

I describe rebirth for someone who grasps fuel, not for someone who does not. It’s like a fire which only burns with fuel, not without fuel.[2128] In the same way I describe rebirth for someone who grasps fuel, not for someone who doesn’t grasp fuel.”

“But when a flame is blown away by the wind, what does the worthy Gotama say is its fuel then?”

“At such a time, I say that it’s fueled by the wind. For the wind is its fuel then.”

“But when someone who is attached has laid down this body and has not been reborn in one of the realms, what does the worthy Gotama say is their fuel then?”[2129]

“When someone who is attached has laid down this body, Vaccha, and has not been reborn in one of the realms, I say they’re fueled by craving. For craving is their fuel then.”

SN 44.10 With Ānanda Ānandasutta

Then the wanderer Vacchagotta went up to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, does the self survive?”[2130] But when he said this, the Buddha kept silent.

“Then does the self not survive?” But for a second time the Buddha kept silent. Then the wanderer Vacchagotta rose from his seat and left.[2131]

And then, not long after Vacchagotta had left, Venerable Ānanda said to the Buddha:

“Sir, why didn’t you answer Vacchagotta’s question?”[2132]

“Ānanda, when Vacchagotta asked me whether the self survives, if I had answered that ‘the self survives’ I would have been siding with the ascetics and brahmins who are eternalists.[2133] When Vacchagotta asked me whether the self does not survive, if I had answered that ‘the self does not survive’ I would have been siding with the ascetics and brahmins who are annihilationists.[2134]

When Vacchagotta asked me whether the self survives, if I had answered that ‘the self survives’, would that have facilitated the arising of the knowledge that[2135] all things are not-self?”

“No, sir.”

“When Vacchagotta asked me whether the self does not survive, if I had answered that ‘the self does not survive’, Vacchagotta—who is already confused—would have got even more confused, thinking: ‘It seems that the self that I once had no longer survives.’”[2136]

SN 44.11 With Sabhiya Kaccāna Sabhiyakaccānasutta

At one time Venerable Sabhiya Kaccāna was staying at Ñātika in the brick house. Then the wanderer Vacchagotta went up to him, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side, and said to Sabhiya Kaccāna:

“Worthy Kaccāna, does a realized one still exist after death?”

“Vaccha, this has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one no longer exist after death?”

“This too has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one both still exist and no longer exist after death?”

“This has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Well then, does a realized one neither still exist nor no longer exist after death?”

“This too has not been declared by the Buddha.”

“Worthy Kaccāna, when asked these questions, you say that this has not been declared by the Buddha. What’s the cause, what’s the reason why this has not been declared by the Buddha?”

“In order to describe him as ‘formed’ or ‘formless’ or ‘percipient’ or ‘non-percipient’ or ‘neither percipient nor non-percipient’, there must be some cause or reason for doing so. But if that cause and reason were to totally and utterly cease without remainder, how could you describe him in any such terms?”

“Worthy Kaccāna, how long has it been since you went forth?”

“Not long, reverend: three years.”

“One who has learned this much in this time, reverend, has learned a lot, who can say what lies ahead!”

The Linked Discourses on undeclared questions are complete.

The Book of the Six Sense Fields is finished.

The Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on Followers of Other Paths

SN 45.41 The Fading Away of Greed Rāgavirāgasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, if wanderers who follow another religion were to ask you: ‘Reverends, what’s the goal of leading the spiritual life under the ascetic Gotama?’ You should answer them like this: ‘The goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha is the fading away of greed.’

If wanderers of other religions were to ask you: ‘Is there a path and a practice for the fading away of greed?’ You should answer them like this: ‘There is a path and a practice for the fading away of greed.’

And what is that path, what is that practice for the fading away of greed? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the path, this is the practice for the fading away of greed.

When questioned by wanderers of other religions, that’s how you should answer them.”

SN 45.42–47 Six Discourses on Giving Up Fetters, Etc. Saṁyojanappahānādisuttachakka

“Mendicants, if wanderers who follow another religion were to ask you: ‘Reverends, what’s the goal of leading the spiritual life under the ascetic Gotama?’ You should answer them like this:

‘The goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha is to give up the fetters.’ …[2202]

‘… to uproot the underlying tendencies.’ …

‘… to completely understand the course of time.’ …[2203]

‘… to end the defilements.’ …

‘… to realize the fruit of knowledge and freedom.’ …

‘… for knowledge and vision.’ …”

SN 45.48 Extinguishment With No Fuel For Grasping Anupādāparinibbānasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, if wanderers who follow another religion were to ask you: ‘Reverends, what’s the goal of leading the spiritual life under the ascetic Gotama?’ You should answer them like this: ‘The goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha is complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping.’

If wanderers of other religions were to ask you: ‘Is there a path and a practice for complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping?’ You should answer them like this: ‘There is a path and a practice for complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping.’

And what is that path, what is that practice for complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the path, this is the practice for complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping.

When questioned by wanderers of other religions, that’s how you should answer them.”

The Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on Diligence

SN 45.139 The Realized One Tathāgatasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, is said to be the best of all sentient beings—be they footless, with two feet, four feet, or many feet; with form or formless; with perception or without perception or with neither perception nor non-perception. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them. A mendicant who is diligent can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant who is diligent develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who is diligent develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.

Mendicants, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, is said to be the best of all sentient beings—be they footless, with two feet, four feet, or many feet; with form or formless; with perception or without perception or with neither perception nor non-perception. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them. A mendicant who is diligent can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant who is diligent develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion. That’s how a mendicant who is diligent develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.

Mendicants, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, is said to be the best of all sentient beings—be they footless, with two feet, four feet, or many feet; with form or formless; with perception or without perception or with neither perception nor non-perception. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them. A mendicant who is diligent can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant who is diligent develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, whose objective, destination, and culmination is freedom from death. That’s how a mendicant who is diligent develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.

Mendicants, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, is said to be the best of all sentient beings—be they footless, with two feet, four feet, or many feet; with form or formless; with perception or without perception or with neither perception nor non-perception. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them. A mendicant who is diligent can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant who is diligent develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment. That’s how a mendicant who is diligent develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

SN 45.140 Footprints Padasutta

“The footprints of all creatures that walk can fit inside an elephant’s footprint. So an elephant’s footprint is said to be the biggest of them all. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them. A mendicant who is diligent can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant who is diligent develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. … That’s how a mendicant who is diligent develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

SN 45.141–145 A Roof Peak Kūṭādisutta

“Mendicants, the rafters of a bungalow all lean to the peak, slope to the peak, and meet at the peak, so the peak is said to be the topmost of them all.[2207] In the same way …”

(Tell in full as in the previous discourse.)

“Of all kinds of fragrant root, spikenard is said to be the best. …”

“Of all kinds of fragrant heartwood, red sandalwood is said to be the best. …”

“Of all kinds of fragrant flower, jasmine is said to be the best. …”

“All lesser kings are vassals of a wheel-turning monarch, so the wheel-turning monarch is said to be the foremost of them all. …”

SN 45.146–148 The Moon, Etc. Candimādisutta

“The radiance of all the stars is not worth a sixteenth part of the moon’s radiance, so the moon’s radiance is said to be the best of them all. …”

“In the autumn, the heavens are sunny and cloudless. And as the sun is rising to the firmament, having dispelled all the darkness of space, it shines and glows and dazzles. …”

“Mendicants, cloth from Kāsi is said to be the best kind of woven cloth. …”

(Tell these in full as in the section on the Realized One.)

The Chapter on Ignorance

SN 45.1 Ignorance Avijjāsutta

So I have heard.[2137] At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, ignorance leads the attainment of unskillful qualities, with lack of conscience and prudence following along.[2138] An ignoramus, sunk in ignorance, produces wrong view.[2139] Wrong view produces wrong purpose.[2140] Wrong purpose produces wrong speech. Wrong speech produces wrong action. Wrong action produces wrong livelihood. Wrong livelihood produces wrong effort. Wrong effort produces wrong mindfulness. Wrong mindfulness produces wrong immersion.

Knowledge leads the attainment of skillful qualities, with conscience and prudence following along.[2141] A knowing one, firm in knowledge, produces right view. Right view produces right purpose. Right purpose produces right speech. Right speech produces right action. Right action produces right livelihood. Right livelihood produces right effort. Right effort produces right mindfulness. Right mindfulness produces right immersion.”

SN 45.2 Half the Spiritual Life Upaḍḍhasutta

So I have heard.[2142] At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, where they have a town named Townsville. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, good friends, companions, and associates are half the spiritual life.”

“Not so, Ānanda! Not so, Ānanda! Good friends, companions, and associates are the whole of the spiritual life. A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant with good friends develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go.[2143] They develop right purpose … right speech … right action … right livelihood … right effort … right mindfulness … right immersion, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with good friends develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.

And here’s another way to understand how good friends are the whole of the spiritual life. For, by relying on me as a good friend, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things. This is another way to understand how good friends are the whole of the spiritual life.”

SN 45.3 Sāriputta Sāriputtasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, good friends, companions, and associates are the whole of the spiritual life.”[2144]

“Good, good, Sāriputta! Good friends, companions, and associates are the whole of the spiritual life. A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path. And how does a mendicant with good friends develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path?

It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with good friends develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.

And here’s another way to understand how good friends are the whole of the spiritual life. For, by relying on me as a good friend, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things. This is another way to understand how good friends are the whole of the spiritual life.”

SN 45.4 Regarding the Brahmin Jānussoṇi Jāṇussoṇibrāhmaṇasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Sāvatthī for alms. He saw the brahmin Jānussoṇi driving out of Sāvatthī in an all-white chariot drawn by mares.[2145] The yoked horses were pure white, as were the ornaments, chariot, upholstery, reins, goad, and canopy. And his turban, robes, sandals were white, as was the chowry fanning him.

When people saw it they exclaimed, “Wow! That’s a divine vehicle! It’s a vehicle fit for divinity!”

Then Ānanda wandered for alms in Sāvatthī. After the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened, adding, “Sir, can you point out a divine vehicle in this teaching and training?”

“I can, Ānanda,” said the Buddha.

“These are all terms for the noble eightfold path: ‘divine vehicle’, or else ‘vehicle of truth’, or else ‘supreme victory in battle’.

When right view is developed and cultivated it culminates with the removal of greed, hate, and delusion. When right purpose … right speech … right action … right livelihood … right effort … right mindfulness … right immersion is developed and cultivated it culminates with the removal of greed, hate, and delusion.

This is a way to understand how these are all terms for the noble eightfold path: ‘divine vehicle’, or else ‘vehicle of truth’, or else ‘supreme victory in battle’.”

That is what the Buddha said.

Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:[2146]

“Of which the qualities of faith and wisdom[2147]
are always yoked to the shaft;
conscience its draft-pole, mind its strap,[2148]
mindfulness its careful driver;

the chariot equipped with ethics,[2149]
its axle absorption, energy its wheel;
equanimity and immersion its draft-pole,[2150]
desirelessness its upholstery;[2151]

of which good will, harmlessness,
and seclusion are its weaponry;
endurance, its shield and armor:[2152]
to sanctuary from the yoke it rolls—

this, originating in oneself,[2153]
is the supreme divine vehicle.
The attentive leave the world in it,
sure of winning the victory.”

SN 45.5 What’s the Goal? Kimatthiyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha … and said to him:

“Sir, sometimes wanderers of other religions ask us: ‘Reverends, what’s the goal of leading the spiritual life under the ascetic Gotama?’ We answer them like this: ‘The goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha is to completely understand suffering.’[2154]

Answering this way, we trust that we repeat what the Buddha has said, and don’t misrepresent him with an untruth. We trust our explanation is in line with the teaching, and that there are no legitimate grounds for rebuttal or criticism.”

“Indeed, in answering this way you repeat what I’ve said, and don’t misrepresent me with an untruth. Your explanation is in line with the teaching, and there are no legitimate grounds for rebuttal or criticism. For the goal of leading the spiritual life under me is to completely understand suffering.

If wanderers of other religions were to ask you: ‘Is there a path and a practice for completely understanding that suffering?’ You should answer them like this: ‘There is.’

And what is that path? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the path and the practice for completely understanding suffering. When questioned by wanderers of other religions, that’s how you should answer them.”

SN 45.6 A Mendicant (1st) Paṭhamaaññatarabhikkhusutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and asked him, “Sir, they speak of this thing called the ‘spiritual path’. What is the spiritual path? And what is the culmination of the spiritual path?”

“Mendicant, the spiritual path is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is the culmination of the spiritual path.”

SN 45.7 A Mendicant (2nd) Dutiyaaññatarabhikkhusutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of ‘the removal of greed, hate, and delusion’. What is this a term for?”

“Mendicant, the removal of greed, hate, and delusion is a term for an element of extinguishment.[2155] It’s used to speak of the ending of defilements.”

When he said this, the mendicant said to the Buddha:

“Sir, they speak of ‘freedom from death’. What is freedom from death? And what is the path that leads to freedom from death?”

“The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called freedom from death. The path that leads to freedom from death is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.”

SN 45.8 Analysis Vibhaṅgasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach and analyze for you the noble eightfold path.[2156] Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what is the noble eightfold path? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

And what is right view?[2157] Knowing about suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.[2158] This is called right view.

And what is right purpose?[2159] The purpose of renunciation, good will, and harmlessness.[2160] This is called right purpose.

And what is right speech?[2161] Refraining from speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. This is called right speech.

And what is right action? Refraining from killing living creatures, stealing, and unchastity.[2162] This is called right action.

And what is right livelihood? It’s when a noble disciple gives up wrong livelihood and earns a living by right livelihood.[2163] This is called right livelihood.

And what is right effort?[2164] It’s when a mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen are given up. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed.[2165] This is called right effort.

And what is right mindfulness?[2166] It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. This is called right mindfulness.

And what is right immersion?[2167] It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected.[2168] As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected.[2169] And with the fading away of rapture, they enter and remain in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’[2170] With the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, they enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.[2171] This is called right immersion.”

SN 45.9 A Spike Sūkasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, suppose a spike of rice or barley was pointing the wrong way. If you trod on it with hand or foot, it is impossible for it to break the skin and produce blood. Why is that? Because the spike is pointing the wrong way.

In the same way, a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the wrong way cannot break ignorance, produce knowledge, and realize extinguishment. Why is that? Because their view is pointing the wrong way.

Suppose a spike of rice or barley was pointing the right way. If you trod on it with hand or foot, it’s possible it may break the skin and produce blood. Why is that? Because the spike is pointing the right way.

In the same way, a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the right way may well break ignorance, produce knowledge, and realize extinguishment. Why is that? Because their view is pointing the right way.

And how does a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the right way break ignorance, give rise to knowledge, and realize extinguishment? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the right way breaks ignorance, gives rise to knowledge, and realizes extinguishment.”

SN 45.10 With Nandiya Nandiyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then the wanderer Nandiya went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him.[2172] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side, and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, how many things, when developed and cultivated, have extinguishment as their target, destination, and culmination?”

“These eight things, when developed and cultivated, have extinguishment as their target, destination, and culmination. What eight? They are: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. These eight things, when developed and cultivated, have extinguishment as their target, destination, and culmination.”

When he said this, the wanderer Nandiya said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

The Chapter on Hard Work

SN 45.149 Hard Work Balasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, all the hard work that gets done depends on the earth and is grounded on the earth. In the same way, a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics.

And how does a mendicant grounded on ethics develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant grounded on ethics develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

“… which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion …”

“… which have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination …”

“… slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment …”

SN 45.150 Seeds Bījasutta

“All the plants and seeds that achieve growth, increase, and maturity do so depending on the earth and grounded on the earth. In the same way, a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics, achieving growth, increase, and maturity in good qualities.

And how does a mendicant develop the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics, achieving growth, increase, and maturity in good qualities? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics, achieving growth, increase, and maturity in good qualities.”

SN 45.151 Dragons Nāgasutta

“Mendicants, dragons grow and wax strong supported by the Himalayas, the king of mountains. When they’re strong they dive into the pools. Then they dive into the lakes, the streams, the rivers, and finally the ocean. There they acquire a great and abundant body. In the same way, a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics, acquiring great and abundant good qualities.

And how does a mendicant develop the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics, acquiring great and abundant good qualities? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path depending on and grounded on ethics, acquiring great and abundant good qualities.”

SN 45.152 Trees Rukkhasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a tree slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. If it was cut off at the root, where would it fall?”

“Sir, it would fall in the direction that it slants, slopes, and inclines.”

“In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

And how does a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.”

SN 45.153 Pots Kumbhasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a pot full of water is tipped over, so the water drains out and doesn’t go back in. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path expels bad, unskillful qualities and doesn’t let them back in.

And how does a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path expel bad, unskillful qualities and not let them back in? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path expels bad, unskillful qualities and doesn’t let them back in.”

SN 45.154 A Spike Sūkasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a spike of rice or barley was pointing the right way. If you trod on it with hand or foot, it’s possible it may break the skin and produce blood. Why is that? Because the spike is pointing the right way.

In the same way, a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the right way may well break ignorance, produce knowledge, and realize extinguishment. Why is that? Because their view is pointing the right way.

And how does a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the right way break ignorance, give rise to knowledge, and realize extinguishment? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant whose view and development of the path is pointing the right way breaks ignorance, gives rise to knowledge, and realizes extinguishment.”

SN 45.155 The Sky Ākāsasutta

“Mendicants, various winds blow in the sky. Winds blow from the east, the west, the north, and the south. There are winds that are dusty and dustless, cool and warm, weak and strong.[2208] In the same way, when the noble eightfold path is developed and cultivated the following are fully developed: the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, the four right efforts, the four bases of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, and the seven awakening factors.

And how are they fully developed? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how they’re fully developed.”

SN 45.156 Storms (1st) Paṭhamameghasutta

“Mendicants, in the last month of summer, when the dust and dirt is stirred up, a large storm out of season disperses and settles it on the spot. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path disperses and stills bad, unskillful qualities on the spot.

How does a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path disperse and still bad, unskillful qualities on the spot? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path disperses and stills bad, unskillful qualities on the spot.”

SN 45.157 Storms (2nd) Dutiyameghasutta

“Mendicants, when a large storm has blown up, a strong wind disperses and settles it as it proceeds. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path disperses and stills bad, unskillful qualities as they proceed.

And how does a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path disperse and still bad, unskillful qualities as they proceed? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path disperses and stills bad, unskillful qualities as they proceed.”

SN 45.158 A Ship Nāvāsutta

“Mendicants, suppose there was a sea-faring ship bound together with ropes. For six months they deteriorated in the water. Then in the cold season it was hauled up on dry land, where the ropes were weathered by wind and sun. When the monsoon clouds soaked it with rain, the ropes would readily collapse and rot away.[2209] In the same way, when a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path their fetters readily collapse and rot away.

And how do they develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path so that their fetters readily collapse and rot away? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how they develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path so that their fetters readily collapse and rot away.”

SN 45.159 A Guest House Āgantukasutta

“Mendicants, suppose there was a guest house. Lodgers come from the east, west, north, and south. Aristocrats, brahmins, peasants, and menials all stay there.[2210] In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path completely understands by direct knowledge the things that should be completely understood by direct knowledge. They give up by direct knowledge the things that should be given up by direct knowledge. They realize by direct knowledge the things that should be realized by direct knowledge. They develop by direct knowledge the things that should be developed by direct knowledge.

And what are the things that should be completely understood by direct knowledge? It should be said: the five grasping aggregates. What five? That is: form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness. These are the things that should be completely understood by direct knowledge. And what are the things that should be given up by direct knowledge? Ignorance and craving for continued existence. These are the things that should be given up by direct knowledge. And what are the things that should be realized by direct knowledge? Knowledge and freedom. These are the things that should be realized by direct knowledge. And what are the things that should be developed by direct knowledge? Serenity and discernment. These are the things that should be developed by direct knowledge.

And how does a mendicant develop the noble eightfold path in this way? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the eightfold path in this way.”

SN 45.160 A River Nadīsutta

“Mendicants, suppose that, although the Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east,[2211] a large crowd were to come along with a spade and basket, saying: ‘We’ll make this Ganges River slant, slope, and incline to the west!’

What do you think, mendicants? Would they succeed?”

“No, sir. Why is that? The Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. It’s not easy to make it slant, slope, and incline to the west. That large crowd will eventually get weary and frustrated.”

“In the same way, while a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path, if rulers or their chief ministers, friends or colleagues, relatives or kin should invite them to accept wealth, saying: ‘Please, my man, why let these ocher robes torment you? Why follow the practice of shaving your head and carrying an alms bowl? Come, return to a lesser life, enjoy wealth, and make merit!’ It is quite impossible for a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path to resign the training and return to a lesser life. Why is that? Because for a long time that mendicant’s mind has slanted, sloped, and inclined to seclusion. So it’s impossible for them to return to a lesser life.

And how does a mendicant develop the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

The Chapter on Searches

SN 45.161 Searches Esanāsutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path.[2212] These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to directly know these three searches. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed to directly know these three searches.”

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to directly know these three searches. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed to directly know these three searches.”

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to directly know these three searches. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, whose objective, destination, and culmination is freedom from death.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed to directly know these three searches.”

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to directly know these three searches. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed to directly know these three searches.”

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to completely understand …”

(Tell in full with “completely understand” instead of “directly know”.)

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to finish …”

(Tell in full with “finish” instead of “directly know”.)

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to give up …”

(Tell in full with “give up” instead of “directly know”.)

SN 45.162 Discriminations Vidhāsutta

“Mendicants, there are three kinds of discrimination. What three? One discriminates, thinking that ‘I’m better’ or ‘I’m equal’ or ‘I’m worse’. These are the three kinds of discrimination.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three kinds of discrimination. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three kinds of discrimination.”

(Tell in full as in the section on searches.)

SN 45.163 Defilements Āsavasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three defilements. What three? The defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. These are the three defilements.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three defilements.”

SN 45.164 States of Existence Bhavasutta

“There are these three states of existence. What three? Existence in the sensual realm, the realm of luminous form, and the formless realm. These are the three states of existence.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three states of existence.”

SN 45.165 Forms of Suffering Dukkhatāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three forms of suffering.[2213] What three? The suffering inherent in painful feeling; the suffering inherent in conditions; and the suffering inherent in perishing.[2214] These are the three forms of suffering.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three forms of suffering.”

SN 45.166 Kinds of Barrenness Khilasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three kinds of barrenness. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion. These are the three kinds of barrenness.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three kinds of barrenness.”

SN 45.167 Stains Malasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three stains. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion. These are the three stains.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three stains.”

SN 45.168 Troubles Nīghasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three troubles. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion. These are the three troubles.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three troubles.”

SN 45.169 Feelings Vedanāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings: What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three feelings.”

SN 45.170 Craving Taṇhāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three cravings. What three? Craving for sensual pleasures, craving for continued existence, and craving for nonexistence. These are the three cravings.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three cravings. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three cravings.”

Thirst[2215]

“Mendicants, there are these three thirsts. What three? Thirst for sensual pleasures, thirst to continue existence, and thirst to end existence.

For the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three thirsts … … which culminates in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion. … whose objective, destination, and culmination is freedom from death. … which slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three thirsts.”

The Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on the Ganges

SN 45.91 Slanting East Paṭhamapācīnaninnasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, the Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

And how does a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.”

SN 45.92–95 Four Discourses on Slanting East Dutiyādipācīnaninnasuttacatukka

“Mendicants, the Yamunā River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. …”

“… the Aciravatī River …”

“… the Sarabhū River …”

“… the Mahī River …”

SN 45.96 Sixth Discourse on Slanting East Chaṭṭhapācīnaninnasutta

“Mendicants, all the great rivers—that is, the Ganges, Yamunā, Aciravatī, Sarabhū, and Mahī—slant, slope, and incline toward the east. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

And how does a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.”

SN 45.97 Slanting to the Ocean Paṭhamasamuddaninnasutta

“Mendicants, the Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the ocean. In the same way, a mendicant who develops the noble eightfold path slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment. …”

SN 45.98–102 Five Discourses on Slanting to the Ocean Dutiyādisamuddaninnasuttapañcaka

“Mendicants, the Yamunā River slants, slopes, and inclines to the ocean. …”

“… the Aciravatī River …”

“… the Sarabhū River …”

“… the Mahī River …”

“… all the great rivers …”

The Chapter on the Wrong Way

SN 45.21 The Wrong Way Micchattasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the wrong way and the right way.[2189] Listen …

And what is the wrong way? It is wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called the wrong way.

And what is the right way? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the right way.”

SN 45.22 Unskillful Qualities Akusaladhammasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you skillful and unskillful qualities. Listen …

And what are unskillful qualities? They are wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. These are called unskillful qualities.

And what are skillful qualities? They are right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. These are called skillful qualities.”

SN 45.23 Practice (1st) Paṭhamapaṭipadāsutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the wrong practice and the right practice.[2190] Listen …

And what’s the wrong practice? It is wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called the wrong practice.

And what’s the right practice? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the right practice.”

SN 45.24 Practice (2nd) Dutiyapaṭipadāsutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I don’t praise wrong practice for laypeople or renunciates.[2191] Because of wrong practice, neither laypeople nor renunciates succeed in the system of the skillful teaching.

And what’s the wrong practice? It is wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called the wrong practice. I don’t praise wrong practice for lay people or renunciates. Because of wrong practice, neither laypeople nor renunciates succeed in the system of the skillful teaching.

I praise right practice for laypeople and renunciates. Because of right practice, both laypeople and renunciates succeed in the system of the skillful teaching. And what’s the right practice? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the right practice. I praise right practice for laypeople and renunciates.

Because of right practice, both laypeople and renunciates succeed in the system of the skillful teaching.”

SN 45.25 An Untrue Person (1st) Paṭhamaasappurisasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you an untrue person and a true person. Listen …

And what is an untrue person? It’s someone who has wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called an untrue person.

And what is a true person? It’s someone who has right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called a true person.”

SN 45.26 An Untrue Person (2nd) Dutiyaasappurisasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you an untrue person and an even more untrue person, a true person and an even truer person. Listen …

And what is an untrue person? It’s someone who has wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called an untrue person.

And what is an even more untrue person? It’s someone who has wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom.[2192] This is called an even more untrue person.

And what is a true person? It’s someone who has right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called a true person.

And what is an even truer person? It’s someone who has right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called an even truer person.”

SN 45.27 Pots Kumbhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“A pot without a stand is easy to overturn, but if it has a stand it’s hard to overturn. In the same way, a mind without a stand is easy to overturn, but if it has a stand it’s hard to overturn.

And what’s the stand for the mind? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the stand for the mind.

A pot without a stand is easy to overturn, but if it has a stand it’s hard to overturn. In the same way, a mind without a stand is easy to overturn, but if it has a stand it’s hard to overturn.”[2193]

SN 45.28 Immersion Samādhisutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you noble right immersion with its vital conditions and its prerequisites.[2194] Listen …

And what is noble right immersion with its vital conditions and its prerequisites? There are right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, and right mindfulness.

Unification of mind with these seven factors as prerequisites is called noble right immersion ‘with its vital conditions’ and also ‘with its prerequisites’.”

SN 45.29 Feeling Vedanāsutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to completely understand these three feelings. What is the noble eightfold path? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

This noble eightfold path should be developed to completely understand these three feelings.”

SN 45.30 With Uttiya Uttiyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Uttiya went up to the Buddha … and asked him,[2195] “Just now, sir, as I was in private retreat this thought came to mind. ‘The Buddha has spoken of the five kinds of sensual stimulation. What are they?’”

“Good, good, Uttiya! I have spoken of these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation that I’ve spoken of.

The noble eightfold path should be developed to give up these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What is the noble eightfold path? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed to give up these five kinds of sensual stimulation.”

The Chapter on Floods

SN 45.171 Floods Oghasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are these four floods. What four? The floods of sensuality, desire to be reborn, views, and ignorance. These are the four floods.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these four floods.”

(Tell in full as in the section on searches.)

SN 45.172 Yokes Yogasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four yokes. What four? The yokes of sensual pleasures, future lives, views, and ignorance. These are the four yokes.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these four yokes.”

SN 45.173 Grasping Upādānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of grasping. What four? Grasping at sensual pleasures, views, precepts and observances, and theories of a self. These are the four kinds of grasping.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these four kinds of grasping.”

SN 45.174 Personal Ties Ganthasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four ties. What four? The personal ties to covetousness, ill will, misapprehension of precepts and observances, and the insistence that this is the only truth. These are the four ties.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these four ties.”

SN 45.175 Tendencies Anusayasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven underlying tendencies. What seven? The underlying tendencies of sensual desire, aversion, views, doubt, conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. These are the seven underlying tendencies.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these seven underlying tendencies.”

SN 45.176 Kinds of Sensual Stimulation Kāmaguṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five kinds of sensual stimulation.”

SN 45.177 Hindrances Nīvaraṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five hindrances. What five? The hindrances of sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. These are the five hindrances.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five hindrances.”

SN 45.178 Grasping Aggregates Upādānakkhandhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five grasping aggregates. What five? The grasping aggregates of form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness. These are the five grasping aggregates.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five grasping aggregates.”

SN 45.179 Lower Fetters Orambhāgiyasutta

“Mendicants, there are five lower fetters.[2216] What five? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, sensual desire, and ill will. These are the five lower fetters.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five lowers fetters.”

SN 45.180 Higher Fetters Uddhambhāgiyasutta

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

The noble eightfold path should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters. What is the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion …” “… whose objective, destination, and culmination is freedom from death …” “… which slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment.

This is the noble eightfold path that should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

The Linked Discourses on the Path, the first section.

The Chapter on Practice

SN 45.31 Practice (1st) Paṭhamapaṭipattisutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the wrong practice and the right practice. Listen …

And what’s the wrong practice? It is wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called the wrong practice.

And what’s the right practice? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the right practice.”

SN 45.32 Practice (2nd) Dutiyapaṭipattisutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you one practicing wrongly and one practicing rightly. Listen …

And who is practicing wrongly? It’s someone who has wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. This is called one practicing wrongly.

And who is practicing rightly? It’s someone who has right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called one practicing rightly.”

SN 45.33 Missed Out Viraddhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, whoever has missed out on the noble eightfold path has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.[2196] Whoever has undertaken the noble eightfold path has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.

And what is the noble eightfold path? It is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

Whoever has missed out on the noble eightfold path has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken the noble eightfold path has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 45.34 Going to the Far Shore Pāraṅgamasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, when these eight things are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore. What eight? They are right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. When these eight things are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Few are those among humans[2197]
who cross to the far shore.
The rest just run
around on the near shore.

When the teaching is well explained,
the people who practice accordingly
will cross over
Death’s dominion so hard to pass.

Rid of dark qualities,[2198]
an astute person would develop the bright.[2199]
Having left home for homelessness[2200]
in seclusion, where joy is hard,

they’d long for satisfaction there.
Forsaking sensual pleasures, owning nothing,
an astute person would cleanse themselves
of mental corruptions.

And those whose minds are rightly developed
in the awakening factors;[2201]
who, letting go of attachments,
delight in not grasping—
with defilements ended, brilliant,
they are quenched in this world.”

SN 45.35 The Ascetic Life (1st) Paṭhamasāmaññasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the ascetic life and the fruits of the ascetic life. Listen …

And what is the ascetic life? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the ascetic life.

And what are the fruits of the ascetic life? The fruits of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, and perfection. These are called the fruits of the ascetic life.”

SN 45.36 The Ascetic Life (2nd) Dutiyasāmaññasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the ascetic life and the goal of the ascetic life. Listen …

And what is the ascetic life? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the ascetic life.

And what is the goal of the ascetic life? The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called the goal of the ascetic life.”

SN 45.37 The Brahmin Life (1st) Paṭhamabrahmaññasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you life as a brahmin and the fruits of life as a brahmin. Listen …

And what is life as a brahmin? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called life as a brahmin.

And what are the fruits of life as a brahmin? The fruits of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, and perfection. These are called the fruits of life as a brahmin.”

SN 45.38 The Brahmin Life (2nd) Dutiyabrahmaññasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you life as a brahmin and the goal of life as a brahmin. Listen …

And what is life as a brahmin? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called life as a brahmin.

And what is the goal of life as a brahmin? The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called the goal of life as a brahmin.”

SN 45.39 The Spiritual Path (1st) Paṭhamabrahmacariyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the spiritual path and the fruits of the spiritual path. Listen …

And what is the spiritual path? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the spiritual path.

And what are the fruits of the spiritual path? The fruits of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, and perfection. These are called the fruits of the spiritual path.”

SN 45.40 The Spiritual Path (2nd) Dutiyabrahmacariyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you the spiritual path and the goal of the spiritual path. Listen …

And what is the spiritual path? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the spiritual path.

And what is the goal of the spiritual path? The ending of greed, hate, and delusion. This is called the goal of the spiritual path.”

The Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on the Sun

SN 45.49 Good Friends (1st) Kalyāṇamittasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way good friendship is the forerunner and harbinger of the noble eightfold path for a mendicant. A mendicant with good friends can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant with good friends develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with good friends develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

SN 45.50–54 Five Discourses on Accomplishment in Ethics, Etc. (1st) Sīlasampadādisuttapañcaka

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way accomplishment in ethics is the forerunner and harbinger of the arising of the noble eightfold path for a mendicant. A mendicant accomplished in ethics can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path. …” …

“… accomplishment in enthusiasm …”[2204]

“… accomplishment in self-development …”[2205]

“… accomplishment in view …”[2206]

“… accomplishment in diligence …”

SN 45.55 Accomplishment in Rational Application of Mind (1st) Yonisomanasikārasampadāsutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way accomplishment in rational application of mind is the forerunner and harbinger of the noble eightfold path for a mendicant. A mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

SN 45.56 Good Friends (2nd) Dutiyakalyāṇamittasutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way good friendship is the forerunner and harbinger of the noble eightfold path for a mendicant. A mendicant with good friends can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant with good friends develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion. That’s how a mendicant with good friends develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

SN 45.57–61 Five Discourses on Accomplishment in Ethics, Etc. (2nd) Dutiyasīlasampadādisuttapañcaka

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way accomplishment in ethics is the forerunner and harbinger of the noble eightfold path for a mendicant. …”

“… accomplishment in enthusiasm …”

“… accomplishment in self-development …”

“… accomplishment in view …”

“… accomplishment in diligence …”

SN 45.62 Accomplishment in Rational Application of Mind (2nd) Dutiyayonisomanasikārasampadāsutta

“… accomplishment in rational application of mind. A mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind can expect to develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path.

And how does a mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind develop and cultivate the noble eightfold path? It’s when a mendicant develops right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion, which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion. That’s how a mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind develops and cultivates the noble eightfold path.”

The Chapter on Meditation

SN 45.11 Meditation (1st) Paṭhamavihārasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I wish to go on retreat for a fortnight.[2173] No-one should approach me, except the one who brings my almsfood.”

“Yes, sir,” replied those mendicants. And no-one approached him, except the one who brought the almsfood.

Then after a fortnight had passed, the Buddha came out of retreat and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, I’ve been practicing part of the meditation I practiced when I was first awakened.[2174] I understand that there’s feeling conditioned by wrong view[2175] and feeling conditioned by right view. …[2176] There’s feeling conditioned by wrong immersion,[2177] and feeling conditioned by right immersion.

There’s feeling conditioned by desire.[2178] There’s feeling conditioned by thought.[2179] There’s feeling conditioned by perception.[2180] As long as desire, thought, and perception are not stilled, there is feeling conditioned by that.[2181] When desire, thought, and perception are stilled, there is feeling conditioned by that.[2182]

There is effort to attain the unattained. When that state has been attained, there is also feeling conditioned by that.”[2183]

SN 45.12 Meditation (2nd) Dutiyavihārasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I wish to go on retreat for three months. No-one should approach me, except the one who brings my almsfood.”

“Yes, sir,” replied those mendicants. And no-one approached him, except the one who brought the almsfood.

Then after three months had passed, the Buddha came out of retreat and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, I’ve been practicing part of the meditation I practiced when I was first awakened.

I understand that there’s feeling conditioned by wrong view and by the settling of wrong view, by right view and by the settling of right view. … There’s feeling conditioned by wrong immersion and by the settling of wrong immersion, by right immersion and by the settling of right immersion.

There’s feeling conditioned by desire and by the settling of desire. There’s feeling conditioned by thought, and by the settling of thought. There’s feeling conditioned by perception, and by the settling of perception. As long as desire, thought, and perception are not stilled, there is feeling conditioned by that. When desire, thought, and perception are stilled, there is feeling conditioned by that.

There is effort to attain the unattained. When that state has been attained, there is also feeling conditioned by that.”

SN 45.13 A Trainee Sekkhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and asked him, “Sir, they speak of the one called ‘a trainee’. How is a trainee defined?”

“Mendicant, it’s someone who has a trainee’s right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.[2184] That’s how a trainee is defined.”

SN 45.14 Arising (1st) Paṭhamauppādasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these eight things don’t arise to be developed and cultivated except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared.[2185] What eight? They are: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. These eight things don’t arise to be developed and cultivated except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared.”

SN 45.15 Arising (2nd) Dutiyauppādasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these eight things don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training.[2186] What eight? They are: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. These are the eight things that don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training.”

SN 45.16 Purified (1st) Paṭhamaparisuddhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these eight things don’t arise to be purified, bright, flawless, and rid of corruptions except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared. What eight? They are: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. These eight things don’t arise to be purified, bright, flawless, and rid of corruptions except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared.”

SN 45.17 Purified (2nd) Dutiyaparisuddhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these eight things don’t arise to be purified, bright, flawless, and rid of corruptions apart from the Holy One’s training. What eight? They are: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. These eight things don’t arise to be purified, bright, flawless, and rid of corruptions apart from the Holy One’s training.”

SN 45.18 At the Chicken Monastery (1st) Paṭhamakukkuṭārāmasutta

So I have heard. At one time the venerables Ānanda and Bhadda were staying near Pāṭaliputta, in the Chicken Monastery.[2187] Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Bhadda came out of retreat, went to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Ānanda:

“Reverend, they speak of this thing called ‘not the spiritual path’.[2188] What is not the spiritual path?”

“Good, good, Reverend Bhadda! Your approach and eloquence are excellent, and it’s a good question. For you asked: ‘They speak of this thing called “not the spiritual path”. What is not the spiritual path?’”

“Yes, reverend.”

“What is not the spiritual path is simply the wrong eightfold path, that is: wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion.”

SN 45.19 At the Chicken Monastery (2nd) Dutiyakukkuṭārāmasutta

At Pāṭaliputta.

“Reverend, they speak of this thing called the ‘spiritual path’. What is the spiritual path? And what is the culmination of the spiritual path?”

“Good, good, Reverend Bhadda! Your approach and eloquence are excellent, and it’s a good question. For you asked: ‘They speak of this thing called “the spiritual path”. What is the spiritual path? And what is the culmination of the spiritual path?’”

“Yes, reverend.”

“The spiritual path is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

The ending of greed, hate, and delusion: this is the culmination of the spiritual path.”

SN 45.20 At the Chicken Monastery (3rd) Tatiyakukkuṭārāmasutta

At Pāṭaliputta.

“Reverend, they speak of this thing called the ‘spiritual path’. What is the spiritual path? Who is someone on the spiritual path? And what is the culmination of the spiritual path?”

“Good, good, Reverend Bhadda! Your approach and eloquence are excellent, and it’s a good question. …

The spiritual path is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

Someone who possesses this noble eightfold path is called someone on the spiritual path.

The ending of greed, hate, and delusion: this is the culmination of the spiritual path.”

The Chapter on Breathing

SN 46.57 A Skeleton Aṭṭhikamahapphalasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, when the perception of a skeleton is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial.[2286] How so? It’s when a mendicant develops the perception of a skeleton together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how the perception of a skeleton, when developed and cultivated, is very fruitful and beneficial.”

“When the perception of a skeleton is developed and cultivated you can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return. How so? …”

“Mendicants, when the perception of a skeleton is developed and cultivated it leads to great benefit. How so? …”

“Mendicants, when the perception of a skeleton is developed and cultivated it leads to great sanctuary from the yoke. How so? …”

“Mendicants, when the perception of a skeleton is developed and cultivated it leads to great inspiration. How so? …”

“Mendicants, when the perception of a skeleton is developed and cultivated it leads to dwelling in great ease. How so? …”

SN 46.58 Worm-Infested Puḷavakasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of a worm-infested corpse is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.59 Livid Vinīlakasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of a livid corpse is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.60 Split Open Vicchiddakasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of a split open corpse is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.61 Bloated Uddhumātakasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of a bloated corpse is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.62 Love Mettāsutta

“Mendicants, when love is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.63 Compassion Karuṇāsutta

“Mendicants, when compassion is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.64 Rejoicing Muditāsutta

“Mendicants, when rejoicing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.65 Equanimity Upekkhāsutta

“Mendicants, when equanimity is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.66 Breathing Ānāpānasutta

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”[2287]

The Chapter on the Wheel-Turning Monarch

SN 46.41 Discriminations Vidhāsutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, all the ascetics and brahmins in the past who have given up the three discriminations have done so by developing and cultivating the seven awakening factors.[2265] All the ascetics and brahmins in the future who will give up the three discriminations will do so by developing and cultivating the seven awakening factors. All the ascetics and brahmins in the present who are giving up the three discriminations do so by developing and cultivating the seven awakening factors.

What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. All the ascetics and brahmins in the past … future … and present who give up the three discriminations do so by developing and cultivating the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.42 A Wheel-Turning Monarch Cakkavattisutta

“Mendicants, when a Wheel-Turning Monarch appears seven treasures appear.[2266] What seven? The wheel, the elephant, the horse, the jewel, the woman, the householder, and the commander. When a Wheel-Turning Monarch appears these seven treasures appear.

When a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha appears the seven treasures of the awakening factors appear. What seven? The treasures of the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. When a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha appears these seven treasures of the awakening factors appear.”

SN 46.43 About Māra Mārasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you a path for crushing Māra’s army.[2267] Listen …

And what is that path? It is the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. This is the path for crushing Māra’s army.”

SN 46.44 Witless Duppaññasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and asked him, “Sir, they speak of ‘a witless idiot’. How is a witless idiot defined?”

“Mendicant, they’re called a witless idiot because they haven’t developed and cultivated the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. They’re called a witless idiot because they haven’t developed and cultivated these seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.45 Wise Paññavantasutta

“Sir, they speak of a one ‘wise and clever’. How is a person who is wise and clever defined?”

“Mendicant, they’re called wise and clever because they’ve developed and cultivated the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. They’re called wise and clever because they’ve developed and cultivated these seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.46 Poor Daliddasutta

“Sir, they speak of someone who is ‘poor’. How is a poor person defined?”

“Mendicant, they’re called poor because they haven’t developed and cultivated the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. They’re called poor because they haven’t developed and cultivated these seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.47 Prosperous Adaliddasutta

“Sir, they speak of someone who is ‘prosperous’. How is a prosperous person defined?”

“Mendicant, they’re called prosperous because they’ve developed and cultivated the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. They’re called prosperous because they’ve developed and cultivated these seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.48 The Sun Ādiccasutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise.

In the same way, for a mendicant good friendship is the forerunner and harbinger of the arising of the seven awakening factors. A mendicant with good friends can expect to develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors.

And how does a mendicant with good friends develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with good friends develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.49 Interior Ajjhattikaṅgasutta

“Taking into account interior factors, mendicants, I do not see a single one that gives rise to the seven awakening factors like rational application of mind. …”

SN 46.50 Exterior Bāhiraṅgasutta

“Taking into account exterior factors, mendicants, I do not see a single one that gives rise to the seven awakening factors like good friendship. …”

The Chapter on Sick

SN 46.11 Living Creatures Pāṇasutta

“Mendicants, whatever living creatures engage in the four postures—sometimes walking, sometimes standing, sometimes sitting, sometimes lying down—all do so depending on the earth and grounded on the earth. In the same way, a mendicant develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors depending on and grounded on ethics.

And how does a mendicant develop the seven awakening factors depending on and grounded on ethics? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors depending on and grounded on ethics.”

SN 46.12 The Simile of the Sun (1st) Paṭhamasūriyūpamasutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way, for a mendicant good friendship is the forerunner and harbinger of the arising of the seven awakening factors. A mendicant with good friends can expect to develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors.

And how does a mendicant with good friends develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with good friends develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.13 The Simile of the Sun (2nd) Dutiyasūriyūpamasutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way, for a mendicant rational application of mind is the forerunner and harbinger of the arising of the seven awakening factors. A mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind can expect to develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors.

And how does a mendicant with rational application of mind develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with rational application of mind develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.14 Sick (1st) Paṭhamagilānasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. Now at that time Venerable Mahākassapa was staying in the Pipphali cave, and he was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat, went to Venerable Mahākassapa, sat down on the seat spread out, and said to him:

“I hope you’re keeping well, Kassapa, I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”[2250]

“Kassapa, I’ve rightly explained these seven awakening factors. When developed and cultivated, they lead to direct knowledge, to awakening, and to extinguishment. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven awakening factors that I’ve rightly explained. When developed and cultivated, they lead to direct knowledge, to awakening, and to extinguishment.”

“Indeed, Blessed One, these are awakening factors! Indeed, Holy One, these are awakening factors!”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, Venerable Mahākassapa approved what the Buddha said. And that’s how he recovered from that illness.[2251]

SN 46.15 Sick (2nd) Dutiyagilānasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. Now at that time Venerable Mahāmoggallāna was staying on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain, and he was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat, went to Venerable Moggallāna, sat down on the seat spread out, and said to him:

“I hope you’re keeping well, Moggallāna, I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”

“Moggallāna, I’ve rightly explained these seven awakening factors. When developed and cultivated, they lead to direct knowledge, to awakening, and to extinguishment. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven awakening factors that I’ve rightly explained. When developed and cultivated, they lead to direct knowledge, to awakening, and to extinguishment.”

“Indeed, Blessed One, these are awakening factors! Indeed, Holy One, these are awakening factors!”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, Venerable Mahāmoggallāna approved what the Buddha said. And that’s how he recovered from that illness.

SN 46.16 Sick (3rd) Tatiyagilānasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. Now at that time he was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then Venerable Mahācunda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Cunda, express your understanding of the awakening factors.”

“Sir, the Buddha has rightly explained these seven awakening factors. When developed and cultivated, they lead to direct knowledge, to awakening, and to extinguishment. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven awakening factors that the Buddha has rightly explained. When developed and cultivated, they lead to direct knowledge, to awakening, and to extinguishment.”

“Indeed, Cunda, these are awakening factors! Indeed, Cunda, these are awakening factors!”

That is what Cunda said, and the Teacher concurred. And that’s how the Buddha recovered from that illness.

SN 46.17 Going to the Far Shore Pāraṅgamasutta

“Mendicants, when these seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, lead to going from the near shore to the far shore.

Few are those among humans[2252]
who cross to the far shore.
The rest just run
around on the near shore.

When the teaching is well explained,
the people who practice accordingly
will cross over
Death’s dominion so hard to pass.

Rid of dark qualities,
an astute person would develop the bright.
Having left home for homelessness
in seclusion, where joy is hard,

they’d long for satisfaction there.
Forsaking sensual pleasures, owning nothing,
an astute person would cleanse themselves
of mental corruptions.

And those whose minds are rightly developed
in the awakening factors;
who, letting go of attachments,
delight in not grasping—
with defilements ended, brilliant,
they are quenched in this world.”

SN 46.18 Missed Out Viraddhasutta

“Mendicants, whoever has missed out on the seven awakening factors has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken the seven awakening factors has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. Whoever has missed out on these seven awakening factors has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken these seven awakening factors has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 46.19 Noble Ariyasutta

“Mendicants, when these seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they are noble and emancipating, and bring one who practices them to the complete ending of suffering. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. When these seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they are noble and emancipating, and bring one who practices them to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 46.20 Disillusionment Nibbidāsutta

“Mendicants, the seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.”

The Chapter on Cessation

SN 46.67 Ugliness Asubhasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of ugliness is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”[2288]

SN 46.68 Death Maraṇasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of death is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”[2289]

SN 46.69 Repulsiveness of Food Āhārepaṭikūlasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of repulsiveness of food is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.70 Dissatisfaction Anabhiratisutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of dissatisfaction with the whole world is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”[2290]

SN 46.71 Impermanence Aniccasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of impermanence is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.72 Suffering in Impermanence Dukkhasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of suffering in impermanence is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.73 Not-Self in Suffering Anattasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of not-self in suffering is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.74 Giving Up Pahānasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of giving up is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.75 Dispassion Virāgasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of dispassion is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. …”

SN 46.76 Cessation Nirodhasutta

“Mendicants, when the perception of cessation is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. How so? It’s when a mendicant develops the perception of cessation together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how, when the perception of cessation is developed and cultivated, it’s very fruitful and beneficial.

When the perception of cessation is developed and cultivated you can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return. How so? It’s when a mendicant develops the perception of cessation together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. When the perception of cessation is developed and cultivated in this way you can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

“The perception of cessation, when developed and cultivated, leads to great benefit … great sanctuary from the yoke … great inspiration … great ease. How so? It’s when a mendicant develops the perception of cessation together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how the perception of cessation, when developed and cultivated, leads to great benefit … great sanctuary from the yoke … great inspiration … great ease.”

The Chapter on Hindrances

SN 46.31 Skillful (1st) Paṭhamakusalasutta

“Mendicants, whatever qualities are skillful, part of the skillful, on the side of the skillful, all of them are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them. A mendicant who is diligent can expect to develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors.

And how does a diligent mendicant develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a diligent mendicant develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.32 Skillful (2nd) Dutiyakusalasutta

“Mendicants, whatever qualities are skillful, part of the skillful, on the side of the skillful, all of them are rooted in rational application of mind and meet at rational application of mind, and rational application of mind is said to be the best of them. A mendicant accomplished in rational application of mind can expect to develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors.

And how does a mendicant with rational application of mind develop and cultivate the seven awakening factors? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant with rational application of mind develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.33 Corruptions Upakkilesasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five corruptions of native gold. When native gold is corrupted by these it’s not pliable, workable, or radiant, but is brittle and not completely ready for working.[2259] What five? Iron, copper, tin, lead, and silver. When native gold is corrupted by these five corruptions it’s not pliable, workable, or radiant, but is brittle and not completely ready for working.

In the same way, there are these five corruptions of the mind. When the mind is corrupted by these it’s not pliable, workable, or radiant. It’s brittle, and not rightly immersed in samādhi for the ending of defilements. What five? Sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt.[2260] These are the five corruptions of the mind. When the mind is corrupted by these it’s not pliable, workable, or radiant. It’s brittle, and not rightly immersed in samādhi for the ending of defilements.”

SN 46.34 Not Corruptions Anupakkilesasutta

“Mendicants, these seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or corruptions of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or corruptions of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom.”

SN 46.35 Irrational Application of Mind Yonisomanasikārasutta

“Mendicants, when you apply the mind irrationally, sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt arise, and once arisen they increase and grow.”[2261]

“Mendicants, when you apply the mind rationally, the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity arise, and once they’ve arisen, they’re fully developed.”

SN 46.36 Growth Buddhisutta

“Mendicants, when the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they lead to growth and progress. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. When these seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they lead to growth and progress.”

SN 46.37 Obstacles Āvaraṇanīvaraṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five obstacles and hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom.[2262] What five? Sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. These are the five obstacles and hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom.

There are these seven awakening factors that are not obstacles, hindrances, or corruptions of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or corruptions of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom.”

SN 46.38 Without Obstacles Anīvaraṇasutta

“Mendicants, sometimes a noble disciple pays attention, applies the mind, concentrates wholeheartedly, and actively listens to the teaching. At such a time the five hindrances are absent, and the seven awakening factors are fully developed.

What are the five hindrances that are absent? Sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. These are the five hindrances that are absent.

And what are the seven awakening factors that are fully developed? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven awakening factors that are fully developed. Sometimes a noble disciple pays attention, applies the mind, concentrates wholeheartedly, and actively listens to the teaching. At such a time the five hindrances are absent, and the seven awakening factors are fully developed.”

SN 46.39 Trees Rukkhasutta

“Mendicants, there are large trees with tiny seeds and big bodies, which grow up and around other trees as parasites. The trees they engulf break apart, collapse, and fall.[2263] And what are those large trees with tiny seeds and big bodies? The peepal, banyan, wavy leaf fig, cluster fig, Moreton Bay fig, and white fig.[2264] These are the large trees with tiny seeds and big bodies, which grow up and around other trees as parasites. The trees they engulf break apart, collapse, and fall.

In the same way, take a certain gentleman who has gone forth from the lay life to homelessness, abandoning sensual pleasures. But beset by sensual pleasures that are similar, or even worse, he breaks apart, collapses, and falls.

There are these five obstacles and hindrances, parasites of the mind that weaken wisdom. What five? Sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. These are the five obstacles and hindrances, parasites of the mind that weaken wisdom.

These seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or parasites of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or parasites of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom.”

SN 46.40 Hindrances Nīvaraṇasutta

“Mendicants, these five hindrances are destroyers of sight, vision, and knowledge. They block wisdom, they’re on the side of distress, and they don’t lead to extinguishment. What five? Sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. These five hindrances are destroyers of sight, vision, and knowledge. They block wisdom, they’re on the side of distress, and they don’t lead to extinguishment.

These seven awakening factors are creators of vision and knowledge. They grow wisdom, they’re on the side of solace, and they lead to extinguishment. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors are creators of vision and knowledge. They grow wisdom, they’re on the side of solace, and they lead to extinguishment.”

The Chapter on Floods

SN 46.121–129 Floods Oghādisutta

“Mendicants, there are these four floods. What four? The floods of sensuality, desire to be reborn, views, and ignorance.”

(Tell in full as in SN 45.171–179.)

SN 46.130 Higher Fetters Uddhambhāgiyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters. The seven awakening factors should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.

What seven? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion. …”

“… which have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination …”

“… which slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment …

The seven awakening factors should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

The Chapter on Mountains

SN 46.1 The Himalaya Himavantasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, dragons grow and wax strong supported by the Himalayas, the king of mountains.[2217] When they’re strong they dive into the pools. Then they dive into the lakes, the streams, the rivers, and finally the ocean. There they acquire a great and abundant body.

In the same way, a mendicant develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors depending on and grounded on ethics, acquiring great and abundant good qualities.[2218] And how does a mendicant develop the seven awakening factors depending on and grounded on ethics, acquiring great and abundant good qualities?

It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factor of mindfulness, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go.[2219]

They develop the awakening factor of investigation of principles …[2220]

They develop the awakening factor of energy …

They develop the awakening factor of rapture …[2221]

They develop the awakening factor of tranquility …[2222]

They develop the awakening factor of immersion …

They develop the awakening factor of equanimity, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go.[2223]

That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors depending on and grounded on ethics, acquiring great and abundant good qualities.”

SN 46.2 The Body Kāyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, this body is sustained by food. It depends on food to continue, and without food it doesn’t continue.[2224] In the same way, the five hindrances are sustained by fuel. They depend on fuel to continue, and without fuel they don’t continue.[2225]

And what fuels the arising of sensual desire, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow? There is the feature of beauty.[2226] Frequent irrational application of mind to that[2227] fuels the arising of sensual desire, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of ill will, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow? There is the feature of aversion. Frequent irrational application of mind to that fuels the arising of ill will, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of dullness and drowsiness, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow? There is discontent, sloth, yawning, sleepiness after eating, and mental sluggishness. Frequent irrational application of mind to them fuels the arising of dullness and drowsiness, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of restlessness and remorse, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow? There is the unsettled mind.[2228] Frequent irrational application of mind to that fuels the arising of restlessness and remorse, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of doubt, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow? There are things that are grounds for doubt.[2229] Frequent irrational application of mind to them fuels the arising of doubt, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow.

This body is sustained by food. It depends on food to continue, and without food it doesn’t continue. In the same way, the five hindrances are sustained by fuel. They depend on fuel to continue, and without fuel they don’t continue.

This body is sustained by food. It depends on food to continue, and without food it doesn’t continue. In the same way, the seven awakening factors are sustained by fuel. They depend on fuel to continue, and without fuel they don’t continue.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of mindfulness, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of mindfulness.[2230] Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of mindfulness, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of investigation of principles, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are qualities that are skillful and unskillful, blameworthy and blameless, inferior and superior, and those with a portion of dark or bright.[2231] Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of investigation of principles, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of energy, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are the elements of initiative, persistence, and exertion. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of energy, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of rapture, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of rapture.[2232] Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of rapture, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of tranquility, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There is tranquility of the body and of the mind. Frequent rational application of mind to that fuels the arising of the awakening factor of tranquility, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of immersion, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are the basis of serenity and freedom from distraction.[2233] Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of immersion, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of equanimity, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of equanimity.[2234] Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of equanimity, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

This body is sustained by food. It depends on food to continue, and without food it doesn’t continue. In the same way, the seven awakening factors are sustained by fuel. They depend on fuel to continue, and without fuel they don’t continue.”

SN 46.3 Ethics Sīlasutta

“Mendicants, when a mendicant is accomplished in ethics, immersion, knowledge, freedom, or the knowledge and vision of freedom, even the sight of them is very helpful, I say.[2235] Even to hear them, approach them, pay homage to them, recollect them, or go forth following them is very helpful, I say. Why is that? Because after hearing the teaching of such mendicants, a mendicant will live withdrawn in both body and mind, as they recollect and think about that teaching.[2236]

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of mindfulness; they develop it and perfect it. As they live mindfully in this way they investigate, explore, and inquire into that teaching with wisdom.[2237]

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of investigation of principles; they develop it and perfect it. As they investigate principles with wisdom in this way their energy is roused up and unflagging.

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of energy; they develop it and perfect it. When they’re energetic, rapture not of the flesh arises.

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of rapture; they develop it and perfect it. When the mind is full of rapture, the body and mind become tranquil.

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of tranquility; they develop it and perfect it. When the body is tranquil and one feels bliss, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi.[2238]

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of immersion; they develop it and perfect it. They closely watch over that mind immersed in samādhi.

At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of equanimity; they develop it and perfect it.

When the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated in this way they can expect seven fruits and benefits. What seven? They attain enlightenment early on in this very life. If not, they attain enlightenment at the time of death. If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters, they’re extinguished between one life and the next.[2239] If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing.[2240] If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort.[2241] If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort.[2242] If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm.[2243] When the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated in this way these are the seven fruits and benefits they can expect.”

SN 46.4 Clothes Vatthasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“There are these seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven awakening factors.

In the morning, I meditate on whichever of these seven awakening factors I want.[2244] At midday, and in the evening, I meditate on whichever of these seven awakening factors I want. If it’s the awakening factor of mindfulness, I know that it’s limitless and that it’s properly implemented. While it remains I understand that it remains. And if it subsides in me I understand the specific reason it subsides. … If it’s the awakening factor of equanimity, I know that it’s limitless and that it’s properly implemented. While it remains I understand that it remains. And if it subsides I understand the specific reason it subsides.

Suppose that a ruler or their chief minister had a chest full of garments of different colors. In the morning, they’d don whatever pair of garments they wanted. At midday, and in the evening, they’d don whatever pair of garments they wanted.

In the same way, in the morning, at midday, and in the evening, I meditate on whichever of these seven awakening factors I want. If it’s the awakening factor of mindfulness, I know that it’s limitless and that it’s properly implemented. While it remains I understand that it remains. And if it subsides I understand the specific reason it subsides. … If it’s the awakening factor of equanimity, I know that it’s limitless and that it’s properly implemented. While it remains I understand that it remains. And if it subsides I understand the specific reason it subsides.”

SN 46.5 A Monk Bhikkhusutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and asked him, “Sir, they speak of the ‘awakening factors’. How are the awakening factors defined?”

“Mendicant, they’re called awakening factors because they lead to awakening.[2245]

A mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. As they develop the seven awakening factors, their mind is freed from the defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. When they’re freed, they know they’re freed. They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

They’re called awakening factors because they lead to awakening.”

SN 46.6 Kuṇḍaliya Kuṇḍaliyasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāketa in the deer park at the Añjana Wood.[2246] Then the wanderer Kuṇḍaliya went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him.[2247] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, I like to hang around the monasteries and visit the assemblies. When I’ve finished breakfast, it’s my habit to wander from monastery to monastery, from park to park. There I see some ascetics and brahmins speaking for the sake of winning debates and finding fault. But what benefit does the worthy Gotama live for?”

“The benefit the Realized One lives for, Kuṇḍaliya, is the fruit of knowledge and freedom.”

“But what things must be developed and cultivated in order to fulfill knowledge and freedom?”

“The seven awakening factors.”

“But what things must be developed and cultivated in order to fulfill the seven awakening factors?”

“The four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

“But what things must be developed and cultivated in order to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation?”

“The three kinds of good conduct.”

“But what things must be developed and cultivated in order to fulfill the three kinds of good conduct?”

“Sense restraint.

And Kuṇḍaliya, how is sense restraint developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the three kinds of good conduct? A mendicant sees an agreeable sight with their eyes. They don’t desire it or enjoy it, and they don’t give rise to greed. Their mind and body are steady internally, well settled and well freed. But if they see a disagreeable sight they’re undismayed, with mind unirritated, spirit undaunted, and heart unangered.[2248] Their mind and body are steady internally, well settled and well freed.

Furthermore, a mendicant hears an agreeable sound with their ears … smells an agreeable odor with their nose … tastes an agreeable flavor with their tongue … encounters an agreeable touch with their body … knows an agreeable idea with their mind. They don’t desire it or enjoy it, and they don’t give rise to greed. Their mind and body are steady internally, well settled and well freed. But if they know a disagreeable idea they’re undismayed, with mind unirritated, spirit undaunted, and heart unangered. Their mind and body are steady internally, well settled and well freed.

When a mendicant’s mind and body are steady internally, they’re well settled and well freed when it comes to both agreeable and disagreeable sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas. That’s how sense restraint is developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the three kinds of good conduct.

And how are the three kinds of good conduct developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? A mendicant gives up bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and develops good conduct by way of body, speech, and mind. That’s how the three kinds of good conduct are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

And how are the four kinds of mindfulness meditation developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the seven awakening factors? A mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how the four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the seven awakening factors.

And how are the seven awakening factors developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom? A mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom.”

When he said this, the wanderer Kuṇḍaliya said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! As if he were righting the overturned, or revealing the hidden, or pointing out the path to the lost, or lighting a lamp in the dark so people with clear eyes can see what’s there, worthy Gotama has made the teaching clear in many ways. I go for refuge to the worthy Gotama, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 46.7 A Bungalow Kūṭāgārasutta

“Mendicants, the rafters of a bungalow all slant, slope, and incline to the peak. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

And how does a mendicant who develops the seven awakening factors slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the seven awakening factors slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.”

SN 46.8 With Upavāṇa Upavānasutta

At one time the venerables Upavāṇa and Sāriputta were staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery. Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Sāriputta came out of retreat, went to Venerable Upavāṇa and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Upavāṇa:

“Reverend Upavāṇa, can a mendicant know that by investigating inside themselves, the seven awakening factors have been properly implemented so that they lead to living at ease?”[2249]

“They can, Reverend Sāriputta.

As a mendicant rouses up the awakening factor of mindfulness, they understand: ‘My mind is well freed. I’ve eradicated dullness and drowsiness, and eliminated restlessness and remorse. My energy is roused up, and my mind is sharply focused, not sluggish.’ …

As they rouse up the awakening factor of equanimity, they understand: ‘My mind is well freed. I’ve eradicated dullness and drowsiness, and eliminated restlessness and remorse. My energy is roused up, and my mind is sharply focused, not sluggish.’

That’s how a mendicant can know that by investigating inside themselves, the seven awakening factors are properly implemented so that they lead to living at ease.”

SN 46.9 Arisen (1st) Paṭhamauppannasutta

“Mendicants, these seven awakening factors don’t arise to be developed and cultivated except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors don’t arise to be developed and cultivated except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared.”

SN 46.10 Arisen (2nd) Dutiyauppannasutta

“Mendicants, these seven awakening factors don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training.”

The Chapter on Discussion

SN 46.51 Nourishing Āhārasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, I will teach you what fuels and what starves the five hindrances and the seven awakening factors.[2268] Listen …

And what fuels the arising of sensual desire, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow? There is the feature of beauty. Frequent irrational application of mind to that fuels the arising of sensual desire, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of ill will, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow? There is the feature of aversion. Frequent irrational application of mind to that fuels the arising of ill will, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of dullness and drowsiness, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow? There is discontent, sloth, yawning, sleepiness after eating, and mental sluggishness. Frequent irrational application of mind to that fuels the arising of dullness and drowsiness, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of restlessness and remorse, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow? There is the unsettled mind. Frequent irrational application of mind to that fuels the arising of restlessness and remorse, or, when they have arisen, makes them increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of doubt, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow? There are things that are grounds for doubt. Frequent irrational application of mind to them fuels the arising of doubt, or, when it has arisen, makes it increase and grow.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of mindfulness, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of mindfulness. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of mindfulness, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of investigation of principles, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are qualities that are skillful and unskillful, blameworthy and blameless, inferior and superior, and those with a portion of dark or bright. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of investigation of principles, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of energy, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are the elements of initiative, persistence, and exertion. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of energy, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of rapture, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of rapture. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of rapture, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of tranquility, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There is tranquility of the body and of the mind. Frequent rational application of mind to that fuels the arising of the awakening factor of tranquility, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of immersion, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are the basis of serenity and freedom from distraction. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of immersion, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.

And what fuels the arising of the awakening factor of equanimity, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of equanimity. Frequent rational application of mind to them fuels the arising of the awakening factor of equanimity, or, when it has arisen, fully develops it.[2269]

And what starves the arising of sensual desire, or, when it has arisen, starves its increase and growth? There is the feature of ugliness. Frequent rational application of mind to that starves the arising of sensual desire, or, when it has arisen, starves its increase and growth.

And what starves the arising of ill will, or, when it has arisen, starves its increase and growth? There is the heart’s release by love. Frequent rational application of mind to that starves the arising of ill will, or, when it has arisen, starves its increase and growth.

And what starves the arising of dullness and drowsiness, or, when they have arisen, starves their increase and growth? There are the elements of initiative, persistence, and exertion. Frequent rational application of mind to them starves the arising of dullness and drowsiness, or, when they have arisen, starves their increase and growth.

And what starves the arising of restlessness and remorse, or, when they have arisen, starves their increase and growth? There is the settled mind. Frequent rational application of mind to that starves the arising of restlessness and remorse, or, when they have arisen, starves their increase and growth.

And what starves the arising of doubt, or, when it has arisen, starves its increase and growth? There are qualities that are skillful and unskillful, blameworthy and blameless, inferior and superior, and those with a portion of dark or bright. Frequent rational application of mind to them starves the arising of doubt, or, when it has arisen, starves its increase and growth.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of mindfulness, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of mindfulness. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of mindfulness, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of investigation of principles, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There are qualities that are skillful and unskillful, blameworthy and blameless, inferior and superior, and those with a portion of dark or bright. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of investigation of principles, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of energy, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There are the elements of initiative, persistence, and exertion. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of energy, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of rapture, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of rapture. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of rapture, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of tranquility, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There is tranquility of the body and of the mind. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of tranquility, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of immersion, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There are things that are the basis of serenity and freedom from distraction. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of immersion, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.

And what starves the arising of the awakening factor of equanimity, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development? There are things that are grounds for the awakening factor of equanimity. Not frequently applying the mind to that starves the arising of the awakening factor of equanimity, or, when it has arisen, starves its full development.”

SN 46.52 Is There a Way? Pariyāyasutta

Then several mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, entered Sāvatthī for alms. Then it occurred to him, “It’s too early to wander for alms in Sāvatthī. Why don’t we visit the monastery for the wanderers of other religions?”

Then they went to the monastery for the wanderers of other religions and exchanged greetings with the wanderers there. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. The wanderers said to them:

“Reverends, the ascetic Gotama teaches his disciples like this: ‘Mendicants, please give up the five hindrances—corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom—and truly develop the seven awakening factors.’ We too teach our disciples: ‘Reverends, please give up the five hindrances—corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom—and truly develop the seven awakening factors.’[2270] What, then, is the difference between the ascetic Gotama’s teaching and instruction and ours?”

Those mendicants neither approved nor rejected that statement of the wanderers of other religions. They rose from their seats, thinking:

“We will learn the meaning of this statement from the Buddha himself.” Then, after the meal, when they returned from almsround, they went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Mendicants, when wanderers of other religions say this, you should say to them: ‘But reverends, is there a way in which the five hindrances become ten and the seven awakening factors become fourteen?’ Questioned like this, the wanderers of other religions would be stumped, and, in addition, would get frustrated.[2271] Why is that? Because they’re out of their element. I don’t see anyone in this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—who could provide a satisfying answer to these questions except the Realized One or his disciple or someone who has heard it from them.

And what is the way in which the five hindrances become ten? Sensual desire for what is internal is a hindrance; and sensual desire for what is external is also a hindrance. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the hindrance of sensual desire’ becomes twofold. Ill will for what is internal is a hindrance; and ill will for what is external is also a hindrance. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the hindrance of ill will’ becomes twofold. Dullness is a hindrance; and drowsiness is also a hindrance. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the hindrance of dullness and drowsiness’ becomes twofold. Restlessness is a hindrance; and remorse is also a hindrance. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the hindrance of restlessness and remorse’ becomes twofold. Doubt about internal things is a hindrance; and doubt about external things is also a hindrance. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the hindrance of doubt’ becomes twofold. This is the way in which the five hindrances become ten.

And what is the way in which the seven awakening factors become fourteen? Mindfulness of internal things is the awakening factor of mindfulness; and mindfulness of external things is also the awakening factor of mindfulness. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of mindfulness’ becomes twofold.

Investigating, exploring, and inquiring into internal things with wisdom is the awakening factor of investigation of principles; and investigating, exploring, and inquiring into external things with wisdom is also the awakening factor of investigation of principles. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of investigation of principles’ becomes twofold.

Physical energy is the awakening factor of energy; and mental energy is also the awakening factor of energy. That’s how what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of energy’ becomes twofold.

Rapture while placing the mind and keeping it connected is the awakening factor of rapture; and rapture without placing the mind and keeping it connected is also the awakening factor of rapture.[2272] In this way what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of rapture’ becomes twofold.

Physical tranquility is the awakening factor of tranquility; and mental tranquility is also the awakening factor of tranquility. In this way what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of tranquility’ becomes twofold.

Immersion while placing the mind and keeping it connected is the awakening factor of immersion; and immersion without placing the mind and keeping it connected is also the awakening factor of immersion.[2273] In this way what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of immersion’ becomes twofold.

Equanimity for internal things is the awakening factor of equanimity; and equanimity for external things is also the awakening factor of equanimity. In this way what is concisely referred to as ‘the awakening factor of equanimity’ becomes twofold. This is the way in which the seven awakening factors become fourteen.”

SN 46.53 Fire Aggisutta

Then several mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, entered Sāvatthī for alms.

(The same as the previous discourse.)

“Mendicants, when wanderers of other religions say this, you should say to them: ‘Reverends, which awakening factors should not be developed when the mind is sluggish? And which awakening factors should be developed at that time?[2274] Which awakening factors should not be developed when the mind is restless? And which awakening factors should be developed at that time?’ Questioned like this, the wanderers of other religions would be stumped, and, in addition, would get frustrated. Why is that? Because they’re out of their element.

I don’t see anyone in this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—who could provide a satisfying answer to these questions except the Realized One or his disciple or someone who has heard it from them.

When the mind is sluggish, it’s the wrong time to develop the awakening factors of tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. Why is that? Because it’s hard to stimulate a sluggish mind with these things.

Suppose someone wanted to make a small fire flare up. If they toss wet grass, cow-dung, and timber on it, spray it with water, and scatter dirt on it, could they make it flare up?”

“No, sir.”

“In the same way, when the mind is sluggish, it’s the wrong time to develop the awakening factors of tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. Why is that? Because it’s hard to stimulate a sluggish mind with these things.

When the mind is sluggish, it’s the right time to develop the awakening factors of investigation of principles, energy, and rapture. Why is that? Because it’s easy to stimulate a sluggish mind with these things.

Suppose someone wanted to make a small fire flare up. If they toss dry grass, cow-dung, and timber on it, blow on it, and don’t scatter dirt on it, could they make it flare up?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when the mind is sluggish, it’s the right time to develop the awakening factors of investigation of principles, energy, and rapture. Why is that? Because it’s easy to stimulate a sluggish mind with these things.

When the mind is restless, it’s the wrong time to develop the awakening factors of investigation of principles, energy, and rapture. Why is that? Because it’s hard to settle a restless mind with these things.

Suppose someone wanted to extinguish a great mass of fire. If they toss dry grass, cow-dung, and timber on it, blow on it, and don’t scatter dirt on it, could they extinguish it?”

“No, sir.”

“In the same way, when the mind is restless, it’s the wrong time to develop the awakening factors of investigation of principles, energy, and rapture. Why is that? Because it’s hard to settle a restless mind with these things.

When the mind is restless, it’s the right time to develop the awakening factors of tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. Why is that? Because it’s easy to settle a restless mind with these things.

Suppose someone wanted to extinguish a great mass of fire. If they toss wet grass, cow-dung, and timber on it, spray it with water, and scatter dirt on it, could they extinguish it?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when the mind is restless, it’s the right time to develop the awakening factors of tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. Why is that? Because it’s easy to settle a restless mind with these things. But mindfulness is always useful, I say.”[2275]

SN 46.54 Full of Love Mettāsahagatasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Koliyans, where they have a town named Haliddavasana.[2276] Then several mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, entered Haliddavasana for alms. Then it occurred to them, “It’s too early to wander for alms in Haliddavasana. Why don’t we visit the monastery for the wanderers of other religions?”

Then they went to the monastery for the wanderers of other religions and exchanged greetings with the wanderers there. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. The wanderers said to them:

“Reverends, the ascetic Gotama teaches his disciples like this: ‘Come, mendicants, give up these five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom, and meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Meditate spreading a heart full of compassion to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, spread a heart full of compassion to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Meditate spreading a heart full of rejoicing to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, spread a heart full of rejoicing to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Meditate spreading a heart full of equanimity to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of equanimity to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.’

We too teach our disciples in just the same way.[2277] What, then, is the difference between the ascetic Gotama’s teaching and instruction and ours?”

Those mendicants neither approved nor rejected that statement of the wanderers of other religions. They rose from their seats, thinking:

“We will learn the meaning of this statement from the Buddha himself.” Then, after the meal, when they returned from almsround, they went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Mendicants, when wanderers of other religions say this, you should say to them: ‘But reverends, how is the heart’s release by love developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and culmination? How is the heart’s release by compassion developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end? How is the heart’s release by rejoicing developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end? How is the heart’s release by equanimity developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end?’ Questioned like this, the wanderers of other religions would be stumped, and, in addition, would get frustrated. Why is that? Because they’re out of their element. I don’t see anyone in this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—who could provide a satisfying answer to these questions except the Realized One or his disciple or someone who has heard it from them.

And how is the heart’s release by love developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end? It’s when a mendicant develops the heart’s release by love together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive and the repulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. The apex of the heart’s release by love is the beautiful, I say, for a wise mendicant here who has not penetrated to a higher freedom.[2278]

And how is the heart’s release by compassion developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end? It’s when a mendicant develops the heart’s release by compassion together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. …[2279] If they wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. Or else, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space. The apex of the heart’s release by compassion is the dimension of infinite space, I say, for a wise mendicant here who has not penetrated to a higher freedom.

And how is the heart’s release by rejoicing developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end? It’s when a mendicant develops the heart’s release by rejoicing together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. … If they wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. Or else, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness. The apex of the heart’s release by rejoicing is the dimension of infinite consciousness, I say, for a wise mendicant here who has not penetrated to a higher freedom.

And how is the heart’s release by equanimity developed? What is its destination, apex, fruit, and end? It’s when a mendicant develops the heart’s release by equanimity together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive and the repulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. Or else, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness. The apex of the heart’s release by equanimity is the dimension of nothingness, I say, for a wise mendicant here who has not penetrated to a higher freedom.”

SN 46.55 With Saṅgārava Saṅgāravasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Saṅgārava the brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him.[2280] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“What is the cause, Worthy Gotama, what is the reason why sometimes even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed?[2281] And why is it that sometimes even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed?”[2282]

“Brahmin, there’s a time when your heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire and you don’t truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. At that time you don’t truly know or see what is good for yourself, good for another, or good for both. Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water that was mixed with dye such as red lac, turmeric, indigo, or rose madder. Even a person with clear eyes checking their own reflection wouldn’t truly know it or see it.

In the same way, when your heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is overcome and mired in ill will … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water that was heated by fire, boiling and bubbling. Even a person with clear eyes checking their own reflection wouldn’t truly know it or see it.

In the same way, when your heart is overcome and mired in ill will … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is overcome and mired in dullness and drowsiness … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water enveloped with moss and aquatic plants. Even a person with clear eyes checking their own reflection wouldn’t truly know it or see it.

In the same way, when your heart is overcome and mired in dullness and drowsiness … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is overcome and mired in restlessness and remorse … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water stirred by the wind, quivering, swirling, and rippling. Even a person with clear eyes checking their own reflection wouldn’t truly know it or see it.

In the same way, when your heart is overcome and mired in restlessness and remorse … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is overcome and mired in doubt … Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water that was cloudy, murky, and muddy, hidden in the darkness. Even a person with clear eyes checking their own reflection wouldn’t truly know it or see it.

In the same way, there’s a time when your heart is overcome and mired in doubt and you don’t truly understand the escape from doubt that has arisen. At that time you don’t truly know or see what is good for yourself, good for another, or good for both. Even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed. This is the cause, brahmin, this is the reason why sometimes even hymns that are long-rehearsed don’t spring to mind, let alone those that are not rehearsed.

There’s a time when your heart is not overcome and mired in sensual desire and you truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. At that time you truly know and see what is good for yourself, good for another, and good for both. Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water that was not mixed with dye such as red lac, turmeric, indigo, or rose madder. A person with clear eyes checking their own reflection would truly know it and see it.

In the same way, when your heart is not overcome and mired in sensual desire … Even hymns that are long-unpracticed spring to mind, let alone those that are practiced.

Furthermore, when your heart is not overcome and mired in ill will … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Suppose there is a bowl of water that is not heated by a fire, boiling and bubbling. A person with clear eyes checking their own reflection would truly know it and see it.

In the same way, when your heart is not overcome and mired in ill will … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is not overcome and mired in dullness and drowsiness … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Suppose there is a bowl of water that is not enveloped with moss and aquatic plants. A person with clear eyes checking their own reflection would truly know it and see it.

In the same way, when your heart is not overcome and mired in dullness and drowsiness … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is not overcome and mired in restlessness and remorse … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Suppose there is a bowl of water that is not stirred by the wind, quivering, swirling, and rippling. A person with clear eyes checking their own reflection would truly know it and see it.

In the same way, when your heart is not overcome and mired in restlessness and remorse … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Furthermore, when your heart is not overcome and mired in doubt … Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

Suppose there was a bowl of water that was transparent, clear, and unclouded, brought into the light. A person with clear eyes checking their own reflection would truly know it and see it.

In the same way, there’s a time when your heart is not overcome and mired in doubt and you truly understand the escape from doubt that has arisen. At that time you truly know and see what is good for yourself, good for another, and good for both. Even hymns that are long-unrehearsed spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed. This is the cause, brahmin, this is the reason why sometimes even hymns that are long-unrehearsed do spring to mind, let alone those that are rehearsed.

These seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or corruptions of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These seven awakening factors are not obstacles, hindrances, or corruptions of the mind. When developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of knowledge and freedom.”

When he said this, Saṅgārava said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 46.56 With Prince Abhaya Abhayasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain. Then Prince Abhaya went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2283]

“Sir, Pūraṇa Kassapa says this: ‘There is no cause or reason for not knowing and not seeing.[2284] Not knowing and not seeing have no cause or reason. There is no cause or reason for knowing and seeing. Knowing and seeing have no cause or reason.’ What does the Buddha say about this?”

“Prince, there are causes and reasons for not knowing and not seeing. Not knowing and not seeing have causes and reasons. There are causes and reasons for knowing and seeing. Knowing and seeing have causes and reasons.”

“But sir, what is the cause and reason for not knowing and not seeing? How do not knowing and not seeing have causes and reasons?”

“There’s a time when the heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire, without truly knowing and seeing the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. This is a cause and reason for not knowing and not seeing. And this is how not knowing and not seeing have causes and reasons.

Furthermore, there’s a time when the heart is overcome and mired in ill will … dullness and drowsiness … restlessness and remorse … doubt, without truly knowing and seeing the escape from doubt that has arisen. This is a cause and reason for not knowing and not seeing. And this is how not knowing and not seeing have causes and reasons.”

“Sir, what is the name of this exposition of the teaching?”

“These are called the ‘hindrances’, prince.”

“Indeed, Blessed One, these are hindrances! Indeed, Holy One, these are hindrances! Overcome by even a single hindrance you wouldn’t truly know or see, let alone all five hindrances.

But sir, what is the cause and reason for knowing and seeing? How do knowing and seeing have causes and reasons?”

“It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factor of mindfulness, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. They truly know and see with a mind that has developed the awakening factor of mindfulness. This is a cause and reason for knowing and seeing. And this is how knowing and seeing have causes and reasons.

Furthermore, a mendicant develops the awakening factor of investigation of principles … energy … rapture … tranquility … immersion … equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. They truly know and see with a mind that has developed the awakening factor of equanimity. This is a cause and reason for knowing and seeing. And this is how knowing and seeing have causes and reasons.”

“Sir, what is the name of this exposition of the teaching?”

“These are called the ‘awakening factors’, prince.”

“Indeed, Blessed One, these are awakening factors! Indeed, Holy One, these are awakening factors! Endowed with even a single awakening factor you would truly know and see, let alone all seven awakening factors. When climbing Mount Vulture’s Peak I became fatigued in body and mind. But this has now faded away. And I’ve comprehended the teaching.”[2285]

The Chapter with Udāyī

SN 46.21 To Awakening Bodhāyasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of the ‘awakening factors’. How are the awakening factors defined?”

“Mendicant, they’re called awakening factors because they lead to awakening. A mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. They’re called awakening factors because they lead to awakening.”

SN 46.22 A Teaching on the Awakening Factors Bojjhaṅgadesanāsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the seven awakening factors. Listen …

And what are the seven awakening factors? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven awakening factors.”

SN 46.23 Grounds Ṭhāniyasutta

“Mendicants, when you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for sensual greed, sensual desire arises, and once arisen it increases and grows. When you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for ill will, ill will arises, and once arisen it increases and grows. When you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for dullness and drowsiness, dullness and drowsiness arise, and once arisen they increase and grow. When you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for restlessness and remorse, restlessness and remorse arise, and once arisen they increase and grow. When you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for doubt, doubt arises, and once arisen it increases and grows.

When you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for the awakening factor of mindfulness, the awakening factor of mindfulness arises, and once arisen it’s fully developed. … When you frequently apply the mind to things that are grounds for the awakening factor of equanimity, the awakening factor of equanimity arises, and once arisen it’s fully developed.”

SN 46.24 Irrational Application of Mind Ayonisomanasikārasutta

“Mendicants, when you apply the mind irrationally, sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt arise, and once arisen they increase and grow. And the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity don’t arise, or if they’ve already arisen, they cease.

When you apply the mind rationally, sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt don’t arise, or if they’ve already arisen they’re given up.

And the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity arise, and once they’ve arisen, they’re fully developed.”

SN 46.25 Non-decline Aparihāniyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you seven principles that prevent decline.[2253] Listen …

And what are the seven principles that prevent decline? They are the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. These are the seven principles that prevent decline.”

SN 46.26 The Ending of Craving Taṇhakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, you should develop the path and the practice that leads to the ending of craving. And what is the path and the practice that leads to the ending of craving? It is the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity.” When he said this, Udāyī said to him:

“Sir, how are the seven awakening factors developed and cultivated so as to lead to the ending of craving?”

“Udāyī, it’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factor of mindfulness, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. And it is abundant, expansive, limitless, and free of ill will.[2254] As they do so, craving is given up.[2255] When craving is given up, deeds are given up. When deeds are given up, suffering is given up. …

A mendicant develops the awakening factor of equanimity, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. And it is abundant, expansive, limitless, and free of ill will. As they do so, craving is given up. When craving is given up, deeds are given up. When deeds are given up, suffering is given up.

And so, Udāyī, when craving ends, deeds end; when deeds end suffering ends.”

SN 46.27 The Cessation of Craving Taṇhānirodhasutta

“Mendicants, you should develop the path and the practice that leads to the cessation of craving. And what is the path and the practice that leads to the cessation of craving? It is the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. And how are the seven awakening factors developed and cultivated so as to lead to the cessation of craving?

It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion,

and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. This is how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to lead to the cessation of craving.”

SN 46.28 Helping Penetration Nibbedhabhāgiyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you a path that helps penetration. Listen …

And what is the path that helps penetration? It is the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity.” When he said this, Udāyī said to him:

“Sir, how are the seven awakening factors developed and cultivated so as to lead to penetration?”

“Udāyī, it’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factor of mindfulness, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. And it is abundant, expansive, limitless, and free of ill will. With a mind that has developed the awakening factor of mindfulness, they penetrate and shatter the mass of greed, the mass of hate, and the mass of delusion for the first time. …

A mendicant develops the awakening factor of equanimity, which relies on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripens as letting go. And it is abundant, expansive, limitless, and free of ill will. With a mind that has developed the awakening factor of equanimity, they penetrate and shatter the mass of greed, the mass of hate, and the mass of delusion for the first time.

This is how are the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to lead to penetration.”

SN 46.29 One Thing Ekadhammasutta

“Mendicants, I do not see a single thing that, when it is developed and cultivated like this, leads to giving up the things that tighten the fetters like the seven awakening factors. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. And how are the seven awakening factors developed and cultivated so as to lead to giving up the things that tighten the fetters?

It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to lead to giving up the things that tighten the fetters.[2256]

And what are the things that tighten the fetters? The eye is something that tightens the fetters. This is where these fetters, shackles, and attachments arise. The ear … nose … tongue … body … mind is something that tightens the fetters. This is where these fetters, shackles, and attachments arise. These are called the things that tighten the fetters.”

SN 46.30 With Udāyī Udāyisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sumbhas, near the town of the Sumbhas named Sedaka. Then Venerable Udāyī went up to the Buddha … and said to him:

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How helpful my fondness and respect for the Buddha have been, and my sense of conscience and prudence. For when I was still a layman, I wasn’t helped much by the teaching or the Saṅgha. But when I considered my fondness and respect for the Buddha, and my sense of conscience and prudence, I went forth from the lay life to homelessness. The Buddha taught me the Dhamma: ‘Such is form, such is the origin of form, such is the disappearance of form. Such is feeling … Such is perception … Such are choices … Such is consciousness, such is the origin of consciousness, such is the disappearance of consciousness.’

Then, while staying in an empty hut, I followed the churning of the five grasping aggregates. I truly understood: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’.[2257] I comprehended the teaching, sir, I acquired the path.[2258] This, when developed and cultivated by me meditating in just such a way, will bring me to such a state that I will understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

I acquired the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. Each of these, when developed and cultivated by me meditating in just such a way, will bring me to such a state that I will understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’ This is the path that I acquired which, when developed and cultivated by me meditating in just such a way, will bring me to such a state that I will understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

“Good, good, Udāyī! For that is indeed the path that you acquired which, when developed and cultivated by you meditating in just such a way, will bring you to such a state that you will understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

The Chapter on Freedom From Death

SN 47.41 Freedom From Death Amatasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, you should meditate with your mind firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. Don’t let freedom from death be lost on you.[2383] What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. You should meditate with your mind firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. Don’t let freedom from death be lost on you.”

SN 47.42 Origin Samudayasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the origin and disappearance of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.[2384] Listen …

What is the origin of the body?[2385] The body originates from fuel.[2386] When fuel ceases, the body disappears.[2387]

Feelings originate from contact.[2388] When contact ceases, feelings disappear.

The mind originates from name and form.[2389] When name and form cease, the mind disappears.

Principles originate from application of mind.[2390] When application of mind disappears, principles disappear.”[2391]

SN 47.43 The Path Maggasutta

At Sāvatthī.[2392]

There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, this one time, when I was first awakened, I was staying in Uruvelā at the goatherd’s banyan tree on the bank of the Nerañjarā River. As I was in private retreat this thought came to mind: ‘The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.

What four? A mendicant would meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Or they’d meditate observing an aspect of feelings … or mind … or principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.’

And then the divinity Sahampati, knowing my train of thought, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from the realm of divinity and reappeared in front of me. He arranged his robe over one shoulder, raised his joined palms toward me, and said: ‘That’s so true, Blessed One! That’s so true, Holy One! Sir, the four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.

What four? A mendicant would meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Or they’d meditate observing an aspect of feelings … or mind … or principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.’

That is what the divinity Sahampati said. Then he went on to say:

‘The compassionate one, who sees the ending of rebirth,
understands the path to convergence.
By this path people crossed over before,
will cross over, and are crossing over.’”

SN 47.44 Mindful Satisutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant should live mindfully. This is my instruction to you.

And how is a mendicant mindful? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant is mindful. A mendicant should live mindfully. This is my instruction to you.”

SN 47.45 A Heap of the Skillful Kusalarāsisutta

“Rightly speaking, mendicants, you’d call these four kinds of mindfulness meditation a ‘heap of the skillful’. For these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are entirely a heap of the skillful.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Rightly speaking, you’d call these four kinds of mindfulness meditation a ‘heap of the skillful’. For these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are entirely a heap of the skillful.”

SN 47.46 Restraint in the Monastic Code Pātimokkhasaṁvarasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Well then, mendicant, you should purify the starting point of skillful qualities. What is the starting point of skillful qualities? Live restrained in the monastic code, conducting yourself well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, keep the rules you’ve undertaken. When you’ve done this, you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, depending on and grounded on ethics.

What four? Meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

When you develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation in this way, depending on and grounded on ethics, you can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.”

And then that mendicant approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then that mendicant, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And that mendicant became one of the perfected.

SN 47.47 Bad Conduct Duccaritasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha … and said:

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Well then, mendicant, you should purify the starting point of skillful qualities. What is the beginning of skillful qualities? Give up bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind and develop good conduct by way of body, speech, and mind. When you’ve done this, you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, depending on and grounded on ethics.

What four? Meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. When you develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation in this way, depending on and grounded on ethics, you can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.” …

And that mendicant became one of the perfected.

SN 47.48 Friends Mittasutta

“Mendicants, those for whom you have sympathy, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the development of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Those for whom you have sympathy, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the development of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.49 Feelings Vedanāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three feelings. What three? Pleasant, painful, and neutral feeling. These are the three feelings. The four kinds of mindfulness meditation should be developed to completely understand these three feelings.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

These four kinds of mindfulness meditation should be developed to completely understand these three feelings.”

SN 47.50 Defilements Āsavasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three defilements. What three? The defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. These are the three defilements.

The four kinds of mindfulness meditation should be developed to give up these three defilements.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

These four kinds of mindfulness meditation should be developed to give up these three defilements.”

The Chapter on Ambapālī the Courtesan

SN 47.1 In Ambapālī’s Mango Grove Ambapālisutta

So I have heard.[2291] At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī in Ambapālī’s Mango Grove.[2292] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, the four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.[2293] What four?

It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2294]

They meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2295]

They meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2296]

They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2297]

The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

SN 47.2 Mindful Satisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī in Ambapālī’s Mango Grove.[2298] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, a mendicant should live mindful and aware.[2299] This is my instruction to you.

And how is a mendicant mindful? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant is mindful.

And how is a mendicant aware? It’s when a mendicant acts with situational awareness when going out and coming back; when looking ahead and aside; when bending and extending the limbs; when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes; when eating, drinking, chewing, and tasting; when urinating and defecating; when walking, standing, sitting, sleeping, waking, speaking, and keeping silent.[2300] That’s how a mendicant acts with situational awareness.[2301] A mendicant should live mindful and aware. This is my instruction to you.”

SN 47.3 A Monk Bhikkhusutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“This is exactly how some futile people ask me for something. But when the teaching has been explained they think only of following me around.”[2302]

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief! May the Holy One teach me the Dhamma in brief! Hopefully I can understand the meaning of what the Buddha says! Hopefully I can be an heir of the Buddha’s teaching!”

“Well then, mendicant, you should purify the starting point of skillful qualities. What is the starting point of skillful qualities? Well purified ethics and correct view.[2303] When your ethics are well purified and your view is correct, you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation in three ways, depending on and grounded on ethics.

What four?

Meditate observing an aspect of the body internally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2304] Or meditate observing an aspect of the body externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Or meditate observing an aspect of the body internally and externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Or meditate observing an aspect of feelings internally … externally … internally and externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Or meditate observing an aspect of the mind internally … externally … internally and externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Or meditate observing an aspect of principles internally … externally … internally and externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. When you develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation in these three ways, depending on and grounded on ethics, you can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.”

And then that mendicant approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then that mendicant, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And that mendicant became one of the perfected.

SN 47.4 At Sālā Sālasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Kosalans near the brahmin village of Sālā.[2305] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, those mendicants who are junior—recently gone forth, newly come to this teaching and training—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.[2306] What four? Please, reverends, meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to truly know the body. Meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to truly know feelings. Meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to truly know the mind. Meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to truly know principles.

Those mendicants who are trainees—who haven’t achieved their heart’s desire, but live aspiring to the supreme sanctuary from the yoke—also meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to fully understand the body.[2307] They meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to fully understand feelings. They meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to fully understand the mind. They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, so as to fully understand principles.

Those mendicants who are perfected—who have ended the defilements, completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their own goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and are rightly freed through enlightenment—also meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, detached from the body.[2308] They meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, detached from feelings. They meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, detached from the mind. They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, at one, with minds that are clear, immersed and unified in samādhi, detached from principles.

Those mendicants who are junior—recently gone forth, newly come to this teaching and training—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.5 A Heap of the Unskillful Akusalarāsisutta

At Sāvatthī.

There the Buddha said:

“Rightly speaking, mendicants, you’d call the five hindrances a ‘heap of the unskillful’.[2309] For these five hindrances are entirely a heap of the unskillful. What five? The hindrances of sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. Rightly speaking, you’d call these five hindrances a ‘heap of the unskillful’. For these five hindrances are entirely a heap of the unskillful.

Rightly speaking, you’d call these four kinds of mindfulness meditation a ‘heap of the skillful’.[2310] For these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are entirely a heap of the skillful. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … They meditate observing an aspect of the mind … They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Rightly speaking, you’d call these four kinds of mindfulness meditation a ‘heap of the skillful’. For these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are entirely a heap of the skillful.”

SN 47.6 A Hawk Sakuṇagghisutta

“Once upon a time, mendicants, a hawk suddenly swooped down and grabbed a quail.[2311] And as the quail was being carried off he wailed,[2312] ‘I’m so unlucky, of so little merit, to have roamed out of my territory into the domain of others. If today I’d roamed within my own territory, the domain of my fathers, this hawk wouldn’t have stood a chance against me in a fight.’[2313]

‘So, quail, what is your own territory, the domain of your fathers?’

‘It’s a ploughed field covered with clods of earth.’

Confident in her own strength, the hawk was not daunted or intimidated. She released the quail, saying, ‘Go now, quail. But even there you won’t escape me!’

Then the quail went to a ploughed field covered with clods of earth. He climbed up a big clod, and standing there, he said to the hawk: ‘Come get me, hawk! Come get me, hawk!’

Confident in her own strength, the hawk was not daunted or intimidated. She folded her wings and suddenly swooped down on the quail. When the quail knew that the hawk was nearly there, he slipped under that clod. But the hawk crashed chest-first right there.

That’s what happens when you roam out of your territory into the domain of others.

So, mendicants, don’t roam out of your own territory into the domain of others. If you roam out of your own territory into the domain of others, Māra will find a vulnerability and get an opportunity.

And what is not a mendicant’s own territory but the domain of others? It’s the five kinds of sensual stimulation.[2314] What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. This is not a mendicant’s own territory but the domain of others.

You should roam inside your own territory, the domain of your fathers. If you roam inside your own territory, the domain of your fathers, Māra won’t find a vulnerability or get an opportunity.

And what is a mendicant’s own territory, the domain of the fathers? It’s the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. This is a mendicant’s own territory, the domain of the fathers.”

SN 47.7 A Monkey Makkaṭasutta

“Mendicants, in the Himalayas there are regions that are rugged and impassable. In some such regions, neither monkeys nor humans can go,[2315] while in others, monkeys can go but not humans. There are also level, pleasant places where both monkeys and humans can go. There hunters set snares of tar on the monkey trails to catch the monkeys.[2316]

The monkeys who are not foolhardy and reckless see the tar and avoid it from afar. But a foolish and reckless monkey goes up to the tar and grabs it with a hand. He gets stuck there. Thinking to free his hand, he grabs it with his other hand. He gets stuck there. Thinking to free both hands, he grabs it with a foot. He gets stuck there. Thinking to free both hands and foot, he grabs it with his other foot. He gets stuck there. Thinking to free both hands and feet, he grabs it with his snout. He gets stuck there.

And so the monkey, trapped at five points, just lies there screeching. He’d meet with tragedy and disaster, and the hunter can do what he wants with him.[2317] The hunter spears him on that very banana tree, pries him off, and goes wherever he wants.[2318]

That’s what happens when you roam out of your territory into the domain of others.

So, mendicants, don’t roam out of your own territory into the domain of others. If you roam out of your own territory into the domain of others, Māra will find a vulnerability and get an opportunity.

And what is not a mendicant’s own territory but the domain of others? It’s the five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. This is not a mendicant’s own territory but the domain of others.

You should roam inside your own territory, the domain of your fathers. If you roam inside your own territory, the domain of your fathers, Māra won’t find a vulnerability and get an opportunity.

And what is a mendicant’s own territory, the domain of the fathers? It’s the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. This is a mendicant’s own territory, the domain of the fathers.”

SN 47.8 Cooks Sūdasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a foolish, incompetent, unskillful cook was to serve a ruler or their chief minister with an excessive variety of curries:[2319] chiefly sour, bitter, pungent, and sweet; hot and mild, and salty and bland.[2320]

But that cook didn’t take their master’s hint:[2321] ‘Today my master preferred this sauce, or he reached for it, or he took a lot of it, or he praised it. Today my master preferred the chiefly sour or bitter or pungent or sweet or hot or mild or salty sauce. Or he preferred the bland sauce, or he reached for the bland one, or he took a lot of it, or he praised it.’

That foolish, incompetent, unskillful cook doesn’t get presented with clothes, wages, or bonuses. Why is that? Because they don’t take their master’s hint.

In the same way, a foolish, incompetent, unskillful mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of the body, their mind doesn’t enter immersion, and their corruptions aren’t given up.[2322] But they don’t take the hint. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of principles, the mind doesn’t enter immersion, and the corruptions aren’t given up. But they don’t take the hint.

That foolish, incompetent, unskillful mendicant doesn’t get blissful meditations in this very life, nor do they get mindfulness and situational awareness. Why is that? Because they don’t take their mind’s hint.

Suppose an astute, competent, skillful cook was to serve a ruler or their chief minister with an extravagant variety of curries: chiefly sour, bitter, pungent, and sweet; hot and mild, and salty and bland.

And that cook took their master’s hint: ‘Today my master preferred this sauce, or he reached for it, or he took a lot of it, or he praised it. Today my master preferred the chiefly sour or bitter or pungent or sweet or hot or mild or salty sauce. Or he preferred the bland sauce, or he reached for the bland one, or he took a lot of it, or he praised it.’

That astute, competent, skillful cook gets presented with clothes, wages, and bonuses. Why is that? Because they take their master’s hint.

In the same way, an astute, competent, skillful mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of the body, their mind enters immersion, and their corruptions are given up. They take the hint. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of principles, their mind enters immersion, and their corruptions are given up. They take the hint.

That astute, competent, skillful mendicant gets blissful meditations in this very life, and they get mindfulness and situational awareness. Why is that? Because they take their mind’s hint.”

SN 47.9 Sick Gilānasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the little village of Beluva.[2323] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, please enter the rainy season residence with whatever friends or acquaintances you have around Vesālī.[2324] I’ll commence the rainy season residence right here in the little village of Beluva.”

“Yes, sir,” those mendicants replied. They did as the Buddha said, while the Buddha commenced the rainy season residence right there in the little village of Beluva.

After the Buddha had commenced the rainy season residence, he fell severely ill, struck by dreadful pains, close to death. But he endured unbothered, with mindfulness and situational awareness. Then it occurred to the Buddha:

“It would not be appropriate for me to be fully extinguished before informing my supporters and taking leave of the mendicant Saṅgha.[2325] Why don’t I forcefully suppress this illness, stabilize the life force, and live on?”[2326] So that is what he did. Then the Buddha’s illness died down.

Soon after the Buddha had recovered from that sickness, he left his dwelling and sat in the shade of the porch on the seat spread out. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, it’s fantastic that the Buddha is comfortable,[2327] that he’s keeping well, and that he’s getting by. Because when the Buddha was sick, my body felt like it was drugged. I was disorientated, and the teachings didn’t spring to mind. Still, at least I was consoled by the thought that the Buddha won’t be fully extinguished without bringing something up regarding the Saṅgha of mendicants.”[2328]

“But what could the mendicant Saṅgha expect from me now, Ānanda?[2329] I’ve taught the Dhamma without making any distinction between secret and public teachings.[2330] The Realized One doesn’t have the closed fist of a tutor when it comes to the teachings.[2331]

If there’s anyone who thinks: ‘I shall lead the mendicant Saṅgha,’ or ‘the Saṅgha of mendicants is meant for me,’ let them bring something up regarding the Saṅgha.[2332] But the Realized One doesn’t think like this, so why should he bring something up regarding the Saṅgha?

Now I am old, elderly and senior. I’m advanced in years and have reached the final stage of life. I’m currently eighty years old. Just as a decrepit old cart is kept going by a rope,[2333] in the same way, the Realized One’s body is kept going as if by a rope.[2334]

Sometimes the Realized One, not focusing on any signs, and with the cessation of certain feelings, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart. Only then does the Realized One’s body become more comfortable.

So Ānanda, live as your own island, your own refuge, with no other refuge. Let the teaching be your island and your refuge, with no other refuge.[2335]

And how does a mendicant do this? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant lives with themselves as island and refuge, without other refuge; with the teachings as island and refuge, without other refuge.

Whether now or after I have passed, any who shall live as their own island, their own refuge, with no other refuge; with the teaching as their island and their refuge, with no other refuge—those mendicants of mine who want to train shall be among the best of the best.”[2336]

SN 47.10 The Nuns’ Quarters Bhikkhunupassayasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the nuns’ quarters, and sat down on the seat spread out. Then several nuns went up to Venerable Ānanda bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Honorable Ānanda, several nuns meditate with their minds firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. They have realized a higher distinction than they had before.”[2337]

“That’s how it is, sisters! That’s how it is, sisters! Any monk or nun who meditates with their mind firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation can expect to realize a higher distinction than they had before.”

Then Ānanda educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired those nuns with a Dhamma talk, after which he rose from his seat and left. Then Ānanda wandered for alms in Sāvatthī. After the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“That’s so true, Ānanda! That’s so true! Any monk or nun who meditates with their mind firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation can expect to realize a higher distinction than they had before.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2338] As they meditate observing an aspect of the body, based on the body there arises sweltering in the body, or mental sluggishness, or the mind is externally scattered.[2339] That mendicant should direct their mind toward an inspiring subject as a basis for meditation.[2340] As they do so, joy springs up. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, one feels bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. Then they reflect:[2341] ‘I have accomplished the goal for which I directed my mind.[2342] Let me now relax.’[2343] They relax, and neither place the mind nor keep it connected. They understand: ‘I’m neither placing the mind nor keeping it connected. Mindful within myself, I’m happy.’[2344]

Furthermore, a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of principles, based on principles there arises sweltering in the body, or mental sluggishness, or the mind is externally scattered. That mendicant should direct their mind toward an inspiring subject as a basis for meditation. As they do so, joy springs up. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, one feels bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. Then they reflect: ‘I have accomplished the goal for which I directed my mind. Let me now relax.’ They relax, and neither place the mind nor keep it connected. They understand: ‘I’m neither placing the mind nor keeping it connected. Mindful within myself, I’m happy.’ That’s how there is directed development.

And how is there undirected development? Not directing their mind externally, a mendicant understands: ‘My mind is not directed externally.’[2345] And they understand: ‘Before and behind, it’s unconstricted, freed, and undirected.’ And they also understand: ‘I meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, mindful; I am happy.’ Not directing their mind externally, a mendicant understands: ‘My mind is not directed externally.’ And they understand: ‘Before and behind, it’s unconstricted, freed, and undirected.’ And they also understand: ‘I meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, mindful; I am happy.’ Not directing their mind externally, a mendicant understands: ‘My mind is not directed externally.’ And they understand: ‘Before and behind, it’s unconstricted, freed, and undirected.’ And they also understand: ‘I meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, mindful; I am happy.’ Not directing their mind externally, a mendicant understands: ‘My mind is not directed externally.’ And they understand: ‘Before and behind, it’s unconstricted, freed, and undirected.’ And they also understand: ‘I meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, mindful; I am happy.’ That’s how there is undirected development.

So, Ānanda, I’ve taught you directed development and undirected development. Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, Ānanda! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, Venerable Ānanda approved what the Buddha said.

The Chapter on Not Learned From Anyone Else

SN 47.31 Not Learned From Anyone Else Ananussutasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“‘This is the observation of an aspect of the body.’ Such, mendicants, was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.[2376] ‘This observation of an aspect of the body should be developed.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of the body has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.

‘This is the observation of an aspect of feelings.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of feelings should be developed.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of feelings has been developed.’ …

‘This is the observation of an aspect of the mind.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of the mind should be developed.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of the mind has been developed.’ …

‘This is the observation of an aspect of principles.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of principles should be developed.’ … ‘This observation of an aspect of principles has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.”

SN 47.32 Fading Away Virāgasutta

“Mendicants, these four kinds of mindfulness meditation, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

These four kinds of mindfulness meditation, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.”

SN 47.33 Missed Out Viraddhasutta

“Mendicants, whoever has missed out on the four kinds of mindfulness meditation has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken the four kinds of mindfulness meditation has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Whoever has missed out on these four kinds of mindfulness meditation has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken these four kinds of mindfulness meditation has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 47.34 Developed Bhāvitasutta

“Mendicants, when these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

When these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore.”

SN 47.35 Mindful Satisutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, a mendicant should live mindful and aware. This is my instruction to you.

And how is a mendicant mindful? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant is mindful.

And how is a mendicant aware? It’s when a mendicant knows feelings as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away.[2377] They know thoughts as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away. They know perceptions as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away. That’s how a mendicant is aware. A mendicant should live mindful and aware. This is my instruction to you.”

SN 47.36 Enlightenment Aññāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. These are the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

Because of developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation, one of two results can be expected:[2378] enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

SN 47.37 Desire Chandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they give up desire for the body. When desire is given up they realize freedom from death.

They meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they give up desire for feelings. When desire is given up they realize freedom from death.

They meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they give up desire for the mind. When desire is given up they realize freedom from death.

They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they give up desire for principles. When desire is given up they realize freedom from death.”

SN 47.38 Complete Understanding Pariññātasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they completely understand the body. When the body is completely understood they realize freedom from death.

They meditate observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they completely understand feelings. When feelings are completely understood they realize freedom from death.

They meditate observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they completely understand the mind. When the mind is completely understood they realize freedom from death.

They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they do so they completely understand principles. When principles are completely understood they realize freedom from death.”

SN 47.39 Development Bhāvanāsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the development of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.[2379] Listen …

And what is the development of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

This is the development of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.40 Analysis Vibhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you mindfulness meditation, the development of mindfulness meditation, and the practice that leads to the development of mindfulness meditation.[2380] Listen …

And what is mindfulness meditation? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. This is called mindfulness meditation.

And what is the development of mindfulness meditation?[2381] It’s when a mendicant, with respect to the body, meditates observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2382] With respect to feelings … mind … principles, they meditate observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. This is called the development of mindfulness meditation.

And what is the practice that leads to the development of mindfulness meditation? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the practice that leads to the development of mindfulness meditation.”

The Chapter at Nālandā

SN 47.11 A Great Man Mahāpurisasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of ‘a great man’.[2346] How is a great man defined?”

“Sāriputta, someone whose mind is free is a great man, I say. If their mind is not free, I say they’re not a great man.

And how does someone have a free mind? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of the body, their mind becomes dispassionate, and is freed from the defilements by not grasping. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. As they meditate observing an aspect of principles, their mind becomes dispassionate, and is freed from the defilements by not grasping. That’s how someone has a free mind.

Someone whose mind is free is a great man, I say. If their mind is not free, I say they’re not a great man.”

SN 47.12 At Nāḷandā Nālandasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Nāḷandā in Pāvārika’s Mango Grove.[2347] Then Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, I have such confidence in the Buddha that I believe there’s no other ascetic or brahmin—whether past, future, or present—whose direct knowledge is superior to the Buddha when it comes to awakening.”

“That’s a grand and bold statement, Sāriputta. You’ve roared a definitive, categorical lion’s roar, saying: ‘I have such confidence in the Buddha that I believe there’s no other ascetic or brahmin—whether past, future, or present—whose direct knowledge is superior to the Buddha when it comes to awakening.’

What about all the perfected ones, the fully awakened Buddhas who lived in the past? Have you encompassed their minds to know that those Buddhas had such ethics, or such qualities, or such wisdom, or such meditation, or such freedom?”

“No, sir.”

“And what about all the perfected ones, the fully awakened Buddhas who will live in the future? Have you encompassed their minds to know that those Buddhas will have such ethics, or such qualities, or such wisdom, or such meditation, or such freedom?”

“No, sir.”

“And what about me, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha at present? Have you encompassed my mind to know that I have such ethics, or such qualities, or such wisdom, or such meditation, or such freedom?”

“No, sir.”

“In that case, Sāriputta, given that you don’t encompass the minds of Buddhas past, future, or present, what then are you doing, making such a grand and bold statement, roaring such a definitive, categorical lion’s roar?”

“Sir, though I don’t encompass the minds of Buddhas past, future, and present, still I understand this by inference from the teaching.[2348] Suppose there was a king’s frontier citadel with fortified embankments, ramparts, and arches, and a single gate. And it has a gatekeeper who is astute, competent, and intelligent. He keeps strangers out and lets known people in. As he walks around the patrol path, he doesn’t see a hole or cleft in the wall, not even one big enough for a cat to slip out. He thinks, ‘Whatever sizable creatures enter or leave the citadel, all of them do so via this gate.’

In the same way, I understand this by inference from the teaching: ‘Those who are perfected ones, fully awakened Buddhas—whether past, future, or present—give up the five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom. Their mind is firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. They correctly develop the seven awakening factors. And they awaken to the supreme perfect awakening.’”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! So Sāriputta, you should frequently speak this exposition of the teaching to the monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen.[2349] Though there will be some futile people who have doubt or uncertainty regarding the Realized One, when they hear this exposition of the teaching they’ll give up that doubt or uncertainty.”

SN 47.13 With Cunda Cundasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.[2350] At that time Venerable Sāriputta was staying in the Magadhan lands near the little village of Nālaka, and he was sick, suffering, gravely ill. And the novice Cunda was his carer.[2351]

Then Venerable Sāriputta was fully extinguished from that sickness. Then Cunda took Sāriputta’s bowl and robes and set out for Sāvatthī. He went to see Venerable Ānanda at Jeta’s grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2352]

“Sir, Venerable Sāriputta has become fully quenched. This is his bowl and robe.”

“Reverend Cunda, we should see the Buddha about this matter. Come, let’s go to the Buddha and inform him about this.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Cunda.

Then Ānanda and Cunda went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, this novice Cunda says that Venerable Sāriputta has become fully quenched. This is his bowl and robe. Since I heard this, my body feels like it’s drugged. I’m disorientated, and the teachings don’t spring to mind.”

“Well, Ānanda, when Sāriputta was fully quenched, did he take away your entire spectrum of ethical conduct, of immersion, of wisdom, of freedom, or of the knowledge and vision of freedom?”[2353]

“No, sir, he did not. But Venerable Sāriputta was my adviser and counselor. He educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired me. He never tired of teaching the Dhamma, and he supported his spiritual companions.[2354] I remember the nectar of the teaching, the riches of the teaching, the support of the teaching given by Venerable Sāriputta.”

“Ānanda, did I not prepare for this when I explained that we must be parted and separated from all we hold dear and beloved? How could it possibly be so that what is born, created, conditioned, and liable to wear out should not wear out? That is not possible.

Suppose there was a large tree standing with heartwood, and the largest branch broke off.[2355] In the same way, in the great Saṅgha that stands with heartwood, Sāriputta has become fully quenched.

How could it possibly be so that what is born, created, conditioned, and liable to wear out should not wear out? That is not possible.

So Ānanda, live as your own island, your own refuge, with no other refuge. Let the teaching be your island and your refuge, with no other refuge.

And how does a mendicant do this? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

That’s how a mendicant lives with themselves as island and refuge, without other refuge; with the teachings as island and refuge, without other refuge.

Whether now or after I have passed, any who shall live as their own island, their own refuge, with no other refuge; with the teaching as their island and their refuge, with no other refuge—those mendicants of mine who want to train shall be among the best of the best.”

SN 47.14 At Ukkacelā Ukkacelasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Vajjis near Ukkacelā on the bank of the Ganges River, together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants. It was not long after Sāriputta and Moggallāna had become fully quenched.[2356] Now, at that time the Buddha was sitting in the open, surrounded by the Saṅgha of mendicants.

Then the Buddha looked around the Saṅgha of mendicants, who were silent. He addressed them:

“Mendicants, this assembly seems empty to me now that Sāriputta and Moggallāna have become fully quenched. My assembly never used to be empty; I had no concern for any region where Sāriputta and Moggallāna stayed.[2357] The Buddhas of the past or the future have pairs of chief disciples who at best were like Sāriputta and Moggallāna were to me.

It’s an incredible and amazing quality of such disciples that they fulfill the Teacher’s instructions and follow his advice. And they’re liked and approved, respected and admired by the four assemblies.[2358]

And it’s an incredible and amazing quality of the Realized One that when such a pair of disciples becomes fully quenched he does not sorrow or lament. How could it possibly be so that what is born, created, conditioned, and liable to wear out should not wear out? That is not possible.

Suppose there was a large tree standing with heartwood, and the largest branches broke off. In the same way, in the great Saṅgha that stands with heartwood, Sāriputta and Moggallāna have become fully quenched.

How could it possibly be so that what is born, created, conditioned, and liable to wear out should not wear out? That is not possible.

So mendicants, live as your own island, your own refuge, with no other refuge. Let the teaching be your island and your refuge, with no other refuge.

And how does a mendicant do this? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

That’s how a mendicant lives with themselves as island and refuge, without other refuge; with the teachings as island and refuge, without other refuge.

Whether now or after I have passed, any who shall live as their own island, their own refuge, with no other refuge; with the teaching as their island and their refuge, with no other refuge—those mendicants of mine who want to train shall be among the best of the best.”

SN 47.15 With Bāhiya Bāhiyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Bāhiya went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2359]

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Well then, Bāhiya, you should purify the starting point of skillful qualities. What is the starting point of skillful qualities? Well purified ethics and correct view. When your ethics are well purified and your view is correct, you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, depending on and grounded on ethics.

What four? Meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. When you develop these four kinds of mindfulness meditation, depending on and grounded on ethics, you can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.”

And then Venerable Bāhiya approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving. Then Bāhiya, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Bāhiya became one of the perfected.

SN 47.16 With Uttiya Uttiyasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Uttiya went up to the Buddha … and asked him, “Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Well then, Uttiya, you should purify the starting point of skillful qualities. What is the starting point of skillful qualities? Well purified ethics and correct view. When your ethics are well purified and your view is correct, you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, depending on and grounded on ethics.

What four? Meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. When you develop these four kinds of mindfulness meditation, depending on and grounded on ethics, you’ll cross beyond Death’s dominion.”

And then Venerable Uttiya approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving. Then Uttiya, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Uttiya became one of the perfected.

SN 47.17 Noble Ariyasutta

“Mendicants, when these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated they are noble and emancipating, and bring one who practices them to the complete ending of suffering. What four?

It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

When these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated they are noble and emancipating, and bring one who practices them to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 47.18 Divinity Brahmasutta

At one time, when he was first awakened, the Buddha was staying in Uruvelā at the goatherd’s banyan tree on the bank of the Nerañjarā River.[2360]

Then as he was in private retreat this thought came to his mind, “The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.[2361]

What four? A mendicant would meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2362] Or they’d meditate observing an aspect of feelings … or mind … or principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.”

Then the divinity Sahampati knew the Buddha’s train of thought. As easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from the realm of divinity and reappeared in front of the Buddha.[2363] He arranged his robe over one shoulder, raised his cupped palms toward the Buddha, and said:

“That’s so true, Blessed One! That’s so true, Holy One! Sir, the four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.

What four? A mendicant would meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Or they’d meditate observing an aspect of feelings … or mind … or principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. The four kinds of mindfulness meditation are the path to convergence. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.”

That is what the divinity Sahampati said. Then he went on to say:

“The compassionate one, who sees the ending of rebirth,
understands the path to convergence.
By this path people crossed over before,
will cross, and are crossing.”

SN 47.19 At Sedaka Sedakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sumbhas, near the town of the Sumbhas named Sedaka.[2364] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Once upon a time, mendicants, a pole acrobat of the corpse-workers set up the bamboo pole of his tribe and said to his apprentice Medakathālikā,[2365] ‘Come now, dear Medakathālikā, climb up the bamboo pole and stand above my shoulders.’[2366]

‘Yes, tutor,’ she replied. She climbed up the bamboo pole and stood above her tutor’s shoulders.

Then the pole acrobat of the corpse-workers said to Medakathālikā, ‘You look after me, dear Medakathālikā, and I shall look after you. That’s how, guarding and looking after each other, we’ll display our skill, collect our fee, and get down safely from the bamboo pole.’[2367]

When he said this, Medakathālikā said to her teacher, ‘That’s not how it will be, tutor! You look after yourself, and I shall look after myself. That’s how, guarding and looking after ourselves, we’ll display our skill, collect our fee, and get down safely from the bamboo pole.’

That’s the way,” said the Buddha. “It’s just as Medakathālikā said to her tutor.[2368] Thinking ‘I’ll look after myself,’ you should cultivate mindfulness meditation. Thinking ‘I’ll look after others,’ you should cultivate mindfulness meditation. Looking after yourself, you look after others; and looking after others, you look after yourself.

And how do you look after others by looking after yourself? By development, cultivation, and practice of meditation. And how do you look after yourself by looking after others? By acceptance, harmlessness, love, and sympathy.

Thinking ‘I’ll look after myself,’ you should cultivate mindfulness meditation. Thinking ‘I’ll look after others,’ you should cultivate mindfulness meditation. Looking after yourself, you look after others; and looking after others, you look after yourself.”

SN 47.20 The Finest Lady in the Land Janapadakalyāṇīsutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sumbhas, near the town of the Sumbhas named Sedaka. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, suppose that on hearing, ‘The finest lady in the land! The finest lady in the land!’ a large crowd would gather.[2369] And the finest lady in the land would dance and sing in a most thrilling way.[2370] On hearing, ‘The finest lady in the land is dancing and singing! The finest lady in the land is dancing and singing!’ an even larger crowd would gather.

Then a person would come along who wants to live and doesn’t want to die, who wants to be happy and recoils from pain. They’d say to him, ‘My man, this is a bowl full to the brim with oil. You must carry it in between this large crowd and the finest lady in the land. And a man with a drawn sword will follow right behind you. Wherever you spill even a drop, he’ll chop off your head right there.’

What do you think, mendicants? Would that person lose focus on that bowl, and negligently get distracted outside?”

“No, sir.”

“I’ve made up this simile to make a point. And this is what it means. ‘A bowl of oil filled to the brim’ is a term for mindfulness of the body.

So you should train like this: ‘We will develop mindfulness of the body. We’ll cultivate it, make it our vehicle and our basis, keep it up, consolidate it, and properly implement it.’ That’s how you should train.”

The Chapter on Floods

SN 47.95–104 Higher Fetters, Etc. Oghavagga

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

The four kinds of mindfulness meditation should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

These four kinds of mindfulness meditation should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

(The Linked Discourses on Mindfulness Meditation should be told in full as in the Linked Discourses on the Path. These ten discourses correspond to SN 45.171–179, with the above as the final discourse.)

Floods, yokes, grasping,
ties, and underlying tendencies,
kinds of sensual stimulation, hindrances,
aggregates, and fetters high and low.

The Linked Discourses on Mindfulness Meditation, the third section.

The Chapter on Ethics and Duration

SN 47.21 Ethics Sīlasutta

So I have heard. At one time the venerables Ānanda and Bhadda were staying near Pāṭaliputta, in the Chicken Monastery.[2371] Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Bhadda came out of retreat, went to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Ānanda:

“Reverend Ānanda, the Buddha has spoken of skillful ethics. What’s their purpose?”

“Good, good, Reverend Bhadda! Your approach and eloquence are excellent, and it’s a good question. For you asked: ‘The Buddha has spoken of skillful ethics. What’s their purpose?’”

“Yes, reverend.”

“The Buddha has spoken of skillful ethics to the extent necessary for developing the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. The Buddha has spoken of skillful ethics to the extent necessary for developing the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.22 Long Lasting Ciraṭṭhitisutta

The same setting. Venerable Bhadda said to Venerable Ānanda:

“What is the cause, Reverend Ānanda, what is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?[2372] What is the cause, what is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?”

“Good, good, Reverend Bhadda! Your approach and eloquence are excellent, and it’s a good question. For you asked: ‘What is the cause, Reverend Ānanda, what is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One? What is the cause, what is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?’”

“Yes, reverend.”

“It’s because of not developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching doesn’t last long after the final quenching of the Realized One. It’s because of developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. It’s because of not developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching doesn’t last long after the final quenching of the Realized One. It’s because of developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.”

SN 47.23 Decline Parihānasutta

At one time the venerables Ānanda and Bhadda were staying near Pāṭaliputta, in the Chicken Monastery. Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Bhadda came out of retreat, went to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Ānanda:

“What’s the cause, Reverend Ānanda, what’s the reason why the true teaching declines? And what’s the cause, what’s the reason why the true teaching doesn’t decline?”

“Good, good, Reverend Bhadda! Your approach and eloquence are excellent, and it’s a good question. For you asked: ‘What’s the cause, what’s the reason why the true teaching declines? And what’s the cause, what’s the reason why the true teaching doesn’t decline?’”

“Yes, reverend.”

“It’s because of not developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching declines. It’s because of developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching doesn’t decline.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. It’s because of not developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching declines. And it’s because of developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching doesn’t decline.”

SN 47.24 Plain Version Suddhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

These are the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.25 A Certain Brahmin Aññatarabrāhmaṇasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then a certain brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“What is the cause, worthy Gotama, what is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One? And what is the cause, what is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?”

“Brahmin, it’s because of not developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching doesn’t last long after the final quenching of the Realized One. It’s because of developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. It’s because of not developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching doesn’t last long after the final quenching of the Realized One. It’s because of developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.”

When he said this, the brahmin said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 47.26 Partly Padesasutta

At one time the venerables Sāriputta, Mahāmoggallāna, and Anuruddha were staying near Sāketa in the Thorny Wood.[2373] Then in the late afternoon, Sāriputta and Mahāmoggallāna came out of retreat, went to Anuruddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. Sāriputta said to Anuruddha:

“Reverend, they speak of the one called ‘a trainee’. How is a trainee defined?”

“Reverends, a trainee is someone who has partly developed the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. A trainee is someone who has partly developed the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.27 Completely Samattasutta

The same setting.

“Reverend, they speak of the one called ‘an adept’. How is an adept defined?”

“Reverends, an adept is someone who has completely developed the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. An adept is someone who has completely developed the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 47.28 The World Lokasutta

The same setting. “Reverend Anuruddha, what things have you developed and cultivated to attain great direct knowledge?”

“Reverend, I attained great direct knowledge by developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

What four? It’s when I meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I attained great direct knowledge by developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

And it’s because of developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that I directly know the thousandfold galaxy.”

SN 47.29 With Sirivaḍḍha Sirivaḍḍhasutta

At one time Venerable Ānanda was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. Now at that time the householder Sirivaḍḍha was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then he addressed a man:

“Please, my man, go to Venerable Ānanda, and in my name bow with your head to his feet. Say to him: ‘Sir, the householder Sirivaḍḍha is sick, suffering, gravely ill. He bows with his head to your feet.’ And then say: ‘Sir, please visit him at his home out of sympathy.’”

“Yes, sir,” that man replied. He did as Sirivaḍḍha asked. Ānanda consented with silence.

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the householder Sirivaḍḍha, sat down on the seat spread out, and said to him:

“I hope you’re keeping well, householder, I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”

“So you should train like this: ‘I’ll meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I’ll meditate on an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.’ That’s how you should train.”

“These four kinds of mindfulness meditation that were taught by the Buddha are found in me, and I exhibit them.[2374] For I meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. And of the five lower fetters taught by the Buddha, I don’t see any that I haven’t given up.”

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate! You have declared the fruit of non-return.”

SN 47.30 With Mānadinna Mānadinnasutta

The same setting. Now at that time the householder Mānadinna was sick, suffering, gravely ill.[2375] Then he addressed a man:

“Please, my man, go to Venerable Ānanda …” …

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading. When I experience such painful feelings I meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. And of the five lower fetters taught by the Buddha, I don’t see any that I haven’t given up.”

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate! You have declared the fruit of non-return.”

The Chapter on Leading to Awakening

SN 48.61 Fetters Saṁyojanasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, when these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to giving up the fetters. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to giving up the fetters.”

SN 48.62 Tendencies Anusayasutta

“Mendicants, when these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to uprooting the underlying tendencies. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to uprooting the underlying tendencies.”

SN 48.63 Complete Understanding Pariññāsutta

“Mendicants, when these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to the complete understanding of the course of time. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to the complete understanding of the course of time.”

SN 48.64 Ending of Defilements Āsavakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, when these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to the ending of defilements.[2454] What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to the ending of defilements.”[2455]

“Mendicants, when these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to giving up the fetters, uprooting the underlying tendencies, completely understanding the course of time, and ending the defilements. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they lead to giving up the fetters, uprooting the underlying tendencies, completely understanding the course of time, and ending the defilements.”

SN 48.65 Two Fruits Paṭhamaphalasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Because of developing and cultivating these five faculties, one of two results can be expected: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

SN 48.66 Seven Benefits Dutiyaphalasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Because of developing and cultivating these five faculties, seven fruits and benefits can be expected. What seven? They attain enlightenment early on in this very life. If not, they attain enlightenment at the time of death. If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters, they’re extinguished between one life and the next … they’re extinguished upon landing … they’re extinguished without extra effort … they’re extinguished with extra effort … they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm.

Because of developing and cultivating these five faculties, these seven fruits and benefits can be expected.”

SN 48.67 A Tree (1st) Paṭhamarukkhasutta

“Mendicants, of all the trees in the Black Plum Tree Land, the black plum is said to be the best.[2456] In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened. And what are the qualities on the side of awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are qualities on the side of awakening, in that they lead to becoming awakened. Of all the trees in the Black Plum Tree Land, the black plum is said to be the best. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.”

SN 48.68 A Tree (2nd) Dutiyarukkhasutta

“Mendicants, of all the trees belonging to the gods of the thirty-three, the Orchid Tree is said to be the best.[2457] In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.

And what are the qualities on the side of awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are qualities on the side of awakening, in that they lead to awakening.

Of all the trees belonging to the gods of the thirty-three, the Orchid Tree is said to be the best. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.”

SN 48.69 A Tree (3rd) Tatiyarukkhasutta

“Mendicants, of all the trees belonging to the titans, the Vivid Patala is said to be the best.[2458] In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened. And what are the qualities on the side of awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are qualities on the side of awakening, in that they lead to awakening. Of all the trees belonging to the titans, the Vivid Patala is said to be the best. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened”

SN 48.70 A Tree (4th) Catuttharukkhasutta

“Mendicants, of all the trees belonging to the phoenixes, the Red Silk-Cotton Tree is said to be the best.[2459] In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened. And what are the qualities on the side of awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are qualities on the side of awakening, in that they lead to awakening. Of all the trees belonging to the phoenixes, the Red Silk-Cotton Tree is said to be the best. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.”

The Chapter on the Six Faculties

SN 48.21 Future Lives Punabbhavasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. As long as I didn’t truly understand these five faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when I did truly understand these five faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

SN 48.22 The Life Faculty Jīvitindriyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three faculties.[2415] What three? The faculties of femininity, masculinity, and life.[2416] These are the three faculties.”

SN 48.23 The Faculty of Enlightenment Aññindriyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three faculties. What three? The faculty of understanding that enlightenment is imminent. The faculty of enlightenment. The faculty of one who is enlightened.[2417] These are the three faculties.”

SN 48.24 A One-Seeder Ekabījīsutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties.[2418] What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re one who is extinguished between one life and the next … one who is extinguished upon landing … one who is extinguished without extra effort … one who is extinguished with extra effort … one who heads upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm … a once-returner … a one-seeder … one who goes from family to family … one who has seven rebirths at most … a follower of teachings … a follower by faith.”

SN 48.25 Plain Version Suddhakasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six faculties.[2419] What six? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. These are the six faculties.”

SN 48.26 A Stream-Enterer Sotāpannasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six faculties. What six? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. A noble disciple comes to truly understand these six faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. Such a noble disciple is called a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 48.27 A Perfected One Arahantasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six faculties. What six? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. A mendicant comes to be freed by not grasping after truly understanding these six faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape.

Such a mendicant is called a perfected one, with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment.”

SN 48.28 Awakened Sambuddhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six faculties. What six? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind.

As long as I didn’t truly understand these six faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when I did truly understand these six faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

SN 48.29 Ascetics and Brahmins (1st) Paṭhamasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six faculties. What six? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind.

There are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand the origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape when it comes to these six faculties. I don’t deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables don’t realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and don’t live having realized it with their own insight in this very life.

There are ascetics and brahmins who do truly understand the origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape when it comes to these six faculties. I deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and live having realized it with their own insight.”

SN 48.30 Ascetics and Brahmins (2nd) Dutiyasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t understand the eye faculty, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. They don’t understand the ear faculty … nose faculty … tongue faculty … body faculty … mind faculty, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. I don’t deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables don’t realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and don’t live having realized it with their own insight in this very life.

There are ascetics and brahmins who do understand the eye faculty, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. They understand the ear faculty … nose faculty … tongue faculty … body faculty … mind faculty, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. I deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and live having realized it with their own insight.”

The Chapter on Old Age

SN 48.41 Old Age Jarādhammasutta

So I have heard.[2428] At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery. Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat and sat warming his back in the last rays of the sun.

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and while massaging the Buddha’s limbs he said:

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing, how the complexion of your skin is no longer pure and bright. Your limbs are flaccid and wrinkled, and your body is stooped. And it’s apparent that there has been a deterioration in your faculties of eye, ear, nose, tongue, and body.”

“That’s how it is, Ānanda. When young you’re liable to grow old; when healthy you’re liable to get sick; and when alive you’re liable to die. The complexion of the skin is no longer pure and bright. The limbs are flaccid and wrinkled, and the body is stooped. And it’s apparent that there has been a deterioration in the faculties of eye, ear, nose, tongue, and body.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Curse this wretched old age,
which makes you so ugly.
That’s how much this delightful puppet
is ground down by old age.

Even if you live for a hundred years,
you’ll still end up dying.
Death spares no one,
but crushes all underfoot.”

SN 48.42 The Brahmin Uṇṇābha Uṇṇābhabrāhmaṇasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Uṇṇābha the brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him.[2429] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, these five faculties have different domains and different ranges, and don’t experience each other’s domain and range.[2430] What five? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, and body. What do these five faculties, with their different domains and ranges, have recourse to? What experiences their domains and ranges?”

“Brahmin, these five faculties have different domains and different ranges, and don’t experience each other’s domain and range. What five? The faculties of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, and body. These five faculties, with their different domains and ranges, have recourse to the mind. And the mind experiences their domains and ranges.”[2431]

“But worthy Gotama, what does the mind have recourse to?”

“The mind has recourse to mindfulness.”

“But what does mindfulness have recourse to?”

“Mindfulness has recourse to freedom.”[2432]

“But what does freedom have recourse to?”

“Freedom has recourse to extinguishment.”

“But what does extinguishment have recourse to?”

“This question goes too far, brahmin! You weren’t able to grasp the limit of questioning.[2433] For extinguishment is the objective, destination, and culmination of the spiritual life.”

And then the brahmin Uṇṇābha approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then, not long after he had left, the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Suppose there was a bungalow or a hall with a peaked roof, with windows on the eastern side. When the sun rises and a ray of light enters through a window, where would it land?”

“On the western wall, sir.”

“In the same way, the brahmin Uṇṇābha’s faith in the Realized One is settled, rooted, and planted deep. It’s strong and can’t be shifted by any ascetic or brahmin or god or Māra or divinity or by anyone in the world. If he were to pass away at this time, he would be bound by no fetter that might return him to this world.”[2434]

SN 48.43 At Sāketa Sāketasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāketa in the deer park at the Añjana Wood. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, is there a method in which the five faculties become the five powers, and the five powers become the five faculties?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Mendicants, there is a method in which the five faculties become the five powers, and the five powers become the five faculties.

And what is that method? The faculty of faith is the power of faith, and the power of faith is the faculty of faith.[2435] The faculty of energy is the power of energy, and the power of energy is the faculty of energy. The faculty of mindfulness is the power of mindfulness, and the power of mindfulness is the faculty of mindfulness. The faculty of immersion is the power of immersion, and the power of immersion is the faculty of immersion. The faculty of wisdom is the power of wisdom, and the power of wisdom is the faculty of wisdom.

Suppose there was a river slanting, sloping, and inclining to the east, and in the middle was an island. There’s a method in which that river can be reckoned to have just one stream. But there’s also a method in which that river can be reckoned to have two streams.

And what’s the method in which that river can be reckoned to have just one stream? By taking into account the water to the east and the west of the island, that river can be reckoned to have just one stream.

And what’s the method in which that river can be reckoned to have two streams? By taking into account the water to the north and the south of the island, that river can be reckoned to have two streams.[2436]

By the same method, the faculty of faith is the power of faith, and the power of faith is the faculty of faith. The faculty of energy is the power of energy, and the power of energy is the faculty of energy. The faculty of mindfulness is the power of mindfulness, and the power of mindfulness is the faculty of mindfulness. The faculty of immersion is the power of immersion, and the power of immersion is the faculty of immersion. The faculty of wisdom is the power of wisdom, and the power of wisdom is the faculty of wisdom.

It’s because of developing and cultivating the five faculties that a mendicant realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

SN 48.44 At the Eastern Gate Pubbakoṭṭhakasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in Sāvatthī at the eastern gate. Then the Buddha said to Venerable Sāriputta:

“Sāriputta, do you have faith that the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom, when developed and cultivated, have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination?”

“Sir, in this case I don’t rely on faith in the Buddha’s claim that[2437] the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom, when developed and cultivated, have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination. There are those who have not known or seen or understood or realized or experienced this with wisdom. They may rely on faith in this matter. But there are those who have known, seen, understood, realized, and experienced this with wisdom. They have no doubts or uncertainties in this matter. I have known, seen, understood, realized, and experienced this with wisdom. I have no doubts or uncertainties that the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom, when developed and cultivated, have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! There are those who have not known or seen or understood or realized or experienced this with wisdom. They may rely on faith in this matter. But there are those who have known, seen, understood, realized, and experienced this with wisdom. They have no doubts or uncertainties that the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom, when developed and cultivated, have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination.”

SN 48.45 At the Eastern Monastery (1st) Paṭhamapubbārāmasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, how many faculties must a mendicant develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place”’?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“A mendicant must develop and cultivate one faculty so that they can declare enlightenment.[2438] What one? The faculty of wisdom. When a noble disciple has wisdom, the faith, energy, mindfulness, and immersion that follow along with that become stabilized.[2439] This is the one faculty that a mendicant must develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’”

SN 48.46 At the Eastern Monastery (2nd) Dutiyapubbārāmasutta

The same setting.

“Mendicants, how many faculties must a mendicant develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place”’?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“A mendicant must develop and cultivate two faculties so that they can declare enlightenment. What two? Noble wisdom and noble freedom. For their noble wisdom is the faculty of wisdom. And their noble freedom is the faculty of immersion.

These are the two faculties that a mendicant must develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’”

SN 48.47 At the Eastern Monastery (3rd) Tatiyapubbārāmasutta

The same setting.

“Mendicants, how many faculties must a mendicant develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place”’?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“A mendicant must develop and cultivate four faculties so that they can declare enlightenment. What four? The faculties of energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

These are the four faculties that a mendicant must develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’”

SN 48.48 At the Eastern Monastery (4th) Catutthapubbārāmasutta

The same setting.

“Mendicants, how many faculties must a mendicant develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place”’?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“A mendicant must develop and cultivate five faculties so that they can declare enlightenment. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

These are the five faculties that a mendicant must develop and cultivate so that they can declare enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’”

SN 48.49 About Bhāradvāja the Alms-Gatherer Piṇḍolabhāradvājasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery.

Now at that time Venerable Bhāradvāja the Alms-Gatherer had declared enlightenment: “I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened. Then they said, “What reason does Bhāradvāja the Alms-Gatherer see for doing this?”

“It’s because Bhāradvāja the Alms-Gatherer has developed and cultivated three faculties that he declares enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’

What three? The faculties of mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

It’s because Bhāradvāja the Alms-Gatherer has developed and cultivated these three faculties that he declares enlightenment.

What’s the culmination of these three faculties? They culminate in ending. In the ending of what? Of rebirth, old age, and death.

It’s because he sees that they culminate in the ending of rebirth, old age, and death that Bhāradvāja the Alms-Gatherer declares enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’”

SN 48.50 At Āpaṇa Āpaṇasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Aṅgas, near the Aṅgan town named Āpaṇa.[2440] Then the Buddha said to Venerable Sāriputta:

“Sāriputta, would a noble disciple who is sure and devoted to the Realized One have any doubt or uncertainty about the Realized One or his instructions?”

“Sir, a noble disciple who is sure and devoted to the Realized One would have no doubt or uncertainty about the Realized One or his instructions.

You can expect that a faithful noble disciple will live with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. For their energy is the faculty of energy.

You can expect that a faithful and energetic noble disciple will be mindful, with utmost mindfulness and alertness, able to remember and recall what was said and done long ago. For their mindfulness is the faculty of mindfulness.

You can expect that a faithful, energetic, and mindful noble disciple will, relying on letting go, gain immersion, gain unification of mind. For their immersion is the faculty of immersion.

You can expect that a faithful, energetic, mindful noble disciple with their mind immersed in samādhi will understand this: ‘Transmigration has no known beginning.[2441] No first point is found of sentient beings roaming and transmigrating, shrouded by ignorance and fettered by craving. But when that dark mass of ignorance fades away and ceases with no residue left behind, that state is peaceful and sublime. That is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ For their noble wisdom is the faculty of wisdom.[2442]

When a noble disciple has tried again and again, recollected again and again, entered immersion again and again, and understood with wisdom again and again, they will be confident of this: ‘I have previously heard of these things. But now I have direct meditative experience of them, and see them with penetrating wisdom.’ For their faith is the faculty of faith.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta!

Sāriputta, a noble disciple who is sure and devoted to the Realized One would have no doubt or uncertainty about the Realized One or his instructions. …”

The Buddha then repeated Sāriputta’s answer word for word.

The Chapter on Weaker

SN 48.11 Gain Paṭilābhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

And what is the faculty of faith? It’s when a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ This is called the faculty of faith.

And what is the faculty of energy? The energy that’s gained owing to the four right efforts. This is called the faculty of energy.

And what is the faculty of mindfulness? The mindfulness that’s gained owing to the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. This is called the faculty of mindfulness.

And what is the faculty of immersion? It’s when a noble disciple, relying on letting go, gains immersion, gains unification of mind. This is called the faculty of immersion.

And what is the faculty of wisdom? It’s when a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is called the faculty of wisdom.

These are the five faculties.”

SN 48.12 In Brief (1st) Paṭhamasaṁkhittasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties.[2410] What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re a non-returner. If they are weaker still, they’re a once-returner. If they are weaker still, they’re a stream-enterer. If they’re weaker still, they’re a follower of teachings. If they’re weaker still, they’re a follower by faith.”[2411]

SN 48.13 In Brief (2nd) Dutiyasaṁkhittasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re a non-returner … a once-returner … a stream-enterer … a follower of teachings … a follower by faith.

So from a disparity of faculties there’s a disparity of fruits. And from a disparity of fruits there’s a disparity of individuals.”

SN 48.14 In Brief (3rd) Tatiyasaṁkhittasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re a non-returner … a once-returner … a stream-enterer … a follower of teachings … a follower by faith.

So, mendicants, if you practice partially you succeed partially. If you practice fully you succeed fully.[2412] But in any case, these five faculties are not barren, I say.”

SN 48.15 In Detail (1st) Paṭhamavitthārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re one who is extinguished between one life and the next … one who is extinguished upon landing … one who is extinguished without extra effort … one who is extinguished with extra effort … one who heads upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm … a once-returner … a stream-enterer … a follower of teachings … a follower by faith.”

SN 48.16 In Detail (2nd) Dutiyavitthārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re one who is extinguished between one life and the next … one who is extinguished upon landing … one who is extinguished without extra effort … one who is extinguished with extra effort … one who heads upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm … a once-returner … a stream-enterer … a follower of teachings … a follower by faith.

So from a disparity of faculties there’s a disparity of fruits. And from a disparity of fruits there’s a disparity of individuals.”

SN 48.17 In Detail (3rd) Tatiyavitthārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re one who is extinguished between one life and the next … one who is extinguished upon landing … one who is extinguished without extra effort … one who is extinguished with extra effort … one who heads upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm … a once-returner … a stream-enterer … a follower of teachings … a follower by faith.

So, mendicants, if you practice fully you succeed fully. If you practice partially you succeed partially. But in any case, these five faculties are not barren, I say.”

SN 48.18 Practicing Paṭipannasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

Someone who has completed and fulfilled these five faculties is a perfected one. If they are weaker than that, they’re practicing to realize the fruit of perfection … a non-returner … practicing to realize the fruit of non-return … a once-returner … practicing to realize the fruit of once-return … a stream-enterer … practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. Someone who totally and utterly lacks these five faculties stands outside in the faction of ordinary persons, I say.”[2413]

SN 48.19 Endowed Sampannasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of someone who is ‘accomplished in the faculties’.[2414] How is someone accomplished in the faculties defined?”

“Mendicant, it’s when a mendicant develops the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom that lead to peace and awakening. This is how someone who is accomplished in the faculties is defined.”

SN 48.20 The Ending of Defilements Āsavakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the five faculties.

It’s because of developing and cultivating these five faculties that a mendicant realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

The Chapter on Floods

SN 48.115–124 Floods, etc. Oghavagga

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

The five faculties should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters. What five? It’s when a mendicant develops the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go.

These five faculties should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

(Tell in full as in the Linked Discourses on the Path, SN 45.171–179, with the above as the final discourse.)

Floods, yokes, grasping,
ties, and underlying tendencies,
kinds of sensual stimulation, hindrances,
aggregates, and fetters high and low.

The Chapter on the Plain Version

SN 48.1 Plain Version Suddhikasutta

At Sāvatthī.

There the Buddha said:

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties.[2393] What five?[2394] The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.[2395] These are the five faculties.”

SN 48.2 A Stream-Enterer (1st) Paṭhamasotāpannasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. A noble disciple comes to truly understand these five faculties’ gratification, drawback, and escape.[2396] Such a noble disciple is called a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 48.3 A Stream-Enterer (2nd) Dutiyasotāpannasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. A noble disciple comes to truly understand these five faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. Such a noble disciple is called a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 48.4 A Perfected One (1st) Paṭhamaarahantasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. A noble disciple comes to be freed by not grasping after truly understanding these five faculties’ gratification, drawback, and escape.[2397] Such a mendicant is called a perfected one, with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment.”

SN 48.5 A Perfected One (2nd) Dutiyaarahantasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. A mendicant comes to be freed by not grasping after truly understanding these five faculties’ origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape. Such a mendicant is called a perfected one, with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment.”

SN 48.6 Ascetics and Brahmins (1st) Paṭhamasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

There are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand the gratification, drawback, and escape when it comes to these five faculties. I don’t deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables don’t realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and don’t live having realized it with their own insight in this very life.

There are ascetics and brahmins who do truly understand the origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape when it comes to these five faculties. I deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and live having realized it with their own insight.”

SN 48.7 Ascetics and Brahmins (2nd) Dutiyasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t understand the faculty of faith, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation.[2398] They don’t understand the faculty of energy … mindfulness … immersion … wisdom, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. I don’t deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables don’t realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and don’t live having realized it with their own insight in this very life.

There are ascetics and brahmins who do understand the faculty of faith, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. They do understand the faculty of energy … mindfulness … immersion … wisdom, its origin, its cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation. I deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and live having realized it with their own insight.”

SN 48.8 Should Be Seen Daṭṭhabbasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties.[2399] What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

And where should the faculty of faith be seen? In the four factors of stream-entry.[2400]

And where should the faculty of energy be seen? In the four right efforts.[2401]

And where should the faculty of mindfulness be seen? In the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.[2402]

And where should the faculty of immersion be seen? In the four absorptions.[2403]

And where should the faculty of wisdom be seen? In the four noble truths.[2404]

These are the five faculties.”

SN 48.9 Analysis (1st) Paṭhamavibhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties.[2405] What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

And what is the faculty of faith? It’s when a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’[2406] This is called the faculty of faith.

And what is the faculty of energy? It’s when a noble disciple lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. This is called the faculty of energy.

And what is the faculty of mindfulness? It’s when a noble disciple is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago.[2407] This is called the faculty of mindfulness.

And what is the faculty of immersion? It’s when a noble disciple, relying on letting go, gains immersion, gains unification of mind.[2408] This is called the faculty of immersion.

And what is the faculty of wisdom? It’s when a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is called the faculty of wisdom.

These are the five faculties.”

SN 48.10 Analysis (2nd) Dutiyavibhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five faculties.[2409] What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

And what is the faculty of faith? It’s when a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ This is called the faculty of faith.

And what is the faculty of energy? It’s when a noble disciple lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen are given up. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. This is called the faculty of energy.

And what is the faculty of mindfulness? It’s when a noble disciple is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. They meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. This is called the faculty of mindfulness.

And what is the faculty of immersion? It’s when a noble disciple, relying on letting go, gains immersion, gains unification of mind. Quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, they enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. And with the fading away of rapture, they enter and remain in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’ With the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, they enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. This is called the faculty of immersion.

And what is the faculty of wisdom? It’s when a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. They truly understand: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. This is called the faculty of wisdom.

These are the five faculties.”

The Chapter on the Boar’s Cave

SN 48.51 At Sālā Sālasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Kosalans near the brahmin village of Sālā. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, the lion, king of beasts, is said to be the best of animals in terms of strength, speed, and courage. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.[2443]

And what are the qualities on the side of awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are qualities on the side of awakening, in that they lead to becoming awakened. The lion, king of beasts, is said to be the best of animals in terms of strength, speed, and courage. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.”

SN 48.52 In the Land of the Mallas Mallikasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Mallas, near the Mallian town named Uruvelakappa.[2444] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, as long as noble knowledge hasn’t arisen for a noble disciple the four faculties are not stable and fixed. But when noble knowledge has arisen for a noble disciple the four faculties become stable and fixed.

It’s just like in a bungalow. As long as the roof peak is not lifted into place, the rafters are not stable or fixed. But when the roof peak is lifted into place, the rafters become stable and fixed.

In the same way, as long as noble knowledge hasn’t arisen for a noble disciple the four faculties are not stable and fixed. But when noble knowledge has arisen for a noble disciple the four faculties become stable and fixed.

What four? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, and immersion. When a noble disciple has wisdom, the faith, energy, mindfulness, and immersion that follow along with that become stabilized.”

SN 48.53 A Trainee Sekhasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, is there a way that a mendicant who is a trainee, standing at the level of a trainee, can understand that they are a trainee? And that a mendicant who is an adept, standing at the level of an adept, can understand that they are an adept?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“There is a way that a mendicant who is a trainee, standing at the level of a trainee, can understand that they are a trainee, and that a mendicant who is an adept, standing at the level of an adept, can understand that they are an adept.

And what is a way that a mendicant who is a trainee can understand that they are a trainee? It’s when a mendicant who is a trainee truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. This is a way that a mendicant who is a trainee can understand that they are a trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant who is a trainee reflects: ‘Is there any other ascetic or brahmin elsewhere whose teaching is as true, as real, as accurate as that of the Buddha?’[2445] They understand: ‘There is no other ascetic or brahmin elsewhere whose teaching is as true, as real, as accurate as that of the Buddha.’ This too is a way that a mendicant who is a trainee can understand that they are a trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant who is a trainee understands the five faculties: faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And although they don’t have direct meditative experience of their destination, apex, fruit, and culmination, they do see them with penetrating wisdom. This too is a way that a mendicant who is a trainee can understand that they are a trainee.

And what is the way that a mendicant who is an adept can understand that they are an adept? It’s when a mendicant who is an adept understands the five faculties: faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. They have direct meditative experience of their destination, apex, fruit, and culmination, and they see them with penetrating wisdom. This is a way that a mendicant who is an adept can understand that they are an adept.

Furthermore, a mendicant who is an adept understands the six faculties: eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. They understand: ‘These six faculties will totally and utterly cease without remainder. And no other six faculties will arise anywhere anyhow.’ This too is a way that a mendicant who is an adept can understand that they are an adept.”

SN 48.54 Footprints Padasutta

“The footprints of all creatures that walk can fit inside an elephant’s footprint, so an elephant’s footprint is said to be the biggest of them all. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the steps that lead to awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.[2446]

And what are the steps that lead to awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are steps that lead to awakening, in that they lead to becoming awakened.

The footprints of all creatures that walk can fit inside an elephant’s footprint, so an elephant’s footprint is said to be the biggest of them all. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the steps that lead to awakening; that is, for becoming awakened. ”

SN 48.55 Heartwood Sārasutta

“Of all kinds of fragrant heartwood, red sandalwood is said to be the best. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.

And what are the qualities on the side of awakening? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are qualities on the side of awakening, in that they lead to becoming awakened.

Of all kinds of fragrant heartwood, red sandalwood is said to be the best. In the same way, the faculty of wisdom is said to be the best of the qualities on the side of awakening; that is, for becoming awakened.”

SN 48.56 Grounded Patiṭṭhitasutta

“Mendicants, when a mendicant is grounded in one thing the five faculties become developed, well developed. What one thing? Diligence. And what is diligence? It’s when a mendicant looks after their mind when it comes to defilements and things accompanied by defilements. As they do so the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom are fully developed. That’s how when a mendicant is grounded in one thing the five faculties become developed, well developed.”

SN 48.57 With the Divinity Sahampati Sahampatibrahmasutta

At one time, when he was first awakened, the Buddha was staying in Uruvelā at the goatherd’s banyan tree on the bank of the Nerañjarā River.[2447]

Then as he was in private retreat this thought came to his mind, “When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination.”

Then the divinity Sahampati knew the Buddha’s train of thought. As easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from the realm of divinity and reappeared in front of the Buddha. He arranged his robe over one shoulder, raised his cupped palms toward the Buddha, and said:

“That’s so true, Blessed One! That’s so true, Holy One! When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. When these five faculties are developed and cultivated they have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination.

Once upon a time, sir, I lived the spiritual life under the fully awakened Buddha Kassapa.[2448] There they knew me as the mendicant Sahaka. Because of developing and cultivating these same five faculties I lost desire for sensual pleasures. When my body broke up, after death, I was reborn in a good place, in the realm of divinity. There they know me as the divinity Sahampati.

That’s so true, Blessed One! That’s so true, Holy One! I know and see how when these five faculties are developed and cultivated they have freedom from death as their objective, destination, and culmination.”

SN 48.58 The Boar’s Cave Sūkarakhatasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain in the Boar’s Cave.[2449] Then the Buddha said to Venerable Sāriputta:

“Sāriputta, considering what benefit does a mendicant with defilements ended, in rolling forth, roll forth with utmost deference for the Realized One or his instructions?”[2450]

“Sir, it is considering the supreme sanctuary from the yoke that a mendicant with defilements ended, in rolling forth, rolls forth with utmost deference for the Realized One or his instructions.”[2451]

“Good, good, Sāriputta! For it is considering the supreme sanctuary from the yoke that a mendicant whose defilements are ended, in rolling forth, rolls forth with utmost deference for the Realized One or his instructions.

And what is that supreme sanctuary from the yoke?”

“It’s when a mendicant with defilements ended develops the faculties of faith,[2452] energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom, which lead to peace and awakening. It is considering this supreme sanctuary from the yoke that a mendicant with defilements ended, in rolling forth, rolls forth with utmost deference for the Realized One or his instructions.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! For this is that supreme sanctuary from the yoke.

And what is that utmost deference that a mendicant with defilements ended, in rolling forth, shows toward the Realized One or his instructions?”

“It’s when a mendicant with defilements ended maintains respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, and immersion.[2453] This is that utmost deference.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! For this is that utmost deference that a mendicant with defilements ended, in rolling forth, shows toward the Realized One or his instructions.”

SN 48.59 Arising (1st) Paṭhamauppādasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these five faculties don’t arise to be developed and cultivated except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These five faculties don’t arise to be developed and cultivated except when a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha has appeared.”

SN 48.60 Arising (2nd) Dutiyauppādasutta

“Mendicants, these five faculties don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training. What five? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These five faculties don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training.”

The Chapter on Searches

SN 49.35–44 Ten Discourses on Searches, Etc. Esanāvagga

“Mendicants, there are these three searches. What three? The search for sensual pleasures, the search for continued existence, and the search for a spiritual path. These are the three searches.

The four right efforts should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three searches. What four? It’s when a mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. … so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed.

These four right efforts should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these three searches.”

(Tell in full as in SN 45.161–170.)

Searches, discriminations, defilements,
states of existence, three kinds of suffering,
barrenness, stains, and troubles,
feelings, craving, and thirst.

The Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on the Ganges

SN 49.1–12 Sloping East, Etc. Gaṅgāpeyyālavagga

At Sāvatthī.

There the Buddha said:

“Mendicants, there are these four right efforts.[2460] What four?

It’s when a mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise.[2461]

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen are given up.

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities arise.

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. These are the four right efforts.

The Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the four right efforts slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

And how does a mendicant who develops the four right efforts slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment?

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise.

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen are given up.

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities arise.

They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed.

That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the four right efforts slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.”

(Tell in full as in SN 45.92–102.)

Six on slanting to the east,
and six on slanting to the ocean;
these two sixes make twelve,
and that’s how this chapter is recited.

The Chapter on Floods

SN 49.45–54 Floods, Etc. Oghavagga

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

The four right efforts should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters. What four? It’s when a mendicant generates enthusiasm … so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. … so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed.

These four right efforts should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

(Tell in full as in SN 45.171–179, with the above as the final discourse.)

Floods, yokes, grasping,
ties, and underlying tendencies,
kinds of sensual stimulation, hindrances,
aggregates, and fetters high and low.

The Linked Discourses on the Right Efforts, the fifth section.

The Chapter on the Iron Ball

SN 51.21 The Path Maggasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I thought: ‘What’s the path and practice for developing the bases of psychic power?’ Then it occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. They think: “My enthusiasm won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.” And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.

They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. They think: “My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.” And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.’

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, a mendicant wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

(The six direct knowledges should be told in full.)

SN 51.22 The Iron Ball Ayoguḷasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2507]

“Sir, do you have personal experience of having gone to the realm of divinity by psychic power with a mind-made body?”

“I do, Ānanda.”

“But do you have personal experience of having gone to the realm of divinity by psychic power with this body made up of the four principal states?”[2508]

“I do, Ānanda.”

“It’s incredible and amazing that the Buddha is at least able to go to the realm of divinity by psychic power with a mind-made body! And that he has personal experience of going to the realm of divinity by psychic power with this body made up of the four principal states!”[2509]

“Ānanda, the Realized Ones are incredible and have incredible qualities. They’re amazing and have amazing qualities.

Sometimes the Realized One submerges his body in his mind and his mind in his body. He meditates after sinking into a perception of bliss and lightness in the body. At that time his body becomes lighter, softer, more workable, and more radiant.

Suppose there was an iron ball that had been heated all day. It’d become lighter, softer, more workable, and more radiant.[2510] In the same way, sometimes the Realized One submerges his body in his mind and his mind in his body. He meditates after sinking into a perception of bliss and lightness in the body. At that time his body becomes lighter, softer, more workable, and more radiant.

Sometimes the Realized One submerges his body in his mind and his mind in his body. He meditates after sinking into a perception of bliss and lightness in the body. At that time his body easily rises up from the ground into the air. He wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying himself and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.

Suppose there was a light tuft of cotton-wool or kapok. Taken up by the wind, it would easily rise up from the ground into the air. In the same way, sometimes the Realized One submerges his body in his mind and his mind in his body. He meditates after sinking into a perception of bliss and lightness in the body. At that time his body easily rises up from the ground into the air. He wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying himself and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.”

SN 51.23 A Mendicant Bhikkhusutta

“Mendicants, there are these four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These are the four bases of psychic power. By developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, a mendicant realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

SN 51.24 Plain Version Suddhikasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These are the four bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.25 Fruits (1st) Paṭhamaphalasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These are the four bases of psychic power. Because of developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, one of two results can be expected: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

SN 51.26 Fruits (2nd) Dutiyaphalasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These are the four bases of psychic power. Because of developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, seven fruits and benefits can be expected.

What seven? They attain enlightenment early on in this very life. If not, they attain enlightenment at the time of death. If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters, they’re extinguished between one life and the next … they’re extinguished upon landing … they’re extinguished without extra effort … they’re extinguished with extra effort … they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. Because of developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, these seven fruits and benefits can be expected.”

SN 51.27 With Ānanda (1st) Paṭhamaānandasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is psychic power? What is the basis of psychic power? What is the development of the bases of psychic power? And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power?”

“Ānanda, take a mendicant who wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. This is called psychic power.

And what is the basis of psychic power? The path and practice that leads to gaining psychic power. This is called the basis of psychic power.

And what is the development of the bases of psychic power? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. This is called the development of the bases of psychic power.

And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.28 With Ānanda (2nd) Dutiyaānandasutta

The Buddha said to Venerable Ānanda: “Ānanda, what is psychic power? What is the basis of psychic power? What is the development of the bases of psychic power? And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. …”

“Ānanda, take a mendicant who wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. This is called psychic power.

And what is the basis of psychic power? The path and practice that leads to gaining psychic power. This is called the basis of psychic power.

And what is the development of the bases of psychic power? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. This is called the development of the bases of psychic power.

And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.29 Several Mendicants (1st) Paṭhamabhikkhusutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is psychic power? What is the basis of psychic power? What is the development of the bases of psychic power? And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power?”

“Mendicants, take a mendicant who wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. This is called psychic power.

And what is the basis of psychic power? The path and practice that leads to gaining psychic power. This is called the basis of psychic power.

And what is the development of the bases of psychic power? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. This is called the development of the bases of psychic power.

And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.30 Several Mendicants (2nd) Dutiyabhikkhusutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha … The Buddha said to them:

“Mendicants, what is psychic power? What is the basis of psychic power? What is the development of the bases of psychic power? And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. …”

“And what is psychic power? It’s a mendicant who wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. This is called psychic power.

And what is the basis of psychic power? The path and practice that leads to gaining psychic power. This is called the basis of psychic power.

And what is the development of the bases of psychic power? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. This is called the development of the bases of psychic power.

And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.31 About Moggallāna Moggallānasutta

There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “What do you think, mendicants? What things has the mendicant Moggallāna developed and cultivated so as to have such power and might?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. …”

“The mendicant Moggallāna has become so powerful and mighty by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? Moggallāna develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. He thinks: ‘My enthusiasm won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And he meditates perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, he develops a mind that’s full of radiance.

He develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. He thinks: ‘My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ … And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, he develops a mind that’s full of radiance. The mendicant Moggallāna has become so powerful and mighty by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.

And by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, the mendicant Moggallāna wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying himself and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.

And by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, the mendicant Moggallāna realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And he lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

SN 51.32 The Realized One Tathāgatasutta

There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “What do you think, mendicants? What things has the Realized One developed and cultivated so as to have such power and might?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“The Realized One has become so powerful and mighty by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. He thinks: ‘My enthusiasm won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And he meditates perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, he develops a mind that’s full of radiance.

He develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. He thinks: ‘My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And he meditates perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, he develops a mind that’s full of radiance.

The Realized One has become so powerful and mighty by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.

And by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, the Realized One wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying himself and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.

And by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, the Realized One realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And he lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

(The six direct knowledges should be told in full.)

The Chapter at the Cāpāla Shrine

SN 51.1 From the Near Shore Apārasutta

“Mendicants, when these four bases of psychic power are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore.[2463] What four?[2464] It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort.[2465] They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort.[2466] They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort.[2467] They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort. When these four bases of psychic power are developed and cultivated they lead to going from the near shore to the far shore.”

SN 51.2 Missed Out Viraddhasutta

“Mendicants, whoever has missed out on the four bases of psychic power has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken the four bases of psychic power has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. Whoever has missed out on these four bases of psychic power has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken these four bases of psychic power has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 51.3 A Noble One Ariyasutta

“Mendicants, when these four bases of psychic power are developed and cultivated they are noble and emancipating, and bring one who practices them to the complete ending of suffering. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. When these four bases of psychic power are developed and cultivated they are noble and emancipating, and bring one who practices them to the complete ending of suffering.”

SN 51.4 Disillusionment Nibbidāsutta

“Mendicants, these four bases of psychic power, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These four bases of psychic power, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.”

SN 51.5 Partly Iddhipadesasutta

“Mendicants, all the ascetics and brahmins in the past who have partly manifested psychic powers have done so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the future who will partly manifest psychic powers will do so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the present who are partly manifesting psychic powers do so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. All the ascetics and brahmins in the past who have partly manifested psychic powers have done so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the future who will partly manifest psychic powers will do so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the present who are partly manifesting psychic powers do so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.6 Completely Samattasutta

“Mendicants, all the ascetics and brahmins in the past who have completely manifested psychic powers have done so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the future who will completely manifest psychic powers will do so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the present who are completely manifesting psychic powers do so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. All the ascetics and brahmins in the past who have completely manifested psychic powers have done so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the future who will completely manifest psychic powers will do so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power. All the ascetics and brahmins in the present who are completely manifesting psychic powers do so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.7 A Mendicant Bhikkhusutta

“Mendicants, all the mendicants in the past … future … present who realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and who live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements, do so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. All the mendicants in the past … future … present who realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and who live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements, do so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.8 Awakened Buddhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These are the four bases of psychic power. It is because he has developed and cultivated these four bases of psychic power that the Realized One is called ‘the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha’.”

SN 51.9 Knowledge Ñāṇasutta

“Mendicants: ‘This is the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.[2468] ‘This basis of psychic power … should be developed.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.

‘This is the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … should be developed.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.

‘This is the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … should be developed.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.

‘This is the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … should be developed.’ … ‘This basis of psychic power … has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.”

SN 51.10 At the Cāpāla Shrine Cetiyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.[2469] Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Vesālī for alms. Then, after the meal, on his return from almsround, he addressed Venerable Ānanda: “Ānanda, get your sitting cloth.[2470] Let’s go to the Cāpāla Shrine for the day’s meditation.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Ānanda. Taking his sitting cloth he followed behind the Buddha.

Then the Buddha went up to the Cāpāla Shrine, and sat down on the seat spread out. Ānanda bowed to the Buddha and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Ānanda, Vesālī is lovely. And the Udena, Gotamaka, Seven Maidens, Many Sons, Sārandada, and Cāpāla Shrines are all lovely. Whoever has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power—made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them—may, if they wish, live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it.[2471] The Realized One has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power, made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them. If he wished, the Realized One could live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it.”

But Ānanda didn’t get it, even though the Buddha dropped such an obvious hint, such a clear sign. He didn’t beg the Buddha, “Sir, may the Blessed One please remain for the proper lifespan! May the Holy One please remain for the proper lifespan! That would be for the welfare and happiness of the people, out of sympathy for the world, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.” For his mind was as if possessed by Māra.[2472]

For a second time … For a third time, the Buddha said to Ānanda:

“Ānanda, Vesālī is lovely. And the Udena, Gotamaka, Seven Maidens, Many Sons, Sārandada, and Cāpāla Shrines are all lovely. Whoever has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power—made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them—may, if they wish, live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it. The Realized One has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power, made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them. If he wished, the Realized One could live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it.”

But Ānanda didn’t get it, even though the Buddha dropped such an obvious hint, such a clear sign. He didn’t beg the Buddha, “Sir, may the Blessed One please remain for the proper lifespan! May the Holy One please remain for the proper lifespan! That would be for the welfare and happiness of the people, out of sympathy for the world, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.” For his mind was as if possessed by Māra.

Then the Buddha said to him, “Go now, Ānanda, at your convenience.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Ānanda. He rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before sitting at the root of a tree close by.

And then, not long after Ānanda had left, Māra the Wicked went up to the Buddha and said to him:[2473]

“Sir, may the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha. Sir, you once made this statement: ‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have monk disciples who are competent, educated, assured, learned, have memorized the teachings, and practice in line with the principle of the teaching. Not until they practice properly, living in line with the teaching. Not until they’ve learned their own denomination, and explain, teach, assert, establish, disclose, analyze, and make it clear. Not until they can legitimately and completely refute the doctrines of others that come up, and teach with a demonstrable basis.’[2474]

Today you do have such monk disciples. May the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.

Sir, you once made this statement: ‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have nun disciples who are competent, educated, self-assured, learned …’ …[2475]

Today you do have such nun disciples. May the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.

Sir, you once made this statement: ‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have layman disciples … and laywoman disciples who are competent, educated, self-assured, learned …’ …

Today you do have such layman[2476] and laywoman disciples. May the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.

Sir, you once made this statement: ‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until my spiritual path is successful and prosperous, extensive, popular, widespread, and fully revealed among gods and humans.’ Today your spiritual path is successful and prosperous, extensive, popular, widespread, and fully revealed among gods and humans. May the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.”

When this was said, the Buddha said to Māra, “Relax, Wicked One. The full extinguishment of the Realized One will be soon.[2477] Three months from now the Realized One will be fully extinguished.”[2478]

So at the Cāpāla Shrine the Buddha, mindful and aware, surrendered the life force.[2479] When he did so there was a great earthquake, awe-inspiring and hair-raising, and thunder cracked the sky.[2480] Then, understanding this matter, on that occasion the Buddha expressed this heartfelt sentiment:

“Comparing the incomparable with the creation of prolonged life,[2481]
the sage surrendered the life force.[2482]
Happy inside, serene,
he shattered self-creation like a suit of armor.”[2483]

The Chapter on Floods

SN 51.77–86 Floods, Etc. Oghavagga

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

The four bases of psychic power should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. These four bases of psychic power should be developed for the direct knowledge, complete understanding, finishing, and giving up of these five higher fetters.”

(Tell in full as in the Linked Discourses on the Path at SN 45.171–180.)

Floods, yokes, grasping,
ties, and underlying tendencies,
kinds of sensual stimulation, hindrances,
aggregates, and fetters high and low.

The Linked Discourses on the Bases of Psychic Power, the seventh section.

The Chapter on Shaking the Stilt Longhouse

SN 51.11 Before Pubbasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I thought: ‘What’s the cause, what’s the reason for the development of the bases of psychic power?’[2484] Then it occurred to me: ‘It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. They think: “My enthusiasm won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.”[2485] And they meditate perceiving before and behind:[2486] as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below;[2487] as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.

They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. They think: “My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.” And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.’

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they wield the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again; materializing and dematerializing; going unobstructed through a wall, a rampart, or a mountain as if through space; diving in and out of the earth as if it were water; walking on water as if it were earth; flying cross-legged through the sky like a bird; touching and stroking with the hand the sun and moon, so mighty and powerful; controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.[2488]

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, with clairaudience that is purified and superhuman they hear both kinds of sounds, human and heavenly, whether near or far.[2489]

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they understand the minds of other beings and individuals, having encompassed them with their own mind.[2490] They understand mind with greed as ‘mind with greed’, and mind without greed as ‘mind without greed’. They understand mind with hate … mind without hate … mind with delusion … mind without delusion … constricted mind … scattered mind … expansive mind … unexpansive mind … mind that is not supreme … mind that is supreme … mind immersed in samādhi … mind not immersed in samādhi … freed mind … They understand unfreed mind as ‘unfreed mind’.

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they recollect many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. They remember: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so they recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details.[2491]

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they see sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. They understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. ‘These dear beings did bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. They denounced the noble ones; they had wrong view; and they chose to act out of that wrong view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. These dear beings, however, did good things by way of body, speech, and mind. They never denounced the noble ones; they had right view; and they chose to act out of that right view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ And so, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they see sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. They understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.[2492]

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”[2493]

SN 51.12 Very Fruitful Mahapphalasutta

“Mendicants, when the four bases of psychic power are developed and cultivated they’re very fruitful and beneficial. How so? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. They think: ‘My enthusiasm won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.

They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. They think: ‘My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance. When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way they’re very fruitful and beneficial.

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, a mendicant wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. …

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

SN 51.13 Immersion Due to Enthusiasm Chandasamādhisutta

“Mendicants, if a mendicant depends on enthusiasm in order to gain immersion, gain unification of mind, this is called immersion due to enthusiasm.[2494] They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen are given up. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. These are called active efforts.[2495] And so there is this enthusiasm, this immersion due to enthusiasm, and these active efforts. This is called the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort.

If a mendicant depends on energy in order to gain immersion, gain unification of mind, this is called immersion due to energy. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise … so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. These are called active efforts. And so there is this energy, this immersion due to energy, and these active efforts. This is called the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort.

If a mendicant depends on mental development in order to gain immersion, gain unification of mind, this is called immersion due to mental development. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise … so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. These are called active efforts. And so there is this mental development, this immersion due to mental development, and these active efforts. This is called the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort.

If a mendicant depends on inquiry in order to gain immersion, gain unification of mind, this is called immersion due to inquiry. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise … so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. These are called active efforts. And so there is this inquiry, this immersion due to inquiry, and these active efforts. This is called the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort.”

SN 51.14 With Moggallāna Moggallānasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery. Now at that time several mendicants were staying beneath the longhouse. They were haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, loose-tongued, unmindful, lacking situational awareness and immersion, with straying minds and undisciplined faculties.

Then the Buddha addressed Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, “These spiritual companions of yours staying beneath the longhouse are haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, loose-tongued, unmindful, lacking situational awareness and immersion, with straying minds and undisciplined faculties. Go, Moggallāna, and strike awe in those mendicants!”

“Yes, sir,” replied Mahāmoggallāna. Then he used his psychic power to make the longhouse shake and rock and tremble with his big toe.[2496] Then those mendicants stood to one side, shocked and awestruck.

“Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing! There’s no wind at all; and this stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother has deep foundations. It’s firmly embedded, imperturbable and unshakable. And yet it shakes and rocks and quivers!”

Then the Buddha went up to those mendicants and said:

“Why do you, mendicants, stand to one side, shocked and awestruck?”

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! There’s no wind at all; and this stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother has deep foundations. It’s firmly embedded, imperturbable and unshakable. And yet it shakes and rocks and quivers!”

“Wanting to strike awe in you, the mendicant Moggallāna made the longhouse shake and rock and quiver with his big toe.

What do you think, mendicants? What things has the mendicant Moggallāna developed and cultivated so as to have such power and might?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, listen. The mendicant Moggallāna has become so powerful and mighty by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power. What four? Moggallāna develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. He thinks: ‘My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And he meditates perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, he develops a mind that’s full of radiance. The mendicant Moggallāna has become so powerful and mighty by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.

And by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, the mendicant Moggallāna wields the many kinds of psychic power … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. …[2497]

And by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, the mendicant Moggallāna realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And he lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

SN 51.15 The Brahmin Uṇṇābha Uṇṇābhabrāhmaṇasutta

So I have heard. At one time Venerable Ānanda was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery. Then Uṇṇābha the brahmin went up to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him.[2498] When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to him, “Worthy Ānanda, what’s the goal of leading the spiritual life under the ascetic Gotama?”

“The goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha, brahmin, is to give up desire.”[2499]

“But is there a path and a practice for giving up that desire?”

“There is.”

“What is that path?”

“It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. This is the path and the practice for giving up that desire.”

“This being the case, worthy Ānanda, the path is endless, not finite.[2500] For it’s not possible to give up desire by means of desire.”[2501]

“Well then, brahmin, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like. What do you think, brahmin?[2502] Have you ever had a desire to walk to the park,[2503] but when you arrived at the park, the corresponding desire faded away?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Have you ever had the energy to walk to the park, but when you arrived at the park, the corresponding energy faded away?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Have you ever had the idea to walk to the park,[2504] but when you arrived at the park, the corresponding idea faded away?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Have you ever inquired regarding a walk to the park, but when you arrived at the park, the corresponding inquiry faded away?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, take a mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment. They formerly had the desire to attain perfection, but when they attained perfection the corresponding desire faded away. They formerly had the energy to attain perfection, but when they attained perfection the corresponding energy faded away. They formerly had the idea to attain perfection, but when they attained perfection the corresponding idea faded away. They formerly inquired regarding attaining perfection, but when they attained perfection the corresponding inquiry faded away. What do you think, brahmin? This being the case, is the path endless or finite?”

“Clearly, worthy Ānanda, this being the case, the path is finite, not endless. Excellent, worthy Ānanda! Excellent! As if he were righting the overturned, or revealing the hidden, or pointing out the path to the lost, or lighting a lamp in the dark so people with clear eyes can see what’s there, the worthy Ānanda has made the teaching clear in many ways. I go for refuge to the worthy Gotama, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the worthy Ānanda remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

SN 51.16 Ascetics and Brahmins (1st) Paṭhamasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, all the ascetics and brahmins in the past, future, or present who are mighty and powerful have become so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. All the ascetics and brahmins in the past, future, or present who are mighty and powerful have become so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.17 Ascetics and Brahmins (2nd) Dutiyasamaṇabrāhmaṇasutta

“Mendicants, all the ascetics and brahmins in the past, future, or present who wield the various kinds of psychic power—multiplying themselves and becoming one again; materializing and dematerializing; going unobstructed through a wall, a rampart, or a mountain as if through space; diving in and out of the earth as if it were water; walking on water as if it were earth; flying cross-legged through the sky like a bird; touching and stroking with the hand the sun and moon, so mighty and powerful; controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity—do so by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. Mendicants, all the ascetics and brahmins in the past, future, or present who wield the many kinds of psychic power—multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity—do so by developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.18 A Mendicant Bhikkhusutta

“Mendicants, by developing and cultivating the four bases of psychic power, a mendicant realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. By developing and cultivating these four bases of psychic power, a mendicant realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

SN 51.19 A Teaching on Psychic Power, Etc. Iddhādidesanāsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you psychic power, the bases of psychic power, the development of the bases of psychic power, and the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power.[2505] Listen …

And what is psychic power? It’s when a mendicant wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. This is called psychic power.

And what is the basis of psychic power? The path and practice that leads to gaining psychic power. This is called the basis of psychic power.

And what is the development of the bases of psychic power? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm … energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. This is called the development of the bases of psychic power.

And what is the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the practice that leads to the development of the bases of psychic power.”

SN 51.20 Analysis Vibhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, when the four bases of psychic power are developed and cultivated they’re very fruitful and beneficial.

How so? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. They think: ‘My enthusiasm won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.

They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy … mental development … inquiry, and active effort. They think: ‘My inquiry won’t be too lax or too tense. And it’ll be neither constricted internally nor scattered externally.’ And they meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before; as below, so above; as above, so below; as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance.

And what is enthusiasm that’s too lax? It’s when enthusiasm is coupled with laziness. This is called lax enthusiasm.

And what is enthusiasm that’s too tense? It’s when enthusiasm is coupled with restlessness. This is called tense enthusiasm.

And what is enthusiasm that’s constricted internally? It’s when enthusiasm is coupled with dullness and drowsiness. This is called enthusiasm constricted internally.

And what is enthusiasm that’s scattered externally? It’s when enthusiasm is frequently scattered and diffused externally on account of the five kinds of sensual stimulation. This is called enthusiasm scattered externally.

And how does a mendicant meditate perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before? It’s when the perception of before and behind is properly grasped, focused on, borne in mind, and penetrated with wisdom by a mendicant. That’s how a mendicant meditates perceiving before and behind: as before, so behind; as behind, so before.

And how does a mendicant meditate as below, so above; as above, so below? It’s when a mendicant examines their own body up from the soles of the feet and down from the tips of the hairs, wrapped in skin and full of many kinds of filth. ‘In this body there is head hair, body hair, nails, teeth, skin, flesh, sinews, bones, bone marrow, kidneys, heart, liver, diaphragm, spleen, lungs, intestines, mesentery, undigested food, feces, bile, phlegm, pus, blood, sweat, fat, tears, grease, saliva, snot, synovial fluid, urine.’ That’s how a mendicant meditates as below, so above; as above, so below.

And how does a mendicant meditate as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort, with the same features, attributes, and signs by day as by night. And they develop it with the same features, attributes, and signs by night as by day. That’s how a mendicant meditates as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day.

And how, with an open and unenveloped heart, does a mendicant develop a mind that’s full of radiance? It’s when a mendicant has properly grasped the perception of light, and has properly grasped the perception of day. That’s how, with an open and unenveloped heart, a mendicant develops a mind that’s full of radiance.

And what is energy that’s too lax? …

And what is mental development that’s too lax? …

And what is inquiry that’s too lax? It’s when inquiry is coupled with laziness. This is called lax inquiry.

And what is inquiry that’s too tense? It’s when inquiry is coupled with restlessness. This is called tense inquiry.

And what is inquiry that’s constricted internally? It’s when inquiry is coupled with dullness and drowsiness. This is called inquiry constricted internally.

And what is inquiry that’s scattered externally? It’s when inquiry is frequently scattered and diffused externally on account of the five kinds of sensual stimulation. This is called inquiry scattered externally. … That’s how, with an open and unenveloped heart, a mendicant develops a mind that’s full of radiance. When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way they’re very fruitful and beneficial.

When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, a mendicant wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity. …[2506] When the four bases of psychic power have been developed and cultivated in this way, they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

The Chapter on In Private

SN 52.1 In Private (1st) Paṭhamarahogatasutta

So I have heard. At one time Venerable Anuruddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.[2511] Then as Anuruddha was in private retreat this thought came to his mind:

“Whoever has missed out on these four kinds of mindfulness meditation has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.[2512] Whoever has undertaken these four kinds of mindfulness meditation has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.”

Then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna knew what Venerable Anuruddha was thinking. As easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he reappeared in front of Anuruddha,[2513] and said to him:

“Reverend Anuruddha, how do you define the undertaking of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation by a mendicant?”

“Reverend, it’s when a mendicant, with respect to the body internally, meditates observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2514] With respect to the body externally, they meditate observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. With respect to the body internally and externally, they meditate observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive and the repulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. If they wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do.

With respect to feelings internally … externally … internally and externally, they meditate observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish …

With respect to the mind internally … externally … internally and externally, they meditate observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish …

With respect to principles internally … externally … internally and externally, they meditate observing the liability to originate, to vanish, and to originate and vanish …

If they wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do. … If they wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, ignoring both the repulsive and the unrepulsive,’ that’s what they do.

That’s how to define the undertaking of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation by a mendicant.”

SN 52.2 In Private (2nd) Dutiyarahogatasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then as Anuruddha was in private retreat this thought came to his mind:

“Whoever has missed out on these four kinds of mindfulness meditation has missed out on the noble path to the complete ending of suffering. Whoever has undertaken these four kinds of mindfulness meditation has undertaken the noble path to the complete ending of suffering.”

Then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna knew what Venerable Anuruddha was thinking. As easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he reappeared in front of Anuruddha and said to him:

“Reverend Anuruddha, how do you define the undertaking of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation by a mendicant?”

“Reverend, it’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body internally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of the body externally … internally and externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

They meditate observing an aspect of feelings internally … externally … internally and externally …

They meditate observing an aspect of the mind internally … externally … internally and externally …

They meditate observing an aspect of principles internally … externally … internally and externally—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how to define the undertaking of the four kinds of mindfulness meditation by a mendicant.”

SN 52.3 On the Bank of the Sutanu Sutanusutta

At one time Venerable Anuruddha was staying near Sāvatthī on the bank of the Sutanu.[2515] Then several mendicants went up to Venerable Anuruddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side, and said to him:

“What things has Venerable Anuruddha developed and cultivated to attain great direct knowledge?”

“Reverends, I attained great direct knowledge by developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? I meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I attained great direct knowledge by developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

And it was by developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that I directly knew the lower principle as lower, the middle principle as middle, and the higher principle as higher.”[2516]

SN 52.4 At Thorny Wood (1st) Paṭhamakaṇḍakīsutta

At one time the venerables Anuruddha, Sāriputta, and Mahāmoggallāna were staying near Sāketa in the Thorny Wood.[2517] Then in the late afternoon, Sāriputta and Mahāmoggallāna came out of retreat, went to Anuruddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. Sāriputta said to Anuruddha:

“Reverend Anuruddha, what things should a trainee mendicant enter and remain in?”

“Reverend Sāriputta, a trainee mendicant should enter and remain in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. A trainee mendicant should enter and remain in these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 52.5 At Thorny Wood (2nd) Dutiyakaṇḍakīsutta

At Sāketa. Sāriputta said to Anuruddha:

“Reverend Anuruddha, what things should a mendicant who is an adept enter and remain in?”

“Reverend Sāriputta, a mendicant who is an adept should enter and remain in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. A mendicant who is an adept should enter and remain in these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 52.6 At Thorny Wood (3rd) Tatiyakaṇḍakīsutta

At Sāketa. Sāriputta said to Anuruddha:

“What things has Venerable Anuruddha developed and cultivated to attain great direct knowledge?”

“Reverend, I attained great direct knowledge by developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? I meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I meditate observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I attained great direct knowledge by developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

And it’s because of developing and cultivating these four kinds of mindfulness meditation that I directly know the thousandfold galaxy.”

SN 52.7 The Ending of Craving Taṇhākkhayasutta

At Sāvatthī.

There Venerable Anuruddha addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Anuruddha said this:

“Reverends, when these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated they lead to the ending of craving. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body … feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. When these four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated they lead to the ending of craving.”

SN 52.8 The Salaḷa Tree Hut Salaḷāgārasutta

At one time Venerable Anuruddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the salaḷa tree hut.[2518] There Venerable Anuruddha addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, suppose that, although the Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east, a large crowd were to come along with a spade and basket, saying: ‘We’ll make this Ganges River slant, slope, and incline to the west!’ What do you think, reverends? Would they succeed?”

“No, reverend. Why is that? The Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. It’s not easy to make it slant, slope, and incline to the west. That large crowd will eventually get weary and frustrated.”

“In the same way, while a mendicant develops and cultivates the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, if rulers or their chief ministers, friends or colleagues, relatives or family should invite them to accept wealth, saying: ‘Please, my man, why let these ocher robes torment you? Why follow the practice of shaving your head and carrying an alms bowl? Come, return to a lesser life, enjoy wealth, and make merit!’

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who is developing and cultivating the four kinds of mindfulness meditation to resign the training and return to a lesser life. Why is that? Because for a long time that mendicant’s mind has slanted, sloped, and inclined to seclusion. So it’s impossible for them to return to a lesser life.

And how does a mendicant develop and cultivate the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body … feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. That’s how a mendicant develops and cultivates the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

SN 52.9 In Ambapālī’s Mango Grove Ambapālivanasutta

At one time the venerables Anuruddha and Sāriputta were staying near Vesālī in Ambapālī’s Mango Grove. Then in the late afternoon, Sāriputta came out of retreat, went to Anuruddha, and said to him:

“Reverend Anuruddha, your faculties are so very clear, and your complexion is pure and bright. What kind of meditation are you usually practicing these days?”

“These days, reverend, I usually meditate with my mind firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? I meditate observing an aspect of the body … feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. These days I usually meditate with my mind firmly established in these four kinds of mindfulness meditation. A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—usually meditates with their mind firmly established in these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

“We’re so fortunate, reverend, so very fortunate, to have heard such a dramatic statement in the presence of Venerable Anuruddha.”

SN 52.10 Gravely Ill Bāḷhagilānasutta

At one time Venerable Anuruddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the Dark Forest. And he was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then several mendicants went up to Venerable Anuruddha, and said to him:

“What meditation does Venerable Anuruddha practice so that physical pain doesn’t occupy his mind?”

“Reverends, I meditate with my mind firmly established in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation so that physical pain doesn’t occupy my mind. What four? I meditate observing an aspect of the body … feelings … mind … principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. I meditate with my mind firmly established in these four kinds of mindfulness meditation so that physical pain doesn’t occupy my mind.”

The Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on the Ganges

SN 53.1–12 Absorptions, Etc. Gaṅgāpeyyālavagga

At Sāvatthī.[2520]

“Mendicants, there are these four absorptions. What four?

It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected.

As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected.

And with the fading away of rapture, they enter and remain in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’

With the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, they enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.

These are the four absorptions.

The Ganges River slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. In the same way, a mendicant who develops and cultivates the four absorptions slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.

And how does a mendicant who develops and cultivates the four absorptions slant, slope, and incline to extinguishment?

It’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected.

As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption.

That’s how a mendicant who develops and cultivates the four absorptions slants, slopes, and inclines to extinguishment.”

Six on slanting to the east,
and six on slanting to the ocean;
these two sixes make twelve,
and that’s how this chapter is recited.

Chapter Two

SN 54.11 Icchānaṅgala Icchānaṅgalasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in a forest near Icchānaṅgala.[2558] There he addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants, I wish to go on retreat for three months. No-one should approach me, except the one who brings my almsfood.”

“Yes, sir,” replied those mendicants. And no-one approached him, except the one who brought the almsfood.

Then after three months had passed, the Buddha came out of retreat and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, if wanderers who follow another religion were to ask you: ‘Reverends, what was the ascetic Gotama’s usual meditation during the rainy season residence?’ You should answer them like this. ‘Reverends, the ascetic Gotama’s usual meditation during the rainy season residence was immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.’

In this regard: mindful, I breathe in. Mindful, I breathe out.[2559]

Breathing in heavily I know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily I know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’ Breathing in lightly I know: ‘I’m breathing in lightly.’ Breathing out lightly I know: ‘I’m breathing out lightly.’ I know: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the whole body.’ …

I know: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ I know: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

For if anything should be rightly called ‘a noble meditation’, or else ‘a divine meditation’, or else ‘a realized one’s meditation’,[2560] it’s immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

For those mendicants who are trainees—who haven’t achieved their heart’s desire, but live aspiring to the supreme sanctuary from the yoke—the development and cultivation of immersion due to mindfulness of breathing leads to the ending of defilements.

For those mendicants who are perfected—who have ended the defilements, completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and are rightly freed through enlightenment—the development and cultivation of immersion due to mindfulness of breathing leads to blissful meditation in this life, and to mindfulness and awareness.

For if anything should be rightly called ‘a noble meditation’, or else ‘a divine meditation’, or else ‘a realized one’s meditation’, it’s immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.”

SN 54.12 In Doubt Kaṅkheyyasutta

At one time Venerable Lomasakaṅgiya was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery.[2561] Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to Venerable Lomasakaṅgiya, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, is the meditation of a trainee just the same as the meditation of a realized one? Or is the meditation of a trainee different from the meditation of a realized one?”

“Reverend Mahānāma, the meditation of a trainee and a realized one are not the same; they are different. Those mendicants who are trainees haven’t achieved their heart’s desire, but live aspiring for the supreme sanctuary from the yoke. They meditate after giving up the five hindrances.[2562] What five? The hindrances of sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt.

Those who are trainee mendicants … meditate after giving up the five hindrances.

Those mendicants who are perfected—who have ended the defilements, completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and are rightly freed through enlightenment—for them, the five hindrances are cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, obliterated, and unable to arise in the future.[2563] What five? The hindrances of sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt.

Those mendicants who are perfected—who have ended the defilements … for them, the five hindrances are cut off at the root … and unable to arise in the future. And here’s another way to understand how the meditation of a trainee and a realized one are different.

At one time the Buddha was staying in a forest near Icchānaṅgala. There he addressed the mendicants, ‘Mendicants, I wish to go on retreat for three months. No-one should approach me, except the one who brings my almsfood.’

‘Yes, sir,’ replied those mendicants. And no-one approached him, except the one who brought the almsfood.

Then after three months had passed, the Buddha came out of retreat and addressed the mendicants:

‘Mendicants, if wanderers who follow another religion were to ask you: “Reverends, what was the ascetic Gotama’s usual meditation during the rainy season residence?” You should answer them like this: “Reverends, the ascetic Gotama’s usual meditation during the rainy season residence was immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.”

In this regard: mindful, I breathe in. Mindful, I breathe out.

Breathing in heavily I know: “I’m breathing in heavily.” Breathing out heavily I know: “I’m breathing out heavily.” …

I know: “I’ll breathe in observing letting go.” I know: “I’ll breathe out observing letting go.”

For if anything should be rightly called “noble meditation”, or else “divine meditation”, or else “a realized one’s meditation”, it’s immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

For those mendicants who are trainees—who haven’t achieved their heart’s desire, but live aspiring for the supreme sanctuary from the yoke—the development and cultivation of immersion due to mindfulness of breathing leads to the ending of defilements.

For those mendicants who are perfected—who have ended the defilements, completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and are rightly freed through enlightenment—the development and cultivation of immersion due to mindfulness of breathing leads to blissful meditation in this very life, and to mindfulness and awareness.

For if anything should be rightly called “noble meditation”, or else “divine meditation”, or else “a realized one’s meditation”, it’s immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.’

This is another way to understand how the meditation of a trainee and a realized one are different.”

SN 54.13 With Ānanda (1st) Paṭhamaānandasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, is there one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills four things; and those four things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill seven things; and those seven things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill two things?”

“There is, Ānanda.”

“Sir, what is that one thing?”

“Immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. And the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the seven awakening factors. And the seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, fulfill knowledge and freedom.

And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. Breathing in heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’ … They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

There’s a time when a mendicant is breathing in heavily, and they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’ … They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the physical process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the physical process.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Why is that? Because the breath is a certain aspect of the body, I say. Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

There’s a time when a mendicant practices like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing rapture … bliss … mind …’ … They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the mental process.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Why is that? Because careful application of mind to the in-breaths and out-breaths is a certain aspect of feelings, I say. Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

There’s a time when a mendicant practices like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in gladdening the mind … immersing the mind in samādhi … freeing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out freeing the mind.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Why is that? Because there is no development of immersion due to mindfulness of breathing for someone who is unmindful and lacks awareness, I say. Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

There’s a time when a mendicant practices like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing impermanence … fading away … cessation … letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Having seen with wisdom the giving up of covetousness and displeasure, they watch closely over with equanimity. Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

That’s how immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation.

And how are the four kinds of mindfulness meditation developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the seven awakening factors? Whenever a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body, their mindfulness is established and lucid. At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of mindfulness; they develop it and perfect it.

As they live mindfully in this way they investigate, explore, and inquire into that principle with wisdom. At such a time, a mendicant has activated the awakening factor of investigation of principles; they develop it and perfect it.

As they investigate principles with wisdom in this way their energy is roused up and unflagging. At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of energy; they develop it and perfect it.

When you’re energetic, rapture not of the flesh arises. At such a time, a mendicant has initiated the awakening factor of rapture; they develop it and perfect it.

When the mind is full of rapture, the body and mind become tranquil. At such a time, a mendicant has activated the awakening factor of tranquility; they develop it and perfect it.

When the body is tranquil and one feels bliss, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. At such a time, a mendicant has activated the awakening factor of immersion; they develop it and perfect it.

They closely watch over that mind immersed in samādhi. At such a time, a mendicant has activated the awakening factor of equanimity; they develop it and perfect it.

Whenever a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of feelings … mind … principles, their mindfulness is established and lucid. At such a time, a mendicant has activated the awakening factor of mindfulness; they develop it and perfect it. …

(Tell in full as for the first kind of mindfulness meditation.)

They closely watch over that mind immersed in samādhi. At such a time, a mendicant has activated the awakening factor of equanimity; they develop it and perfect it. That’s how the four kinds of mindfulness meditation are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the seven awakening factors.

And how are the seven awakening factors developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom? It’s when a mendicant develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. That’s how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom.”

SN 54.14 With Ānanda (2nd) Dutiyaānandasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him: “Ānanda, is there one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills four things; and those four things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill seven things; and those seven things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill two things?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“There is, Ānanda.

And what is that one thing? Immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. And the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the seven awakening factors. And the seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, fulfill knowledge and freedom.

And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? …

That’s how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom.”

SN 54.15 Several Mendicants (1st) Paṭhamabhikkhusutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, is there one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills four things; and those four things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill seven things; and those seven things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill two things?”

“There is, mendicants.”

“Sir, what is that one thing?”

“Immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. And the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the seven awakening factors. And the seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, fulfill knowledge and freedom.

And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? …

That’s how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom.”

SN 54.16 Several Mendicants (2nd) Dutiyabhikkhusutta

Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to them:

“Mendicants, is there one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills four things; and those four things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill seven things; and those seven things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill two things?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. …”

“There is, mendicants.

And what is that one thing? Immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, fulfills the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. And the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the seven awakening factors. And the seven awakening factors, when developed and cultivated, fulfill knowledge and freedom.

And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so as to fulfill the four kinds of mindfulness meditation? It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. …

That’s how the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated so as to fulfill knowledge and freedom.”

SN 54.17 Giving Up the Fetters Saṁyojanappahānasutta

“Mendicants, when immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it leads to giving up the fetters …”

SN 54.18 Uprooting the Tendencies Anusayasamugghātasutta

“Mendicants, when immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it leads to uprooting the underlying tendencies …”

SN 54.19 Completely Understanding the Course of Time Addhānapariññāsutta

“Mendicants, when immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it leads to completely understanding the course of time …”

SN 54.20 The Ending of Defilements Āsavakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, when immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it leads to the ending of defilements.” …[2564] “And how is immersion due to mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so as to lead to giving up the fetters,[2565] uprooting the underlying tendencies, completely understanding the course of time, and ending the defilements?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and establishes mindfulness in front of them. …

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

That’s how immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated so as to lead to giving up the fetters, uprooting the underlying tendencies, completely understanding the course of time, and ending the defilements.”

The Linked Discourses on Mindfulness of Breathing, the tenth section.

The Chapter on One Thing

SN 54.1 One Thing Ekadhammasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, when one thing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. What one thing? Mindfulness of breathing.

And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated to be very fruitful and beneficial?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present.[2521]

Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out.[2522]

Breathing in heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’[2523] Breathing in lightly they know: ‘I’m breathing in lightly.’ Breathing out lightly they know: ‘I’m breathing out lightly.’[2524] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the whole body.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the whole body.’[2525] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the physical process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the physical process.’[2526]

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing rapture.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing rapture.’[2527] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing bliss.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing bliss.’[2528] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the mental process.’[2529] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the mental process.’[2530]

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the mind.’[2531] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in gladdening the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out gladdening the mind.’[2532] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in immersing the mind in samādhi.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out immersing the mind in samādhi.’[2533] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in freeing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out freeing the mind.’[2534] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing impermanence.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing impermanence.’[2535]

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing fading away.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing fading away.’[2536] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing cessation.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing cessation.’[2537] They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’[2538]

Mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated in this way, is very fruitful and beneficial.”

SN 54.2 Awakening Factors Bojjhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated to be very fruitful and beneficial? It’s when a mendicant develops mindfulness of breathing together with the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. Mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated in this way, is very fruitful and beneficial.”

SN 54.3 Plain Version Suddhikasutta

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated to be very fruitful and beneficial?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present.

Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. …

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

Mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated in this way, is very fruitful and beneficial.”

SN 54.4 Fruits (1st) Paṭhamaphalasutta

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated to be very fruitful and beneficial?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present.

Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. …

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

Mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated in this way, is very fruitful and beneficial. When mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated in this way you can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

SN 54.5 Fruits (2nd) Dutiyaphalasutta

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. And how is mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated to be very fruitful and beneficial?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present.

Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. …

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

Mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated in this way, is very fruitful and beneficial.

When mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated in this way you can expect seven fruits and benefits. What seven? You attain enlightenment early on in this very life. If not, you attain enlightenment at the time of death. If not, with the ending of the five lower fetters you’re extinguished in between one life and the next … you’re extinguished upon landing … you’re extinguished without extra effort … you’re extinguished with extra effort … you head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm … When mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated in this way you can expect these seven fruits and benefits.”

SN 54.6 With Ariṭṭha Ariṭṭhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

There the Buddha … said:

“Mendicants, do you develop mindfulness of breathing?” When he said this, Venerable Ariṭṭha said to him:[2539]

“Sir, I develop mindfulness of breathing.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“Sir, I’ve given up desire for sensual pleasures of the past. I’m rid of desire for sensual pleasures of the future. And I have eliminated perception of aversion regarding phenomena internally and externally.[2540] Just mindful, I will breathe in. Mindful, I will breathe out.[2541] That’s how I develop mindfulness of breathing.”

“That is mindfulness of breathing, Ariṭṭha; I don’t deny it. But as to how mindfulness of breathing is fulfilled in detail, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Ariṭṭha replied. The Buddha said this:

“And how is mindfulness of breathing fulfilled in detail? It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. Breathing in heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’ … They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’ This is how mindfulness of breathing is fulfilled in detail.”

SN 54.7 About Mahākappina Mahākappinasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Now at that time Venerable Mahākappina was sitting not far from the Buddha, cross-legged, his body set straight, and mindfulness brought to the present. The Buddha saw him, and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, do you see any perturbation or trembling in that mendicant’s body?”

“Sir, whenever we see that mendicant meditating—whether in the middle of the Saṅgha or alone in private—we never see any perturbation or trembling in his body.”

“Mendicants, when an immersion has been developed and cultivated there’s no perturbation or trembling of the body or mind. That mendicant gets such immersion when he wants, without trouble or difficulty. And what is that immersion?

When immersion due to mindfulness of breathing has been developed and cultivated there’s no perturbation or trembling of the body or mind.[2542] And how is immersion due to mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated in such a way?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. … They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

That’s how immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated so that there’s no perturbation or trembling of the body or mind.”

SN 54.8 The Simile of the Lamp Padīpopamasutta

“Mendicants, when immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. How so?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. Breathing in heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’ … They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’ That’s how immersion due to mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated, is very fruitful and beneficial.

Before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I too usually practiced this kind of meditation. And while I was usually practicing this kind of meditation neither my body nor my eyes became fatigued.[2543] And my mind was freed from defilements by not grasping.

Now, a mendicant might wish:[2544] ‘May neither my body nor my eyes became fatigued. And may my mind be freed from the defilements by not grasping.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘May I give up memories and thoughts tied to domestic life.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive and the repulsive.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘May I meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive and the unrepulsive.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘May I meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘Quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, may I enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, may I enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘With the fading away of rapture, may I enter and remain in the third absorption, where I will meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, “Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.”’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘With the giving up of pleasure and pain, and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, may I enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘Going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that “space is infinite”, may I enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that “consciousness is infinite”, may I enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that “there is nothing at all”, may I enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘Going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, may I enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

Now, a mendicant might wish: ‘Going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, may I enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling.’ So let them closely focus on this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing.

When immersion due to mindfulness of breathing has been developed and cultivated in this way, if they feel a pleasant feeling, they understand that it’s impermanent, that they’re not attached to it, and that they don’t take pleasure in it. If they feel a painful feeling, they understand that it’s impermanent, that they’re not attached to it, and that they don’t take pleasure in it. If they feel a neutral feeling, they understand that it’s impermanent, that they’re not attached to it, and that they don’t take pleasure in it.

If they feel a pleasant feeling, they feel it detached. If they feel a painful feeling, they feel it detached. If they feel a neutral feeling, they feel it detached. Feeling the end of the body draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of the body draw close.’ Feeling the end of life draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of life draw close.’ They understand: ‘When my body breaks up and my life has come to an end, everything that’s felt, since I no longer take pleasure in it, will become cool right here.’

Suppose an oil lamp depended on oil and a wick to burn. As the oil and the wick are used up, it would be extinguished due to not being fed. In the same way, feeling the end of the body draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of the body draw close.’ Feeling the end of life draw close, they understand: ‘I feel the end of life draw close.’ They understand: ‘When my body breaks up and my life has come to an end, everything that’s felt, since I no longer take pleasure in it, will become cool right here.’”

SN 54.9 At Vesālī Vesālīsutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.[2545] Now at that time the Buddha spoke in many ways to the mendicants about the meditation on ugliness. He praised the meditation on ugliness and its development.[2546]

Then the Buddha said to the mendicants, “Mendicants, I wish to go on retreat for a fortnight.[2547] No-one should approach me, except the one who brings my almsfood.”

“Yes, sir,” replied those mendicants. And no-one approached him, except the one who brought the almsfood.

Then those mendicants thought, “The Buddha spoke in many ways about the meditation on ugliness. He praised the meditation on ugliness and its development.” They committed themselves to developing the many different facets of the meditation on ugliness. Becoming horrified, repelled, and disgusted with this body, they looked for a suicide weapon.[2548] Each day ten, twenty, or thirty mendicants committed suicide.[2549]

Then after a fortnight had passed, the Buddha came out of retreat and addressed Ānanda, “Ānanda, why does the mendicant Saṅgha seem so diminished?”

Ānanda told the Buddha all that had happened, and said, “Sir, please explain another way the mendicant Saṅgha might be settled in enlightenment.”

“Well then, Ānanda, gather all the mendicants staying in the vicinity of Vesālī together in the assembly hall.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Ānanda. He did what the Buddha asked, went up to him, and said, “Sir, the mendicant Saṅgha has assembled. Please, sir, come at your convenience.”

Then the Buddha went to the assembly hall, sat down on the seat spread out, and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, when this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s peaceful and sublime, a delectable and blissful meditation. And it disperses and settles unskillful qualities on the spot whenever they arise.

In the last month of summer, when the dust and dirt is stirred up, a large storm out of season disperses and settles it on the spot.

In the same way, when this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated it’s peaceful and sublime, a delectable and blissful meditation. And it disperses and settles unskillful qualities on the spot whenever they arise. And how is it so developed and cultivated?

It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present.

Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. …

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’

That’s how this immersion due to mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated so that it’s peaceful and sublime, a delectable and blissful meditation. And it disperses and settles unskillful qualities on the spot whenever they arise.”

SN 54.10 With Kimbila Kimilasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Kimbilā in the Freshwater Mangrove Wood. Then the Buddha said to Venerable Kimbila,[2550] “Kimbila, how is immersion due to mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so that it is very fruitful and beneficial?”

When he said this, Kimbila kept silent.

For a second time …

And for a third time, the Buddha said to him, “How is immersion due to mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so that it is very fruitful and beneficial?” And a second time and a third time Kimbila kept silent.

When he said this, Venerable Ānanda said to the Buddha, “Now is the time, Blessed One! Now is the time, Holy One! Let the Buddha speak on immersion due to mindfulness of breathing. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, Ānanda, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied. The Buddha said this:

“Ānanda, how is immersion due to mindfulness of breathing developed and cultivated so that it is very fruitful and beneficial? It’s when a mendicant—gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut—sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present.

Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. …

They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’ That’s how immersion due to mindfulness of breathing, when developed and cultivated, is very fruitful and beneficial.

There’s a time when a mendicant is breathing in heavily, and they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’[2551] Breathing in lightly they know: ‘I’m breathing in lightly.’ Breathing out lightly they know: ‘I’m breathing out lightly.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the whole body.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the whole body.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the physical process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the physical process.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.[2552] Why is that? Because the breath is a certain aspect of the body, I say.[2553] Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

There’s a time when a mendicant practices like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing rapture.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing rapture.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing bliss.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing bliss.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the mental process.’[2554] At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Why is that? Because careful application of mind to the in-breaths and out-breaths is a certain aspect of feelings, I say.[2555] Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of feelings—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

There’s a time when a mendicant practices like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in gladdening the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out gladdening the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in immersing the mind in samādhi.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out immersing the mind in samādhi.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in freeing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out freeing the mind.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Why is that? Because there is no development of immersion due to mindfulness of breathing for someone who is unmindful and lacks awareness, I say.[2556] Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the mind—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

There’s a time when a mendicant practices like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing impermanence.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing impermanence.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing fading away.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing fading away.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing cessation.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing cessation.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’ At such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. Having seen with wisdom the giving up of covetousness and displeasure, they watch closely over with equanimity.[2557] Therefore, at such a time a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.

Suppose there was a large heap of sand at the crossroads. And a cart or chariot were to come by from the east, west, north, or south and destroy that heap of sand.

In the same way, when a mendicant is meditating by observing an aspect of the body, feelings, mind, or principles, they destroy bad, unskillful qualities.”

The Chapter on Overflowing Merit

SN 55.31 Overflowing Merit (1st) Paṭhamapuññābhisandasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness. What four? Firstly, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … This is the first kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching … This is the second kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Saṅgha … This is the third kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness.

Furthermore, a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. This is the fourth kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. These are the four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness.”

SN 55.32 Overflowing Merit (2nd) Dutiyapuññābhisandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. This is the fourth kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. These are the four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness.”

SN 55.33 Overflowing Merit (3rd) Tatiyapuññābhisandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is the fourth kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. These are the four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness.”

SN 55.34 Footprints of the Gods (1st) Paṭhamadevapadasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, these four footprints of the gods are in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings.[2614]

What four? Firstly, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … This is the first footprint of the gods in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. This is the fourth footprint of the gods in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings. These four footprints of the gods are in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings.”

SN 55.35 Footprints of the Gods (2nd) Dutiyadevapadasutta

“Mendicants, these four footprints of the gods are in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings.

What four? Firstly, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ Then they reflect: ‘What now is the footprint of the gods?’ They understand: ‘I hear that these days the gods consider non-harming to be supreme.[2615] But I don’t hurt any creature firm or frail. I definitely live in possession of a footprint of the gods.’ This is the first footprint of the gods in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. Then they reflect: ‘What now is the footprint of the gods?’ They understand: ‘I hear that these days the gods consider non-harming to be supreme. But I don’t hurt any creature firm or frail. I definitely live in possession of a footprint of the gods.’ This is the fourth footprint of the gods in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings. These four footprints of the gods are in order to purify unpurified beings and cleanse unclean beings.”

SN 55.36 In Common With the Gods Devasabhāgatasutta

“Mendicants, when someone possesses four things the gods are pleased and speak of what they have in common. What four? Firstly, a noble disciple possesses experiential confidence in the Buddha … There are deities who possess experiential confidence in the Buddha who passed away from here and were reborn there. They think: ‘Possessing such experiential confidence in the Buddha, we passed away from there and were reborn here. That noble disciple possesses the same kind of experiential confidence in the Buddha, so they will come into the presence of the gods.’[2616]

Furthermore, a noble disciple possesses experiential confidence in the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they possess the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. There are deities who possess the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones who passed away from here and were reborn there. They think: ‘Possessing such ethical conduct loved by the noble ones, we passed away from there and were reborn here. That noble disciple possesses the same kind of ethical conduct loved by the noble ones, so they will come into the presence of the gods.’ When someone possesses four things the gods are pleased and speak of what they have in common.”

SN 55.37 With Mahānāma Mahānāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, how is a lay follower defined?”

“Mahānāma, when you’ve gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, you’re considered to be a lay follower.”

“But how is an ethical lay follower defined?”

“When a lay follower doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, they’re considered to be an ethical lay follower.”[2617]

“But how is a faithful lay follower defined?”

“It’s when a lay follower has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ Then they’re considered to be a faithful lay follower.”

“But how is a generous lay follower defined?”

“It’s when a lay follower lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. Then they’re considered to be a generous lay follower.”

“But how is a wise lay follower defined?”

“It’s when a lay follower is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. Then they’re considered to be a wise lay follower.”

SN 55.38 Rain Vassasutta

“Mendicants, suppose the heavens rain heavily on a mountain top, and the water flows downhill to fill the hollows, crevices, and creeks. As they become full, they fill up the pools. The pools fill up the lakes, the lakes fill up the streams, and the streams fill up the rivers. And as the rivers become full, they fill up the ocean.[2618] In the same way, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and the ethics loved by the noble ones. These things flow onwards; and, after crossing to the far shore, they lead to the ending of defilements.”

SN 55.39 With Kāḷigodhā Kāḷigodhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of Kāḷigodhā the Sakyan lady, where he sat down on the seat spread out.[2619] Then Kāḷigodhā went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Godhā, a female noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. What four? It’s when a female noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And she lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. A female noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

“Sir, these four factors of stream-entry that were taught by the Buddha are found in me, and I exhibit them. For I have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And I share without reservation all the gifts available to give in our family with those who are ethical and of good character.”

“You’re fortunate, Godhā, so very fortunate, You have declared the fruit of stream-entry.”

SN 55.40 Nandiya the Sakyan Nandiyasakkasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Nandiya the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, if a noble disciple were to totally and utterly lack the four factors of stream-entry, would they live negligently?”

“Nandiya, someone who totally and utterly lacks these four factors of stream-entry stands outside in the faction of ordinary persons, I say. Neverthless, Nandiya, as to how a noble disciple lives negligently and how they live diligently, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Nandiya replied. The Buddha said this:

“And how does a noble disciple live negligently? Firstly, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … They’re content with that confidence, and don’t make a further effort for solitude by day or retreat by night. When they live negligently, there’s no joy.[2620] When there’s no joy, there’s no rapture. When there’s no rapture, there’s no tranquility. When there’s no tranquility, there’s suffering. When one is suffering, the mind does not become immersed in samādhi. When the mind is not immersed in samādhi, principles do not become clear. Because principles have not become clear, they’re reckoned to live negligently.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. They’re content with that ethical conduct loved by the noble ones, and don’t make a further effort for solitude by day or retreat by night. When they live negligently, there’s no joy. When there’s no joy, there’s no rapture. When there’s no rapture, there’s no tranquility. When there’s no tranquility, there’s suffering. When one is suffering, the mind does not become immersed in samādhi. When the mind is not immersed in samādhi, principles do not become clear. Because principles have not become clear, they’re reckoned to live negligently. That’s how a noble disciple lives negligently.

And how does a noble disciple live diligently? Firstly, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … But they’re not content with that confidence, and make a further effort for solitude by day and retreat by night. When they live diligently, joy springs up. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. When the mind is immersed in samādhi, principles become clear. Because principles have become clear, they’re reckoned to live diligently.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. But they’re not content with that ethical conduct loved by the noble ones, and make a further effort for solitude by day and retreat by night. When they live diligently, joy springs up. Being joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. When the mind is immersed in samādhi, principles become clear. Because principles have become clear, they’re reckoned to live diligently. That’s how a noble disciple lives diligently.”

The Chapter on the Royal Monastery

SN 55.11 A Saṅgha of a Thousand Nuns Sahassabhikkhunisaṁghasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the Royal Monastery.[2593] Then a Saṅgha of a thousand nuns went up to the Buddha, bowed, and stood to one side. The Buddha said to them:[2594]

“Nuns, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 55.12 The Brahmins Brāhmaṇasutta

At Sāvatthī. “Mendicants, the brahmins advocate a practice called ‘get up and go’. They encourage their disciple: ‘Please, my man, rising early you should face east and walk. Do not avoid a pit, a cliff, a stump, thorny ground, a swamp, or a sewer. You should await death in the place that you fall. And when your body breaks up, after death, you’ll be reborn in a good place, a heaven realm.’[2595]

But this practice of the brahmins is a foolish procedure, a stupid procedure. It doesn’t lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, or extinguishment. But in the training of the Noble One I advocate a ‘get up and go’ practice which does lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.

And what is that ‘get up and go’ practice? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. This is that ‘get up and go’ practice which does lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.”

SN 55.13 With the Senior Monk Ānanda Ānandattherasutta

At one time the venerables Ānanda and Sāriputta were staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Sāriputta came out of retreat, went to Venerable Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to him:

“Reverend, how many things do people have to give up and how many do they have to possess in order for the Buddha to declare that they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening?”

“Reverend, people have to give up four things and possess four things in order for the Buddha to declare that they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

What four? They don’t have the distrust in the Buddha that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And they do have the experiential confidence in the Buddha that causes a learned noble disciple to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a good place, a heavenly realm. ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’

They don’t have the distrust in the teaching that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And they do have the experiential confidence in the teaching that causes a learned noble disciple to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a good place, a heavenly realm. ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’

They don’t have the distrust in the Saṅgha that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And they do have the experiential confidence in the Saṅgha that causes a learned noble disciple to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a good place, a heavenly realm. ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, and worthy of veneration with cupped palms.’

They don’t have the unethical conduct that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And they do have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones that causes a learned noble disciple to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a good place, a heavenly realm. Their ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. People have to give up these four things and possess these four things in order for the Buddha to declare that they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 55.14 Fear of the Bad Place Duggatibhayasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things has gone beyond all fear of being reborn in a bad place. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things has gone beyond all fear of being reborn in a bad place.”

SN 55.15 Fear of the Bad Place, the Underworld Duggativinipātabhayasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things has gone beyond all fear of being reborn in a bad place, the underworld. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things has gone beyond all fear of being reborn in a bad place, the underworld.”

SN 55.16 Friends and Colleagues (1st) Paṭhamamittāmaccasutta

“Mendicants, those who you have sympathy for, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the four factors of stream-entry.[2596] What four? Experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. Those who you have sympathy for, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in these four factors of stream-entry.”

SN 55.17 Friends and Colleagues (2nd) Dutiyamittāmaccasutta

“Mendicants, those who you have sympathy for, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the four factors of stream-entry. What four? Experiential confidence in the Buddha …

There might be change in the four principal states—the elements of earth, water, fire, and air—but a noble disciple with experiential confidence in the Buddha would never change. In this context, ‘change’ means that such a noble disciple will be reborn in hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm: this is quite impossible.

Experiential confidence in the teaching …

Experiential confidence in the Saṅgha …

The ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. There might be change in the four principal states—the elements of earth, water, fire, and air—but a noble disciple with the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones would never change. In this context, ‘change’ means that such a noble disciple will be reborn in hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm: this is quite impossible.

Those who you have sympathy for, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in these four factors of stream-entry.”

SN 55.18 A Visit to the Gods (1st) Paṭhamadevacārikasutta

At Sāvatthī. And then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from Jeta’s Grove and reappeared among the gods of the thirty-three. Then several deities of the company of the thirty-three went up to Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, bowed, and stood to one side. Moggallāna said to them:

“Reverends, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha. … It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching. … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“My good fellow Moggallāna, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha … It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching. … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

SN 55.19 A Visit to the Gods (2nd) Dutiyadevacārikasutta

At Sāvatthī.

And then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from Jeta’s Grove and reappeared among the gods of the thirty-three. Then several deities of the company of the thirty-three went up to Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, bowed, and stood to one side. Moggallāna said to them:

“Reverends, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha. … It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, have been reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching. … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, have been reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“My good Moggallāna, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha … It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, have been reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching. … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, have been reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

SN 55.20 A Visit to the Gods (3rd) Tatiyadevacārikasutta

Then the Buddha, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from Jeta’s Grove and reappeared among the gods of the thirty-three. Then several deities of the company of the thirty-three went up to the Buddha, bowed, and stood to one side. The Buddha said to them:

“Reverends, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha. … It’s the reason why some sentient beings are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching. … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

“Good fellow, it’s good to have experiential confidence in the Buddha … It’s the reason why some sentient beings are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. It’s good to have experiential confidence in the teaching. … the Saṅgha … and to have the ethical conduct that’s loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. It’s the reason why some sentient beings are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

The Chapter on Overflowing Merit, With Verses

SN 55.41 Overflowing Merit (1st) Paṭhamaabhisandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. … These are the four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness.

When a noble disciple has these four kinds of overflowing merit and goodness, it’s not easy to count how much merit they have by saying that[2621] this is the extent of their overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of merit.

It’s like trying to count how much water is in the ocean. It’s not easy to say how many gallons, how many hundreds, thousands, hundreds of thousands of gallons there are. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of water.

In the same way, when a noble disciple has these four kinds of overflowing merit and goodness, it’s not easy to count how much merit they have by saying that this is the extent of their overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of merit.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Hosts of people use the rivers,
and though the rivers are many,
all reach the great deep, the boundless ocean,
the cruel sea that’s home to precious gems.

So too, when a person gives food, drink, and clothes;
and they’re a giver of beds, seats, and mats—[2622]
the streams of merit reach that astute person,
as the rivers bring their waters to the sea.”

SN 55.42 Overflowing Merit (2nd) Dutiyaabhisandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. This is the fourth kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. These are the four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness.

When a noble disciple has these four kinds of overflowing merit and goodness, it’s not easy to count how much merit they have by saying that this is the extent of their overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of merit.

There are places where the great rivers—the Ganges, Yamunā, Aciravatī, Sarabhū, and Mahī—join together and converge. It’s not easy to count how much water is in such places by saying how many gallons, how many hundreds, thousands, hundreds of thousands of gallons there are. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of water.

In the same way, when a noble disciple has these four kinds of overflowing merit and goodness, it’s not easy to count how much merit they have by saying that this is the extent of their overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of merit.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Hosts of people use the rivers,
and though the rivers are many,
all reach the great deep, the boundless ocean,
the cruel sea that’s home to precious gems.

So too, when a person gives food, drink, and clothes;
and they’re a giver of beds, seats, and mats—
the streams of merit reach that astute person,
as the rivers bring their waters to the sea.”

SN 55.43 Overflowing Merit (3rd) Tatiyaabhisandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is the fourth kind of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. These are the four kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurture happiness.

When a noble disciple has these four kinds of overflowing merit and goodness, it’s not easy to count how much merit they have by saying that this is the extent of their overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of merit.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“One who desires merit, grounded in the skillful,
develops the path to realize freedom from death.
Once they’ve reached the heart of the teaching, delighting in ending,
they don’t tremble at the approach of the King of Death.”

SN 55.44 Rich (1st) Paṭhamamahaddhanasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things is said to be rich, affluent, and wealthy.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is said to be rich, affluent, and wealthy.”

SN 55.45 Rich (2nd) Dutiyamahaddhanasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things is said to be rich, affluent, wealthy, and famous.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is said to be rich, affluent, wealthy, and famous.”

SN 55.46 Plain Version Suddhakasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 55.47 With Nandiya Nandiyasutta

At Kapilavatthu. Seated to one side, the Buddha said to Nandiya the Sakyan:

“Nandiya, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 55.48 With Bhaddiya Bhaddiyasutta

At Kapilavatthu. Seated to one side, the Buddha said to Bhaddiya the Sakyan:[2623]

“Bhaddiya, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer …”

SN 55.49 With Mahānāma Mahānāmasutta

At Kapilavatthu. Seated to one side, the Buddha said to Mahānāma the Sakyan:

“Mahānāma, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer …”

SN 55.50 Factors Aṅgasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four factors for stream-entry. What four? Associating with true persons, listening to the true teaching, rational application of mind, and practicing in line with the teaching. These are the four factors for stream-entry.”

The Chapter on a Wise Person

SN 55.51 With Verses Sagāthakasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Whoever has faith in the Realized One,[2624]
unwavering and well grounded;
whose ethical conduct is good,
praised and loved by the noble ones;

who has confidence in the Saṅgha,
and correct view:
they’re said to be prosperous,
their life is not in vain.

So let the wise devote themselves
to faith, ethical behaviour,
confidence, and insight into the teaching,
remembering the instructions of the Buddhas.”

SN 55.52 One Who Completed the Rains Vassaṁvutthasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Now at that time a certain mendicant who had completed the rainy season residence in Sāvatthī arrived at Kapilavatthu on some business. The Sakyans of Kapilavatthu heard about this.

They went to that mendicant, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, we hope that the Buddha is healthy and strong.”

“He is, respectable sirs.”

“And we hope that Sāriputta and Moggallāna are healthy and strong.”

“They are.”

“And we hope that the mendicant Saṅgha is healthy and strong.”

“It is.”

“But sir, during this rains residence did you hear and learn anything in the presence of the Buddha?”

“Respectable sirs, I heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘There are fewer mendicants who realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. There are more mendicants who, having ended the five lower fetters, are reborn spontaneously, and will be extinguished there, not liable to return from that world.’

In addition, I heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘There are fewer mendicants who, having ended the five lower fetters, are reborn spontaneously, and will be extinguished there, not liable to return from that world. There are more mendicants who, with the ending of three fetters, and the weakening of greed, hate, and delusion, are once-returners, who come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering.’

In addition, I heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘There are fewer mendicants who, with the ending of three fetters, and the weakening of greed, hate, and delusion, are once-returners, who come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering. There are more mendicants who, with the ending of three fetters are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.’”

SN 55.53 With Dhammadinna Dhammadinnasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana. Then the lay follower Dhammadinna, together with five hundred lay followers, went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:[2625]

“May the Buddha please advise and instruct us. It will be for our lasting welfare and happiness.”

“So, Dhammadinna, you should all train like this: ‘From time to time we will undertake and dwell upon the discourses spoken by the Realized One that are deep, profound, transcendent, dealing with emptiness.’[2626] That’s how you should train yourselves.”

“Sir, we live at home with our children, using sandalwood imported from Kāsi, wearing garlands, fragrance, and makeup, and accepting gold and currency. It’s not easy for us to undertake and dwell from time to time upon the discourses spoken by the Realized One that are deep, profound, transcendent, dealing with emptiness.[2627] Since we are established in the five training rules, please teach us further.”

“So, Dhammadinna, you should all train like this: ‘We will have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And we will have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion.’ That’s how you should train yourselves.”

“Sir, these four factors of stream-entry that were taught by the Buddha are found in us, and we embody them. For we have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And we have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion.”

“You’re all fortunate, Dhammadinna, so very fortunate! You’ve all declared the fruit of stream-entry.”

SN 55.54 Sick Gilānasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery.

At that time several mendicants were making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering.

Mahānāma the Sakyan heard about this. Then he went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him that he had heard that the Buddha was leaving. He added, “Sir, I haven’t heard and learned it in the presence of the Buddha how a wise lay follower should advise another wise lay follower who is sick, suffering, gravely ill.”

“Mahānāma, a wise lay follower should put at ease another wise lay follower who is sick, suffering, gravely ill with four consolations. ‘Be at ease, sir.[2628] You have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And you have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion.’

When a wise lay follower has put at ease another wise lay follower who is sick, suffering, gravely ill with these four consolations, they should say: ‘Are you concerned for your mother and father?’ If they reply, ‘I am,’ they should say: ‘But sir, it’s your nature to die. Whether or not you are concerned for your mother and father, you will die anyway. It would be good to give up concern for your mother and father.’

If they reply, ‘I have given up concern for my mother and father,’ they should say: ‘But are you concerned for your partners and children?’ If they reply, ‘I am,’ they should say: ‘But sir, it’s your nature to die. Whether or not you are concerned for your partners and children, you will die anyway. It would be good to give up concern for your partners and children.’

If they reply, ‘I have given up concern for my partners and children,’ they should say: ‘But are you concerned for the five kinds of human sensual stimulation?’ If they reply, ‘I am,’ they should say: ‘Respectable sir, heavenly sensual pleasures are better than human sensual pleasures. It would be good to turn your mind away from human sensual pleasures and focus it on the gods of the four great kings.’[2629]

If they reply, ‘I have done so,’ they should say: ‘Respectable sir, the gods of the thirty-three are better than the gods of the four great kings …

Respectable sir, the gods of Yama … the joyful gods … the gods who love to create … the gods who control what is created by others … the gods of the realm of divinity are better than the gods who control what is created by others. It would be good to turn your mind away from the gods who control what is created by others and focus it on the gods of the realm of divinity.’ If they reply, ‘I have done so,’ they should say: ‘Respectable sir, the realm of divinity is impermanent, not lasting, and included within substantial reality. It would be good to turn your mind away from the realm of divinity and apply it to the cessation of substantial reality.’[2630]

If they reply, ‘I have done so,’ then there is no difference between a lay follower whose mind is freed in this way and a mendicant whose mind is freed from defilements; that is,[2631] between the freedom of one and the other.”

SN 55.55 The Fruit of Stream-Entry Sotāpattiphalasutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of stream-entry. What four? Associating with true persons, listening to the true teaching, rational application of mind, and practicing in line with the teaching. When these four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of stream-entry.”

SN 55.56 The Fruit of Once-Return Sakadāgāmiphalasutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of once-return. …”

SN 55.57 The Fruit of Non-Return Anāgāmiphalasutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of non-return. …”

SN 55.58 The Fruit of Perfection Arahattaphalasutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the realization of the fruit of perfection. …”

SN 55.59 The Getting of Wisdom Paññāpaṭilābhasutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the getting of wisdom. …”

SN 55.60 The Growth of Wisdom Paññāvuddhisutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the growth of wisdom. …”

SN 55.61 The Increase of Wisdom Paññāvepullasutta

“Mendicants, when four things are developed and cultivated they lead to the increase of wisdom. …”

The Chapter with Sarakāni

SN 55.21 With Mahānāma (1st) Paṭhamamahānāmasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, this Kapilavatthu is successful and prosperous, populous and full of people, with cramped cul-de-sacs.[2597] In the late afternoon, after paying homage to the Buddha or an esteemed mendicant, I enter Kapilavatthu. I encounter a stray elephant, horse, chariot, cart, or person. At that time I lose mindfulness regarding the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. I think: ‘If I were to die at this time, where would I be reborn in my next life?’”[2598]

“Do not fear, Mahānāma, do not fear! Your death will not be a bad one; your passing will not be a bad one. Take someone whose mind has for a long time been imbued with faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. Their body is formed, made up of the four principal states, produced by mother and father, built up from rice and porridge, liable to impermanence, to wearing away and erosion, to breaking up and destruction. Right here the crows, vultures, hawks, hounds, jackals, and many kinds of little creatures devour it. But their mind rises up, headed for a higher place.

Suppose a person was to sink a pot of ghee or oil into a deep lake and break it open. Its shards and chips would sink down, while the ghee or oil in it would rise up, headed for a higher place.[2599]

In the same way, take someone whose mind has for a long time been imbued with faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. Their body is formed, made up of the four principal states, produced by mother and father, built up from rice and porridge, liable to impermanence, to wearing away and erosion, to breaking up and destruction. Right here the crows, vultures, hawks, hounds, jackals, and many kinds of little creatures devour it. But their mind rises up, headed for a higher place.[2600]

Your mind, Mahānāma, has for a long time been imbued with faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. Do not fear, Mahānāma, do not fear! Your death will not be a bad one; your passing will not be a bad one.”

SN 55.22 With Mahānāma (2nd) Dutiyamahānāmasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, this Kapilavatthu is successful and prosperous, populous and full of people, with cramped cul-de-sacs. In the late afternoon, after paying homage to the Buddha or an esteemed mendicant, I enter Kapilavatthu. I encounter a stray elephant, horse, chariot, cart, or person. At that time I lose mindfulness regarding the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. I think: ‘If I were to die at this time, where would I be reborn in my next life?’”

“Do not fear, Mahānāma, do not fear! Your death will not be a bad one; your passing will not be a bad one. A noble disciple who has four things slants, slopes, and inclines toward extinguishment. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion.

Suppose there was a tree that slants, slopes, and inclines to the east. If it was cut off at the root where would it fall?”

“Sir, it would fall in the direction that it slants, slopes, and inclines.”

“In the same way, a noble disciple who has four things slants, slopes, and inclines toward extinguishment.”

SN 55.23 With Godhā the Sakyan Godhasakkasutta

At Kapilavatthu. Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to Godhā the Sakyan, and said to her,[2601] “Godhā, how many things must an individual have for you to recognize them as a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening?”

“Mahānāma, an individual must have three things for me to recognize them as a stream-enterer. What three? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … and the Saṅgha … When an individual has these three things I recognize them as a stream-enterer.

But Mahānāma, how many things must an individual have for you to recognize them as a stream-enterer?”

“Godhā, an individual must have four things for me to recognize them as a stream-enterer.[2602] What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. When an individual has these four things I recognize them as a stream-enterer.”

“Hold on, Mahānāma, hold on! Only the Buddha would know whether or not they have these things.”

“Come, Godhā, let’s go to the Buddha and inform him about this.”

Then Mahānāma and Godhā went to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. Mahānāma told the Buddha all that had happened, and then said:

“Sir, some instigation of a legal proceeding might come up. The Buddha might take one side, and the Saṅgha of monks the other.[2603] I’d side with the Buddha. May the Buddha remember me as having such confidence. Some instigation of a legal proceeding might come up. The Buddha might take one side, and the Saṅgha of monks and the Saṅgha of nuns the other. … The Buddha might take one side, and the Saṅgha of monks and the Saṅgha of nuns and the laymen the other. … The Buddha might take one side, and the Saṅgha of monks and the Saṅgha of nuns and the laymen and the laywomen the other. … The Buddha might take one side, and the Saṅgha of monks and the Saṅgha of nuns and the laymen and the laywomen and the world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, gods and humans—the other. I’d side with the Buddha. May the Buddha remember me as having such confidence.”

“Godhā, what do you have to say to Mahānāma when he speaks like this?”

“Sir, I have nothing to say to Mahānāma when he speaks like this, except what is good and wholesome.”

SN 55.24 About Sarakāni (1st) Paṭhamasaraṇānisakkasutta

At Kapilavatthu.

Now at that time Sarakāni the Sakyan had passed away.[2604] The Buddha declared that he was a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

At that, several Sakyans came together complaining, grumbling, and objecting, “Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing! Who can’t become a stream-enterer these days? For the Buddha even declared Sarakāni to be a stream-enterer after he passed away. Sarakāni was too weak for the training; he used to drink liquor.”[2605]

Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened. The Buddha said:

“Mahānāma, when a lay follower has for a long time gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, how could they go to the underworld? And if anyone should rightly be said to have for a long time gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, it’s Sarakāni the Sakyan. Sarakāni the Sakyan has for a long time gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. How could he go to the underworld?

Take a certain individual who has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They have laughing wisdom and swift wisdom, and are endowed with freedom. They’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This individual is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They have laughing wisdom and swift wisdom, but are not endowed with freedom. With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This individual, too, is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … But they don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. With the ending of three fetters, and the weakening of greed, hate, and delusion, they’re a once-returner. They come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering. This individual, too, is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … But they don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. With the ending of three fetters they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. This individual, too, is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who doesn’t have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. Still, they have these qualities: the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And they accept the teachings proclaimed by the Realized One after deliberating them with a degree of wisdom. This individual, too, doesn’t go to hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They don’t go to places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who doesn’t have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. Still, they have these qualities: the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And they have a degree of faith and fondness for the Buddha.[2606] This individual, too, doesn’t go to hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They don’t go to places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

If these great sal trees could understand what was well said and poorly said, I’d declare them to be stream-enterers. Why can’t this apply to Sarakāni? Mahānāma, Sarakāni the Sakyan undertook the training at the time of his death.”[2607]

SN 55.25 About Sarakāni the Sakyan (2nd) Dutiyasaraṇānisakkasutta

At Kapilavatthu.

Now at that time Sarakāni the Sakyan had passed away. The Buddha declared that he was a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

At that, several Sakyans came together complaining, grumbling, and objecting, “Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing! Who can’t become a stream-enterer these days? For the Buddha even declared Sarakāni to be a stream-enterer after he passed away. Sarakāni didn’t fulfill the training.”[2608]

Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened. The Buddha said:

“Mahānāma, when a lay follower has for a long time gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, how could they go to the underworld? And if anyone should rightly be said to have for a long time gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, it’s Sarakāni the Sakyan. Sarakāni the Sakyan has for a long time gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha.

Take a certain individual who is sure and devoted to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They have laughing wisdom and swift wisdom, and are endowed with freedom. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This individual is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who is sure and devoted to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They have laughing wisdom and swift wisdom, but are not endowed with freedom. With the ending of the five lower fetters, they’re extinguished between one life and the next … they’re extinguished upon landing … they’re extinguished without extra effort … they’re extinguished with extra effort … they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. This individual, too, is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who is sure and devoted to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … But they don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. With the ending of three fetters, and the weakening of greed, hate, and delusion, they’re a once-returner. They come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering. This individual, too, is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who is sure and devoted to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … But they don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. With the ending of three fetters they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. This individual, too, is exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who isn’t sure or devoted to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. Still, they have these qualities: the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And they accept the teachings proclaimed by the Realized One after deliberating them with a degree of wisdom. This individual, too, doesn’t go to hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They don’t go to places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Take another individual who isn’t sure or devoted to the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They don’t have laughing wisdom or swift wisdom, nor are they endowed with freedom. Still, they have these qualities: the faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And they have a degree of faith and love for the Buddha. This individual, too, doesn’t go to hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They don’t go to places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Suppose there was a barren field, a barren ground, with uncleared stumps. And you had seeds that were broken, spoiled, weather-damaged, infertile, and ill kept. And the heavens didn’t provide enough rain. Would those seeds grow, increase, and mature?”

“No, sir.”

“In the same way, take a teaching that’s badly explained and badly propounded, not emancipating, not leading to peace, proclaimed by someone who is not a fully awakened Buddha. This is what I call a barren field. A disciple remains in such a teaching, practicing in line with that teaching, practicing it properly, living in line with that teaching. This is what I call a bad seed.

Suppose there was a fertile field, a fertile ground, well-cleared of stumps. And you had seeds that were intact, unspoiled, not weather-damaged, fertile, and well-kept. And there’s plenty of rainfall. Would those seeds grow, increase, and mature?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, take a teaching that’s well explained and well propounded, emancipating, leading to peace, proclaimed by someone who is a fully awakened Buddha. This is what I call a fertile field. A disciple remains in such a teaching, practicing in line with that teaching, practicing it properly, living in line with that teaching. This is what I call a good seed. Why can’t this apply to Sarakāni? Mahānāma, Sarakāni the Sakyan fulfilled the training at the time of his death.”

SN 55.26 With Anāthapiṇḍika (1st) Paṭhamaanāthapiṇḍikasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Now at that time the householder Anāthapiṇḍika was sick, suffering, gravely ill.[2609] Then he addressed a man, “Please, my man, go to Venerable Sāriputta, and in my name bow with your head to his feet. Say to him: ‘Sir, the householder Anāthapiṇḍika is sick, suffering, gravely ill. He bows with his head to your feet.’ And then say: ‘Sir, please visit him at his home out of sympathy.’”

“Yes, sir,” that man replied. He did as Anāthapiṇḍika asked. Sāriputta consented with silence.

Then Venerable Sāriputta robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went with Venerable Ānanda as his second monk to Anāthapiṇḍika’s home. He sat down on the seat spread out and said to Anāthapiṇḍika, “I hope you’re keeping well, householder; I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”

“Householder, you don’t have the distrust in the Buddha that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And you have experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ Seeing in yourself that experiential confidence in the Buddha, that pain may die down on the spot.

You don’t have the distrust in the teaching that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And you have experiential confidence in the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ Seeing in yourself that experiential confidence in the teaching, that pain may die down on the spot.

You don’t have the distrust in the Saṅgha that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. And you have experiential confidence in the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, and worthy of veneration with cupped palms. It is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ Seeing in yourself that experiential confidence in the Saṅgha, that pain may die down on the spot.

You don’t have the unethical conduct that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. Your ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. Seeing in yourself that ethical conduct loved by the noble ones, that pain may die down on the spot.

You don’t have the wrong view that causes an unlearned ordinary person to be reborn—when their body breaks up, after death—in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. You have right view. Seeing in yourself that right view, that pain may die down on the spot.

You don’t have the wrong purpose …

wrong speech …

wrong action …

wrong livelihood …

wrong effort …

wrong mindfulness …

wrong immersion …

wrong knowledge …

wrong freedom … You have right freedom. Seeing in yourself that right freedom, that pain may die down on the spot.”[2610]

And then Anāthapiṇḍika’s pain died down on the spot. Then he served Sāriputta and Ānanda from his own dish. When Sāriputta had eaten and washed his hand and bowl, Anāthapiṇḍika took a low seat and sat to one side. Venerable Sāriputta expressed his appreciation to him with these verses.

“Whoever has faith in the Realized One,
unwavering and well grounded;
whose ethical conduct is good,
praised and loved by the noble ones;

who has confidence in the Saṅgha,
and correct view:
they’re said to be prosperous,
their life is not in vain.

So let the wise devote themselves
to faith, ethical behaviour,
confidence, and insight into the teaching,
remembering the instructions of the Buddhas.”

After expressing his appreciation to Anāthapiṇḍika with these verses, Sāriputta rose from his seat and left.

Then Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “So, Ānanda, where are you coming from in the middle of the day?”

“Sir, Venerable Sāriputta advised the householder Anāthapiṇḍika in this way and that.”

“Sāriputta is astute, Ānanda. He has great wisdom, since he can analyze the four factors of stream-entry in ten respects.”

SN 55.27 With Anāthapiṇḍika (2nd) Dutiyaanāthapiṇḍikasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Now at that time the householder Anāthapiṇḍika was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then he addressed a man, “Please, my man, go to Venerable Ānanda, and in my name bow with your head to his feet. Say to him: ‘Sir, the householder Anāthapiṇḍika is sick, suffering, gravely ill. He bows with his head to your feet.’ And then say: ‘Sir, please visit him at his home out of sympathy.’”

“Yes, sir,” that man replied. He did as Anāthapiṇḍika asked. Ānanda consented with silence.

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the householder Anāthapiṇḍika. He sat down on the seat spread out and said to Anāthapiṇḍika, “I hope you’re keeping well, householder, I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”

“Householder, when an unlearned ordinary person has four things, they’re frightened and terrified, and fear what awaits them after death. What four? Firstly, an unlearned ordinary person distrusts the Buddha. Seeing in themselves that distrust of the Buddha, they’re frightened and terrified, and fear what awaits them after death.

Furthermore, an unlearned ordinary person distrusts the teaching …

Furthermore, an unlearned ordinary person distrusts the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, an unlearned ordinary person has unethical conduct. Seeing in themselves that unethical conduct, they’re frightened and terrified, and fear what awaits them after death. When an unlearned ordinary person has these four things, they’re frightened and terrified, and fear what awaits them after death.

When a learned noble disciple has four things, they’re not frightened or terrified, and don’t fear what awaits them after death. What four? Firstly, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … Seeing in themselves that experiential confidence in the Buddha, they’re not frightened or terrified, and don’t fear what awaits them after death.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching …

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Saṅgha …

Furthermore, a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. Seeing in themselves that ethical conduct loved by the noble ones, they’re not frightened or terrified, and don’t fear what awaits them after death.

When a learned noble disciple has these four things, they’re not frightened or terrified, and don’t fear what awaits them after death.”

“Honorable Ānanda, I am not afraid. What have I to fear? For I have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And of the training rules appropriate for laypeople taught by the Buddha, I don’t see any that I have broken.”

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate! You have declared the fruit of stream-entry.”

SN 55.28 Fears and Enmities (1st) Paṭhamabhayaverūpasantasutta

At Sāvatthī.

Seated to one side, the Buddha said to the householder Anāthapiṇḍika:

“Householder, when a noble disciple has quelled five fears and enmities, possesses the four factors of stream-entry, and has clearly seen and penetrated the noble system with wisdom, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

What are the five fears and enmities they have quelled? Anyone who kills living creatures brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from killing living creatures. Anyone who steals … Anyone who commits sexual misconduct … Anyone who lies … Anyone who consumes beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants. These are the five fears and enmities they have quelled.

What are the four factors of stream-entry that they possess? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. These are the four factors of stream-entry that they possess.

And what is the noble system that they have clearly seen and penetrated with wisdom?[2611] A noble disciple rationally applies the mind to dependent origination itself: ‘So, when this exists, this comes to be; due to the arising of this, this arises. So, when this doesn’t exist, this doesn’t come to be; due to the cessation of this, this ceases. That is: Ignorance is a requirement for choices. Choices are a requirement for consciousness. Consciousness is a requirement for name and form. Name and form are requirements for the six sense fields. The six sense fields are requirements for contact. Contact is a requirement for feeling. Feeling is a requirement for craving. Craving is a requirement for grasping. Grasping is a requirement for continued existence. Continued existence is a requirement for rebirth. Rebirth is a requirement for old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress to come to be. That is how this entire mass of suffering originates. When ignorance fades away and ceases no residue left behind, choices cease. When choices cease, consciousness ceases. When consciousness ceases, name and form cease. When name and form cease, the six sense fields cease. When the six sense fields cease, contact ceases. When contact ceases, feeling ceases. When feeling ceases, craving ceases. When craving ceases, grasping ceases. When grasping ceases, continued existence ceases. When continued existence ceases, rebirth ceases. When rebirth ceases, old age and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress cease. That is how this entire mass of suffering ceases.’ This is the noble system that they have clearly seen and penetrated with wisdom.

When a noble disciple has quelled five fears and enmities, possesses the four factors of stream-entry, and has clearly seen and penetrated the noble system with wisdom, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

SN 55.29 Fears and Enmities (2nd) Dutiyabhayaverūpasantasutta

At Sāvatthī. … “Mendicants, when a noble disciple has quelled five fears and enmities, possesses the four factors of stream-entry, and has clearly seen and penetrated the noble system with wisdom, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

SN 55.30 With Nandaka the Licchavi Nandakalicchavisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then Nandaka the Licchavi chief minister went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Nandaka, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

A noble disciple who has these four things is endowed with long life, both human and heavenly …[2612] beauty … happiness … glory … and sovereignty, both human and heavenly. Now, I don’t say this because I’ve heard it from some other ascetic or brahmin. I only say it because I’ve known, seen, and realized it for myself.”

When he had spoken, a certain person said to Nandaka:

“Sir, it is time to bathe.”

“Enough now, lad, with that exterior bath. This interior bathing will do for me, that is,[2613] confidence in the Buddha.”

The Chapter at Bamboo Gate

SN 55.1 A Wheel-Turning Monarch Cakkavattirājasutta

At Sāvatthī.

There the Buddha … said:

“Mendicants, suppose a wheel-turning monarch were to rule as sovereign lord over these four continents. And when his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm, in the company of the gods of the thirty-three. There he amuses himself in the Garden of Delight, escorted by a band of nymphs, and supplied and provided with the five kinds of heavenly sensual stimulation. Still, as he’s lacking four things, he’s not exempt from hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. He’s not exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.[2566]

Now suppose a noble disciple wears rags and feeds on scraps of almsfood. Still, as they have four things, they’re exempt from hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

What four?[2567] It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha:[2568] ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’[2569]

They have experiential confidence in the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’[2570]

They have experiential confidence in the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’[2571]

Furthermore, a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion.[2572]

These are the four qualities that they possess.

And, mendicants, gaining these four continents is not worth a sixteenth part of gaining these four things.”[2573]

SN 55.2 The Objective of the Spiritual Life Brahmacariyogadhasutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.[2574]

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Those who have faith and ethics,
confidence, and vision of the truth,
in time arrive at happiness,
the objective of the spiritual life.”

SN 55.3 With Dīghāvu Dīghāvuupāsakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground.

Now at that time the lay follower Dīghāvu was sick, suffering, gravely ill.[2575] Then he addressed his father, the householder Jotika,[2576] “Please, householder, go to the Buddha, and in my name bow with your head to his feet. Say to him: ‘Sir, the lay follower Dīghāvu is sick, suffering, gravely ill. He bows with his head to your feet.’ And then say: ‘Sir, please visit him at his home out of sympathy.’”

“Yes, dear,” replied Jotika. He did as Dīghāvu asked. The Buddha consented with silence.

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the lay follower Dīghāvu, sat down on the seat spread out, and said to him, “I hope you’re keeping well, Dīghāvu, I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”

“So, Dīghāvu, you should train like this: ‘I will have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And I will have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion.’ That’s how you should train.”

“Sir, these four factors of stream-entry that were taught by the Buddha are found in me, and I exhibit them.[2577] For I have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And I have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion.”

“In that case, Dīghāvu, grounded on these four factors of stream-entry you should further develop these six things that play a part in realization. You should meditate observing the impermanence of all conditions, perceiving suffering in impermanence, perceiving not-self in suffering, perceiving giving up, perceiving fading away, and perceiving cessation.[2578] That’s how you should train.”

“These six things that play a part in realization that were taught by the Buddha are found in me, and I exhibit them. For I meditate observing the impermanence of all conditions, perceiving suffering in impermanence, perceiving not-self in suffering, perceiving giving up, perceiving fading away, and perceiving cessation.

But still, sir, I think, ‘I hope Jotika doesn’t suffer distress when I’ve gone.’” Jotika said, “Dear Dīghāvu, don’t focus on that.[2579] Come on, dear Dīghāvu, you should closely focus on what the Buddha is saying.”

When the Buddha had given this advice he rose from his seat and left. Not long after the Buddha left, Dīghāvu passed away. Then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, the lay follower named Dīghāvu, who was advised in brief by the Buddha, has passed away. Where has he been reborn in his next life?”

“Mendicants, the lay follower Dīghāvu was astute. He practiced in line with the teaching, and did not trouble me about the teachings. With the ending of the five lower fetters, he’s been reborn spontaneously, and will become extinguished there, not liable to return from that world.”

SN 55.4 With Sāriputta (1st) Paṭhamasāriputtasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then in the late afternoon, Venerable Ānanda came out of retreat … and said to Sāriputta:

“Reverend, how many things do people have to possess in order for the Buddha to declare that they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening?”

“Reverend, people have to possess four things in order for the Buddha to declare that they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. People have to possess these four things in order for the Buddha to declare that they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.”

SN 55.5 With Sāriputta (2nd) Dutiyasāriputtasutta

Then Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Sāriputta, they speak of a ‘factor for stream-entry’. What is a factor for stream-entry?”

“Sir, the factors for stream-entry are associating with true persons, listening to the true teaching, rational application of mind, and practicing in line with the teaching.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! For the factors for stream-entry are associating with true persons, listening to the true teaching, rational application of mind, and practicing in line with the teaching.

Sāriputta, they speak of ‘the stream’. What is the stream?”

“Sir, the stream is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! For the stream is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

Sāriputta, they speak of ‘a stream-enterer’. What is a stream-enterer?”

“Sir, anyone who possesses this noble eightfold path is called a stream-enterer, the venerable of such name and such clan.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! For anyone who possesses this noble eightfold path is called a stream-enterer, the venerable of such name and such clan.”

SN 55.6 The Chamberlains Thapatisutta

At Sāvatthī. At that time several mendicants were making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering. Now at that time the chamberlains Isidatta and Purāṇa were residing in Sādhuka on some business.[2580] They heard about this.

So they posted someone on the road, saying:

“My man, let us know when you see the Blessed One coming, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha.” And that person stood there for two or three days before they saw the Buddha coming off in the distance. When they saw him, they went to the chamberlains and said:

“Sirs, the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha is coming. Please come at your convenience.”

Then the chamberlains went up to the Buddha, bowed, and followed behind him. And then the Buddha left the road, went to the root of a certain tree, and sat down on the seat spread out. The chamberlains Isidatta and Purāṇa bowed, sat down to one side, and said to the Buddha:

“Sir, when we hear that you will be setting out from Sāvatthī to wander in the Kosalan lands, we’re sad and upset, thinking that you will be far from us. And when we hear that you are setting out from Sāvatthī to wander in the Kosalan lands, we’re sad and upset, thinking that you are far from us.

And when we hear that you will be setting out from the Kosalan lands to wander in the Mallian lands, we’re sad and upset, thinking that you will be far from us. And when we hear that you are setting out from the Kosalan lands to wander in the Mallian lands, we’re sad and upset, thinking that you are far from us.

And when we hear that you will be setting out from the Mallian lands to wander in the Vajjian lands …

you will be setting out from the Vajjian lands to wander in the Kāsian lands …

you will be setting out from the Kāsian lands to wander in the Magadhan lands …[2581]

you are setting out from the Kāsian lands to wander in the Magadhan lands, we’re sad and upset, thinking that you are far from us.

But when we hear that you will be setting out from the Magadhan lands to wander in the Kāsian lands, we’re happy and joyful, thinking that you will be near to us. And when we hear that you are setting out from the Magadhan lands to wander in the Kāsian lands …

you will be setting out from the Kāsian lands to wander in the Vajjian lands …

you will be setting out from the Vajjian lands to wander in the Mallian lands …

you will be setting out from the Mallian lands to wander in the Kosalan lands …[2582]

you will be setting out in the Kosalan lands to wander to Sāvatthī, we’re happy and joyful, thinking that[2583] you will be near to us.

And when we hear that you are staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery we have no little happiness and joy, thinking that you are near to us.”

“Well then, chamberlains, life at home is cramped and dirty, life gone forth is wide open. Just this much is enough for diligence.”

“Sir, for us there is something that’s even more cramped than that, and is considered as such.”

“What is that?”

“Sir, it’s when King Pasenadi of Kosala wants to go and visit a park. We have to harness and prepare his royal elephants. Then we have to seat his dear and beloved wives on the elephants, one in front of us, and one behind.[2584] Those sisters smell like a freshly opened perfume box; that’s how the royal ladies smell with makeup on.[2585] The touch of those sisters is like a tuft of cotton-wool or kapok; that’s how pampered the royal ladies are. Now at that time we must look after the elephants, the sisters, and ourselves. But we don’t recall having a bad thought regarding those sisters. This is that thing that’s even more cramped than that, and is considered as such.”

“Well then, chamberlains, life at home is cramped and dirty, life gone forth is wide open. Just this much is enough for diligence. A noble disciple who has four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

What four? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … They live at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.[2586] A noble disciple who has these four things is a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

And you have experiential confidence in the Buddha …[2587] the teaching … the Saṅgha … And whatever there is in your family that’s available to give, you share it all with those who are ethical, of good character.

What do you think, chamberlains? How many people among the Kosalans are your equal when it comes to giving and sharing?”

“We’re fortunate, sir, so very fortunate, in that the Buddha understands us like this.”

SN 55.7 The People of Bamboo Gate Veḷudvāreyyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants when he arrived at a village of the Kosalan brahmins named Bamboo Gate. The brahmins and householders of Bamboo Gate heard:

“It seems the ascetic Gotama—a Sakyan, gone forth from a Sakyan family—has arrived at Bamboo Gate, together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants. He has this good reputation: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ He has realized with his own insight this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, gods and humans—and he makes it known to others. He teaches Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And he reveals a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. It’s good to see such perfected ones.”

Then the brahmins and householders of Bamboo Gate went up to the Buddha. Before sitting down to one side, some bowed, some exchanged greetings and polite conversation, some held up their cupped palms toward the Buddha, some announced their name and clan, while some kept silent. Seated to one side they said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, these are our wishes, desires, and hopes. We wish to live at home with our children; to use sandalwood imported from Kāsi; to wear garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and to accept gold and currency. And when our body breaks up, after death, we wish to be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. Given that we have such wishes, may the Buddha teach us the Dhamma so that we may achieve them.”

“Householders, I will teach you an explanation of the Dhamma that is relevant for oneself.[2588] Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, worthy sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what is the explanation of the Dhamma that applies to oneself?

It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘I want to live and don’t want to die; I want to be happy and recoil from pain. Since this is so, if someone were to take my life, I wouldn’t like that. But others also want to live and don’t want to die; they want to be happy and recoil from pain. So if I were to take the life of someone else, they wouldn’t like that either. The thing that is disliked by me is also disliked by others. Since I dislike this thing, how can I inflict it on someone else?’ Reflecting in this way, they give up killing living creatures themselves. And they encourage others to give up killing living creatures, praising the giving up of killing living creatures. So their bodily behavior is purified in three points.

Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects: ‘If someone were to steal from me, I wouldn’t like that. But if I were to steal from someone else, they wouldn’t like that either. The thing that is disliked by me is also disliked by others. Since I dislike this thing, how can I inflict it on someone else?’ Reflecting in this way, they give up stealing themselves. And they encourage others to give up stealing, praising the giving up of stealing. So their bodily behavior is purified in three points.

Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects: ‘If someone were to have relations with my wives, I wouldn’t like it. But if I were to have relations with someone else’s wives, he wouldn’t like that either. The thing that is disliked by me is also disliked by others. Since I dislike this thing, how can I inflict it on others?’ Reflecting in this way, they give up sexual misconduct themselves. And they encourage others to give up sexual misconduct, praising the giving up of sexual misconduct. So their bodily behavior is purified in three points.

Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects: ‘If someone were to distort my meaning by lying, I wouldn’t like it.[2589] But if I were to distort someone else’s meaning by lying, they wouldn’t like it either. The thing that is disliked by me is also disliked by someone else. Since I dislike this thing, how can I inflict it on others?’ Reflecting in this way, they give up lying themselves. And they encourage others to give up lying, praising the giving up of lying. So their verbal behavior is purified in three points.

Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects: ‘If someone were to break me up from my friends by backbiting, I wouldn’t like it. But if I were to break someone else from their friends by backbiting, they wouldn’t like it either. …’ So their verbal behavior is purified in three points.

Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects: ‘If someone were to attack me with harsh speech, I wouldn’t like it. But if I were to attack someone else with harsh speech, they wouldn’t like it either. …’ So their verbal behavior is purified in three points.

Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects: ‘If someone were to annoy me by talking silliness and nonsense, I wouldn’t like it. But if I were to annoy someone else by talking silliness and nonsense, they wouldn’t like it either.’ The thing that is disliked by me is also disliked by another. Since I dislike this thing, how can I inflict it on another?’ Reflecting in this way, they give up talking nonsense themselves. And they encourage others to give up talking nonsense, praising the giving up of talking nonsense. So their verbal behavior is purified in three points.

And they have experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. When a noble disciple possesses these seven good qualities and these four desirable states they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

When he had spoken, the brahmins and householders of Bamboo Gate said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! … We go for refuge to the worthy Gotama, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember us as lay followers who have gone for refuge for life.”

SN 55.8 In the Brick Hall (1st) Paṭhamagiñjakāvasathasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying at Ñātika in the brick house.[2590] Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, the monk named Sāḷha has passed away. Where has he been reborn in his next life? The nun named Nandā, the layman named Sudatta, and the laywoman named Sujātā have passed away. Where have they been reborn in the next life?”

“Ānanda, the monk Sāḷha passed away having realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

The nun Nandā passed away having ended the five lower fetters. She’s been reborn spontaneously, and will be extinguished there, not liable to return from that world.

The layman Sudatta passed away having ended three fetters, and weakened greed, hate, and delusion. He’s a once-returner; he will come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering.

The laywoman Sujātā passed away having ended three fetters. She’s a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.

It’s no wonder that a human being should pass away. But if you should come and ask me about it each and every time someone dies that would be a bother for me. So Ānanda, I will teach you the explanation of the Dhamma named ‘the mirror of the teaching’. A noble disciple who has this may declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

And what is that mirror of the teaching?

It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. This is that mirror of the teaching. A noble disciple who has this may declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

(The following two discourses have the same setting.)

SN 55.9 At the Brick Hall (2nd) Dutiyagiñjakāvasathasutta

Ānanda said to the Buddha:

“Sir, the monk named Asoka has passed away.[2591] Where has he been reborn in his next life? The nun named Asokā, the layman named Asoka, and the laywoman named Asokā have passed away. Where have they been reborn in the next life?”

“Ānanda, the monk Asoka passed away having realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom … in this very life …

(And all is explained as in SN 55.8.)

This is that mirror of the teaching. A noble disciple who has this may declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

SN 55.10 At the Brick Hall (3rd) Tatiyagiñjakāvasathasutta

Ānanda said to the Buddha:

“Sir, the layman named Kakkaṭa has passed away in Ñātika. Where has he been reborn in his next life? The laymen named Kaḷibha, Nikata, Kaṭissaha, Tuṭṭha, Santuṭṭha, Bhadda, and Subhadda have passed away in Ñātika. Where have they been reborn in the next life?”

“Ānanda, the laymen Kakkaṭa, Kaḷibha, Nikata, Kaṭissaha, Tuṭṭha, Santuṭṭha, Bhadda, and Subhadda passed away having ended the five lower fetters. They’ve been reborn spontaneously, and will be extinguished there, not liable to return from that world.

Over fifty laymen in Ñātika have passed away having ended the five lower fetters. They’ve been reborn spontaneously, and will be extinguished there, not liable to return from that world.

More than ninety laymen in Ñātika have passed away having ended three fetters, and weakened greed, hate, and delusion. They’re once-returners, who will come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering.

More than five hundred laymen in Ñātika have passed away having ended three fetters. They’re stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening.[2592]

It’s no wonder that a human being should pass away. But if you should come and ask me about it each and every time someone passes away, that would be a bother for me. So Ānanda, I will teach you the explanation of the Dhamma named ‘the mirror of the teaching’. A noble disciple who has this may declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

And what is that mirror of the teaching?

It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And they have the ethical conduct loved by the noble ones … leading to immersion. This is that mirror of the teaching. A noble disciple who has this may declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

The Chapter on Rolling Forth the Wheel of Dhamma

SN 56.11 Rolling Forth the Wheel of Dhamma Dhammacakkappavattanasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana.[2637] There the Buddha addressed the group of five mendicants:[2638]

“Mendicants, these two extremes should not be cultivated by one gone forth.[2639] What two? Indulgence in sensual pleasures, which is low, crude, ordinary, ignoble, and pointless. And indulgence in self-mortification, which is painful, ignoble, and pointless.[2640] Avoiding these two extremes, the Realized One understood the middle way of practice, which gives vision and knowledge, and leads to peace, direct knowledge, awakening, and extinguishment.[2641]

And what is that middle way of practice? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.[2642] This is that middle way of practice, which gives vision and knowledge, and leads to peace, direct knowledge, awakening, and extinguishment.

Now this is the noble truth of suffering. Rebirth is suffering; old age is suffering; illness is suffering; death is suffering; being coupled with the disliked is suffering; separation from the liked is suffering; not getting what you wish for is suffering. In brief, the five grasping aggregates are suffering.[2643]

Now this is the noble truth of the origin of suffering. It’s the craving that leads to future lives, mixed up with relishing and greed, taking pleasure there wherever it alights. That is,[2644] craving for sensual pleasures, craving for continued existence, and craving for nonexistence.[2645]

Now this is the noble truth of the cessation of suffering. It’s the fading away and cessation of that very same craving no residue left behind; giving it away, letting it go, releasing it, and not clinging to it.[2646]

Now this is the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.[2647]

‘This is the noble truth of suffering.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.[2648] ‘This noble truth of suffering should be completely understood.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …[2649] ‘This noble truth of suffering has been completely understood.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …

‘This is the noble truth of the origin of suffering.’ Such was the vision that arose in me … ‘This noble truth of the origin of suffering should be given up.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …[2650] ‘This noble truth of the origin of suffering has been given up.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …

‘This is the noble truth of the cessation of suffering.’ Such was the vision that arose in me … ‘This noble truth of the cessation of suffering should be realized.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …[2651] ‘This noble truth of the cessation of suffering has been realized.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …

‘This is the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’ Such was the vision that arose in me … ‘This noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering should be developed.’ Such was the vision that arose in me …[2652] ‘This noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in me regarding teachings not learned before from another.[2653]

As long as my true knowledge and vision about these four noble truths was not fully purified in these three rounds and twelve aspects, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.[2654]

But when my true knowledge and vision about these four noble truths was fully purified in these three rounds and twelve aspects, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”[2655]

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the group of five mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

And while this discourse was being spoken, the stainless, immaculate vision of the Dhamma arose in Venerable Koṇḍañña: “Everything that is liable to arise is liable to cease.”

And when the Buddha rolled forth the Wheel of Dhamma, the earth gods raised the cry:[2656] “Near Varanasi, in the deer park at Isipatana, the Buddha has rolled forth the supreme Wheel of Dhamma. And that wheel cannot be rolled back by any ascetic or brahmin or god or Māra or divinity or by anyone in the world.”[2657]

Hearing the cry of the earth gods, the gods of the four great kings … the gods of the thirty-three … the gods of Yama … the joyful gods … the gods who love to create … the gods who control what is created by others … the gods of the Divinity’s host raised the cry: “Near Varanasi, in the deer park at Isipatana, the Buddha has rolled forth the supreme Wheel of Dhamma. And that wheel cannot be rolled back by any ascetic or brahmin or god or Māra or divinity or by anyone in the world.”

And so at that moment, that second, that hour, the cry soared up to the realm of divinity. And this ten-thousandfold galaxy shook and rocked and trembled. And an immeasurable, magnificent light appeared in the world, surpassing the glory of the gods.[2658]

Then the Buddha expressed this heartfelt sentiment: “Koṇḍañña has really understood! Koṇḍañña has really understood!”

And that’s how Venerable Koṇḍañña came to be known as “Koṇḍañña Who Understood”.

SN 56.12 The Realized Ones Tathāgatasutta

“‘This is the noble truth of suffering.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in the Realized Ones regarding teachings not learned before from another.[2659] ‘This noble truth of suffering should be completely understood.’ … ‘This noble truth of suffering has been completely understood.’ …

‘This is the noble truth of the origin of suffering.’ … ‘This noble truth of the origin of suffering should be given up.’ … ‘This noble truth of the origin of suffering has been given up.’ …

‘This is the noble truth of the cessation of suffering.’ … ‘This noble truth of the cessation of suffering should be realized.’ … ‘This noble truth of the cessation of suffering has been realized.’ …

‘This is the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’ … ‘This noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering should be developed.’ … ‘This noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering has been developed.’ Such was the vision, knowledge, wisdom, realization, and light that arose in the Realized Ones regarding teachings not learned before from another.”

SN 56.13 Aggregates Khandhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.

And what is the noble truth of suffering? You should say: ‘The five grasping aggregates’. That is: form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness.[2660] This is called the noble truth of suffering.

And what is the noble truth of the origin of suffering? It’s the craving that leads to future lives, mixed up with relishing and greed, taking pleasure there wherever it alights. That is, craving for sensual pleasures, craving for existence, and craving for nonexistence. This is called the noble truth of the origin of suffering.

And what is the noble truth of the cessation of suffering? It’s the fading away and cessation of that very same craving no residue left behind; giving it away, letting it go, releasing it, and not clinging to it. This is called the noble truth of the cessation of suffering.

And what is the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering? It is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. This is called the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. These are the four noble truths.

That’s why you should practice meditation to understand: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’.”

SN 56.14 Interior Sense Fields Ajjhattikāyatanasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.

And what is the noble truth of suffering? You should say: ‘The six interior sense fields’. What six? The sense fields of the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. This is called the noble truth of suffering.

And what is the noble truth of the origin of suffering? …

the cessation of suffering? …

the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering? It is simply this noble eightfold path …

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.15 Remembering (1st) Paṭhamadhāraṇasutta

“Mendicants, do you remember the four noble truths that I taught?” When he said this, one of the mendicants said to the Buddha:

“I do, sir.”

“How so, mendicant?”

“Sir, I remember that suffering is the first noble truth you’ve taught; the origin of suffering is the second; the cessation of suffering is the third; and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering is the fourth. That’s how I remember the four noble truths as you’ve taught them.”

“Good, good, mendicant! It’s good that you remember the four noble truths as I’ve taught them. Suffering is the first noble truth I’ve taught, and that’s how you should remember it. The origin of suffering is the second; the cessation of suffering is the third; and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering is the fourth. That’s how you should remember the four noble truths as I’ve taught them.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.16 Remembering (2nd) Dutiyadhāraṇasutta

“Mendicants, do you remember the four noble truths that I taught?” When he said this, one of the mendicants said to the Buddha:

“I do, sir.”

“How so, mendicant?”

“Sir, I remember that suffering is the first noble truth you’ve taught. For if any ascetic or brahmin should say this: ‘What the ascetic Gotama teaches is not the first noble truth of suffering. I’ll deny this first noble truth of suffering and describe another first noble truth of suffering.’ That is not possible. The origin of suffering … The cessation of suffering … The practice that leads to the cessation of suffering is the fourth noble truth you’ve taught. For if any ascetic or brahmin should say this: ‘What the ascetic Gotama teaches is not the fourth noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. I’ll deny this fourth noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering and describe another fourth noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’ That is not possible. That’s how I remember the four noble truths as you’ve taught them.”

“Good, good, mendicant! It’s good that you remember the four noble truths as I’ve taught them. Suffering is the first noble truth I’ve taught, and that’s how you should remember it. For if any ascetic or brahmin should say this: ‘What the ascetic Gotama teaches is not the first noble truth of suffering. I’ll deny this first noble truth of suffering and describe another first noble truth of suffering.’ That is not possible. The origin of suffering … The cessation of suffering … The practice that leads to the cessation of suffering is the fourth noble truth I’ve taught, and that’s how you should remember it. For if any ascetic or brahmin should say this: ‘What the ascetic Gotama teaches is not the fourth noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. I’ll deny this fourth noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering and describe another fourth noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’ That is not possible. That’s how you should remember the four noble truths as I’ve taught them.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.17 Ignorance Avijjāsutta

Seated to one side, that mendicant said to the Buddha:

“Sir, they speak of this thing called ‘ignorance’. What is ignorance? And how is an ignoramus defined?”

“Not knowing about suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. This is called ignorance. And this is how an ignoramus is defined.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.18 Knowledge Vijjāsutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of this thing called ‘knowledge’. What is knowledge? And how is a knowing one defined?”

“Knowing about suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. This is called knowledge. And this is how a knowing one is defined.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.19 Expressions Saṅkāsanasutta

“Mendicants, I’ve declared: ‘This is the noble truth of suffering.’ For that there are limitless arrangements, phrasings, and illustrations:[2661] ‘This is another way of saying that this is the noble truth of suffering.’[2662] I’ve declared: ‘This is the noble truth of the origin of suffering.’ … I’ve declared: ‘This is the noble truth of the cessation of suffering.’ … I’ve declared: ‘This is the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’ For that there are limitless arrangements, phrasings, and illustrations: ‘This is another way of saying that this is the noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.20 Real Tathasutta

“Mendicants, these four things are real, not unreal, not otherwise. What four? ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’ … These four things are real, not unreal, not otherwise.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

The Chapter at the Village of Koṭi

SN 56.21 At the Village of Koṭi (1st) Paṭhamakoṭigāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Vajjis at the village of Koṭi.[2663] There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, due to not understanding and not penetrating four noble truths, both you and I have wandered and transmigrated for such a very long time.

What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. These noble truths of suffering, origin, cessation, and the path have been understood and comprehended. Craving for continued existence has been cut off; the leash to existence is ended; now there’ll be no more future lives.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Because of not truly seeing
the four noble truths,
we have transmigrated for a long time
from one rebirth to the next.

But now that these truths have been seen,
the leash to existence is eradicated.
The root of suffering is cut off,
now there’ll be no more future lives.”

SN 56.22 At the Village of Koṭi (2nd) Dutiyakoṭigāmasutta

“Mendicants, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.[2664] I don’t deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables don’t realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and don’t live having realized it with their own insight in this very life.

There are ascetics and brahmins who do truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. I deem them as true ascetics and brahmins. Those venerables realize the goal of life as an ascetic or brahmin, and live having realized it with their own insight.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“There are those who don’t understand suffering
and suffering’s cause,
and where all suffering
ceases no residue left behind.

And they do not know the path
that leads to the stilling of suffering.
They lack the heart’s release,
as well as the release by wisdom.
Unable to make an end,
they continue to be reborn and grow old.

But there are those who understand suffering
and suffering’s cause,
and where all suffering
ceases no residue left behind.

And they understand the path
that leads to the stilling of suffering.
They’re endowed with the heart’s release,
as well as the release by wisdom.
Able to make an end,
they don’t continue to be reborn and grow old.”

SN 56.23 The Fully Awakened Buddha Sammāsambuddhasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, there are these four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. These are the four noble truths. It is because he has truly understood these four noble truths that the Realized One is called ‘the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha’.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.24 The Perfected Ones Arahantasutta

At Sāvatthī.

“Mendicants, whatever perfected ones, fully awakened Buddhas truly awaken—in the past, future, or present—all of them truly awaken to the four noble truths.

What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. Whatever perfected ones, fully awakened Buddhas truly awaken—in the past, future, or present—all of them truly awaken to the four noble truths.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.25 The Ending of Defilements Āsavakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, I say that the ending of defilements is for one who knows and sees, not for one who does not know or see. For one who knows and sees what? The ending of defilements is for one who knows and sees suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. The ending of the defilements is for one who knows and sees this.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.26 Friends Mittasutta

“Mendicants, those who you have sympathy for, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the true comprehension of the four noble truths.

What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. Those who you have sympathy for, and those worth listening to—friends and colleagues, relatives and family—should be encouraged, supported, and established by you in the true comprehension of these four noble truths.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.27 Real Tathasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. These four noble truths are real, not unreal, not otherwise. That’s why they’re called ‘noble truths’.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.28 The World Lokasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. In this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans, the Realized One is the Noble One. That’s why they’re called ‘noble truths’.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.29 Should Be Completely Understood Pariññeyyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. These are the four noble truths. Of these four noble truths, there is one to be completely understood, one to be given up, one to be realized, and one to be developed.

And which noble truth should be completely understood? The noble truth of suffering should be completely understood. The noble truth of the origin of suffering should be given up. The noble truth of the cessation of suffering should be realized. The noble truth of the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering should be developed.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.30 With Gavampati Gavampatisutta

At one time several mendicants were staying in the land of the Cetīs at Sahajāti.[2665] Now at that time, after the meal, on return from almsround, several senior mendicants sat together in the pavilion and this discussion came up among them:

“Reverends, does someone who sees suffering also see the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering?”

When they said this, Venerable Gavampati said to those senior mendicants:[2666]

“Reverends, I have heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha:[2667] ‘Someone who sees suffering also sees the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. Someone who sees the origin of suffering also sees suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. Someone who sees the cessation of suffering also sees suffering, the origin of suffering, and the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering. Someone who sees the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering also sees suffering, the origin of suffering, and the cessation of suffering.’”

The Chapter on a Cliff

SN 56.41 Speculation About the World Lokacintāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Once upon a time, mendicants, a certain person left Rājagaha, thinking ‘I’ll speculate about the world.’ They went to the Sumāgadhā lotus pond and sat down on the bank speculating about the world.[2678] Then that person saw an army of four divisions enter a lotus stalk. When he saw this he thought, ‘I’ve gone mad, really, I’ve lost my mind! I’m seeing things that don’t exist in the world.’

Then that person entered the city and informed a large crowd, ‘I’ve gone mad, really, I’ve lost my mind! I’m seeing things that don’t exist in the world.’

‘But how is it that you’re mad? How have you lost your mind? And what have you seen that doesn’t exist in the world?’

‘Sirs, I left Rājagaha, thinking “I’ll speculate about the world.” I went to the Sumāgadhā lotus pond and sat down on the bank speculating about the world. Then I saw an army of four divisions enter a lotus stalk. That’s why I’m mad, that’s why I’ve lost my mind. And that’s what I’ve seen that doesn’t exist in the world.’

‘Well, my man, you’re definitely mad, you’ve definitely lost your mind. And you’re seeing things that don’t exist in the world.’

But what that person saw was in fact real, not unreal. Once upon a time, a battle was fought between the gods and the titans. In that battle the gods won and the titans lost. The defeated and terrified titans entered the citadel of the titans through the lotus stalk only to confuse the gods.[2679]

So mendicants, don’t speculate about the world.[2680] For example: the cosmos is eternal, or not eternal, or finite, or infinite; the soul and the body are one and the same, or the soul is one thing, the body another; after death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists. Why is that? Because those thoughts aren’t beneficial or relevant to the fundamentals of the spiritual life. They don’t lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.

When you think something up, you should think: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. Why is that? Because those thoughts are beneficial and relevant to the fundamentals of the spiritual life. They lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.42 A Cliff Papātasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain.

Then the Buddha said to the mendicants, “Come, mendicants, let’s go to Inspiration Peak for the day’s meditation.”[2681]

“Yes, sir,” they replied. Then the Buddha together with several mendicants went to Inspiration Peak.

A certain mendicant saw the big cliff there and said to the Buddha, “Sir, that big cliff is really big and scary. Is there any other cliff bigger and scarier than this one?”

“There is, mendicant.”

“But sir, what is it?”

“Mendicant, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.[2682] They take pleasure in choices that lead to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress.[2683] Since they take pleasure in such choices, they continue to make them. Having made choices that lead to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress, they fall down the cliff of rebirth, old age, and death, of sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

There are ascetics and brahmins who truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They don’t take pleasure in choices that lead to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. Since they don’t take pleasure in such choices, they stop making them. Having stopped making choices that lead to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress, they don’t fall down the cliff of rebirth, old age, and death, of sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from suffering, I say.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.43 The Great Scorching Mahāpariḷāhasutta

“Mendicants, there is a hell called ‘The Great Scorching’.[2684] There, whatever sight you see with your eye is unlikable, not likable; undesirable, not desirable; unpleasant, not pleasant.[2685] Whatever sound you hear … Whatever odor you smell … Whatever flavor you taste … Whatever touch you feel … Whatever idea you know with your mind is unlikable, not likable; undesirable, not desirable; unpleasant, not pleasant.”

When he said this, one of the mendicants said to the Buddha, “Sir, that scorching really is mighty, so very mighty. Is there any other scorching more mighty and terrifying than this one?”

“There is, mendicant.”

“But sir, what is it?”

“Mendicants, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They take pleasure in choices that lead to rebirth … They continue to make such choices … Having made such choices, they burn with the scorching of rebirth, old age, and death, of sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

There are ascetics and brahmins who truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They don’t take pleasure in choices that lead to rebirth … They stop making such choices … Having stopped making such choices, they don’t burn with the scorching of rebirth, old age, and death, of sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from suffering, I say.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.44 A Bungalow Kūṭāgārasutta

“Mendicants, suppose someone were to say: ‘Without truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is not possible.

It’s as if someone were to say: ‘Before the lower story of a bungalow is built, I will hoist up the upper story.’ That is not possible. In the same way, suppose someone were to say: ‘Without truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is not possible.

But suppose someone were to say: ‘After truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is possible.

It’s as if someone were to say: ‘After the lower story of a bungalow is built, I will hoist up the upper story.’ That is possible. In the same way, suppose someone were to say: ‘After truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is possible.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.45 Splitting Hairs Vālasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Vesālī for alms. He saw several Licchavi youths practicing archery near the town hall. They were shooting arrows from a distance through a small keyhole, shaft after shaft without missing.[2686]

When he saw this he thought, “These Licchavi youths really are trained, so well trained, in that they shoot arrows from a distance through a small keyhole, shaft after shaft without missing.”

Then Ānanda wandered for alms in Vesālī. After the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“What do you think, Ānanda? Which is harder and more challenging: to shoot arrows from a distance through a small keyhole, shaft after shaft without missing? Or to take a horsehair split into seven strands and penetrate one tip with another tip?”

“It’s more difficult and challenging, sir, to take a horsehair split into seven strands and penetrate one tip with another tip.”

“Still, Ānanda, those who truly penetrate suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path penetrate something tougher than that.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.46 Darkness Andhakārasutta

“Mendicants, the boundless gloom of interstellar space is so utterly dark that even the luminosity of the moon and the sun, so mighty and powerful, makes no impression.”[2687]

When he said this, one of the mendicants said to the Buddha, “Sir, that darkness really is mighty, so very mighty. Is there any other darkness more mighty and terrifying than this one?”

“There is, mendicant.”

“But sir, what is it?”

“There are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They take pleasure in choices that lead to rebirth … They continue to make such choices … Having made such choices, they fall into the darkness of rebirth, old age, and death, of sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

There are ascetics and brahmins who truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They don’t take pleasure in choices that lead to rebirth … They stop making such choices … Having stopped making such choices, they don’t fall into the darkness of rebirth, old age, and death, of sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from suffering, I say.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.47 A Yoke With a Hole (1st) Paṭhamachiggaḷayugasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a person were to throw a yoke with a single hole into the ocean. And there was a one-eyed turtle who popped up once every hundred years.[2688]

What do you think, mendicants? Would that one-eyed turtle, popping up once every hundred years, still poke its neck through the hole in that yoke?”

“Only after a very long time, sir, if ever.”

“That one-eyed turtle might poke its neck through the hole in that yoke, but in any case it’d be sooner than a fool fallen to the underworld is reborn as a human being, I say.

Why is that? Because in that place there’s no principled or moral conduct, and no doing what is good and skillful. There they just prey on each other, preying on the weak. Why is that? It’s because they haven’t seen the four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.48 A Yoke With a Hole (2nd) Dutiyachiggaḷayugasutta

“Mendicants, suppose the earth was entirely covered with water. And a person threw a yoke with a single hole into it. The east wind wafts it west; the west wind wafts it east; the north wind wafts it south; and the south wind wafts it north. And there was a one-eyed turtle who popped up once every hundred years.

What do you think, mendicants? Would that one-eyed turtle, popping up once every hundred years, still poke its neck through the hole in that yoke?”

“It would be an anomaly, sir.”

“That’s how anomalous it is to get reborn as a human being.[2689] And that’s how anomalous it is for a Realized One to arise in the world, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha. And that’s how anomalous it is for the teaching and training proclaimed by a Realized One to shine in the world. And now, mendicants, you have been reborn as a human being. A Realized One has arisen in the world, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha. And the teaching and training proclaimed by a Realized One shines in the world.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.49 Sineru, King of Mountains (1st) Paṭhamasinerupabbatarājasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a person was to place on Sineru, the king of mountains, seven pebbles the size of mung beans.[2690]

What do you think, mendicants? Which is more: the seven pebbles the size of mung beans? Or Sineru, the king of mountains?”

“Sir, Sineru, the king of mountains, is certainly more. The seven pebbles the size of mung beans are tiny. Compared to Sineru, they don’t count, there’s no comparison, they’re not worth a fraction.”

“In the same way, for an individual with comprehension, a noble disciple accomplished in view, the suffering that’s over and done with is more, what’s left is tiny. Compared to the mass of suffering in the past that’s over and done with, it doesn’t count, there’s no comparison, it’s not worth a fraction, since there are at most seven more lives. Such an individual truly understands about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.50 Sineru, King of Mountains (2nd) Dutiyasinerupabbatarājasutta

“Mendicants, suppose Sineru, the king of mountains, was worn away and eroded except seven pebbles the size of mustard seeds.[2691]

What do you think, mendicants? Which is more: the portion of Sineru, the king of mountains, that has been worn away and eroded? Or the seven pebbles the size of mustard seeds that are left?”

“Sir, the portion of Sineru, the king of mountains, that has been worn away and eroded is certainly more. The seven pebbles the size of mustard seeds are tiny. Compared to Sineru, they don’t count, there’s no comparison, they’re not worth a fraction.”

“In the same way, for an individual with comprehension, a noble disciple accomplished in view, the suffering that’s over and done with is more, what’s left is tiny. Compared to the mass of suffering in the past that’s over and done with, it doesn’t count, there’s no comparison, it’s not worth a fraction, since there are at most seven more lives. Such an individual truly understands about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

The First Chapter of Abbreviated Texts on Raw Grain

SN 56.61 Not Human Aññatrasutta

Then the Buddha, picking up a little bit of dirt on his fingernail, addressed the mendicants: “What do you think, mendicants? Which is more: the little bit of dirt on my fingernail, or this great earth?”

“Sir, the great earth is certainly more. The little bit of dirt on your fingernail is tiny. Compared to the great earth, it doesn’t count, there’s no comparison, it’s not worth a fraction.”

“In the same way, the sentient beings reborn as humans are few, while those not reborn as humans are many.[2693] Why is that? It’s because they haven’t seen the four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.62 In the Borderlands Paccantasutta

Then the Buddha, picking up a little bit of dirt on his fingernail, addressed the mendicants: “What do you think, mendicants? Which is more: the little bit of dirt on my fingernail, or this great earth?”

“Sir, the great earth is certainly more. The little bit of dirt on your fingernail is tiny. Compared to the great earth, it doesn’t count, there’s no comparison, it’s not worth a fraction.”

“In the same way, the sentient beings reborn in central countries are few, while those reborn in the borderlands, among uneducated foreigners, are many. …”[2694]

SN 56.63 Wisdom Paññāsutta

“… the sentient beings who have the noble eye of wisdom are few, while those who are ignorant and confused are many. …”

SN 56.64 Beer and Wine Surāmerayasutta

“… the sentient beings who refrain from intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, are few, while those who don’t refrain are many. …”

SN 56.65 Born in Water Odakasutta

“… the sentient beings born on land are few, while those born in water are many. …”

SN 56.66 Respect Mother Matteyyasutta

“… the sentient beings who respect their mothers are few, while those who don’t are many. …”

SN 56.67 Respect Father Petteyyasutta

“… the sentient beings who respect their fathers are few, while those who don’t are many. …”

SN 56.68 Respect Ascetics Sāmaññasutta

“… the sentient beings who respect ascetics are few, while those who don’t are many. …”

SN 56.69 Respect Brahmins Brahmaññasutta

“… the sentient beings who respect brahmins are few, while those who don’t are many. …”

SN 56.70 Honor the Elders Pacāyikasutta

“… the sentient beings who honor the elders in the family are few, while those who don’t are many. …”

The Chapter in a Rosewood Forest

SN 56.31 In a Rosewood Forest Sīsapāvanasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Kosambī in a rosewood grove.[2668] Then the Buddha picked up a few rosewood leaves in his hand and addressed the mendicants: “What do you think, mendicants? Which is more: the few leaves in my hand, or those in the grove above?”

“Sir, the few leaves in your hand are a tiny amount. There are far more leaves in the grove above.”

“In the same way, there is much more that I have directly known but have not explained to you. What I have explained is a tiny amount.[2669] And why haven’t I explained it? Because it’s not beneficial or relevant to the fundamentals of the spiritual life. It doesn’t lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. That’s why I haven’t explained it.

And what have I explained? I have explained: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’.

And why have I explained this? Because it’s beneficial and relevant to the fundamentals of the spiritual life. It leads to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. That’s why I’ve explained it.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.32 Acacia Leaves Khadirapattasutta

“Mendicants, suppose someone were to say: ‘Without truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is not possible.

It’s as if someone were to say: ‘I’ll make a basket out of acacia leaves or pine needles or myrobalan leaves, and use it to carry water or ripe palmyra fruit.’[2670] That is not possible. In the same way, suppose someone were to say: ‘Without truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is not possible.

But suppose someone were to say: ‘After truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is possible.

It’s as if someone were to say: ‘I’ll make a basket out of lotus leaves or flame-of-the-forest leaves or camel’s foot creeper leaves, and use it to carry water or ripe palmyra fruit.’[2671] That is possible. In the same way, suppose someone were to say: ‘After truly comprehending the noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path, I will completely make an end of suffering.’ That is possible.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.33 A Stick Daṇḍasutta

“Mendicants, suppose a stick was tossed up in the air. Sometimes it’d fall on its bottom and sometimes the top. It’s the same for sentient beings roaming and transmigrating, shrouded by ignorance and fettered by craving. Sometimes they go from this world to the other world, and sometimes they come from the other world to this world. Why is that? It’s because they haven’t seen the four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.34 Clothes Celasutta

“Mendicants, if your clothes or head were on fire, what would you do about it?”

“Sir, if our clothes or head were on fire, we’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness in order to extinguish it.”

“Mendicants, so long as you have not encompassed the four noble truths, regard your burning head or clothes with equanimity, ignore them, and apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness to truly comprehending the four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.35 A Hundred Spears Sattisatasutta

“Mendicants, suppose there was a man with a lifespan of a hundred years. And someone might say to him: ‘Come now, my man, they’ll strike you with a hundred spears in the morning, at midday, and in the late afternoon.[2672] And you’ll live for a hundred years being struck with three hundred spears every day. But when a hundred years have passed, you will comprehend the four noble truths for the first time.’

For an earnest gentleman this is sufficient reason to submit.

Why is that? This transmigration has no known beginning. No first point is found of blows by spears, swords, arrows, and axes. Now this may be so. But the comprehension of the four noble truths doesn’t come with pain or sadness, I say. Rather, the comprehension of the four noble truths comes only with pleasure and happiness, I say. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.36 Living Creatures Pāṇasutta

“Suppose a person was to strip all the grass, sticks, branches, and leaves in the Black Plum Tree Land, gather them together into one pile, and make them into stakes. Then they’d impale the large creatures in the ocean on large stakes; the medium-sized creatures on medium-sized stakes; and the small creatures on small stakes. They wouldn’t run out of sizable creatures in the ocean before using up all the grass, sticks, branches, and leaves in the Black Plum Tree Land. There are far more small creatures in the ocean than this, so it wouldn’t be feasible to impale them on stakes.[2673] Why is that? Because of the small size of those life-forms. That’s how big the plane of loss is.

An individual accomplished in view, exempt from that vast plane of loss, truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.37 The Simile of the Sun (1st) Paṭhamasūriyasutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise.

In the same way, for a mendicant right view is the forerunner and harbinger of truly comprehending the four noble truths. That mendicant can expect to truly understand: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.38 The Simile of the Sun (2nd) Dutiyasūriyasutta

“Mendicants, as long as the moon and the sun don’t arise in the world, no great light or great radiance appears.[2674] Darkness prevails then, utter darkness. Day and night aren’t found, nor months and fortnights, nor seasons and years.

But when the moon and the sun arise in the world, a great light, a great radiance appears. Darkness no longer prevails. Day and night are found, and months and fortnights, and seasons and years.

In the same way, as long as the Realized One doesn’t arise in the world, no great light or great radiance appears. Darkness prevails then, utter darkness. There’s no explanation of the four noble truths, no teaching, advocating, establishing, clarifying, analyzing, and revealing of them.

But when the Realized One arises in the world, a great light, a great radiance appears. Darkness no longer prevails. Then there’s the explanation of the four noble truths, the teaching, advocating, establishing, clarifying, analyzing, and revealing of them. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.39 Indra’s pillar Indakhīlasutta

“Mendicants, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They gaze up at the face of another ascetic or brahmin, thinking:[2675] ‘Surely this worthy one knows and sees.’

Suppose there was a light tuft of cotton-wool or kapok which was taken up by the wind and landed on level ground. The east wind wafts it west; the west wind wafts it east; the north wind wafts it south; and the south wind wafts it north. Why is that? It’s because the tuft of cotton-wool is so light.

In the same way, there are ascetics and brahmins who don’t truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They gaze up at the face of another ascetic or brahmin, thinking: ‘Surely this worthy one knows and sees.’ Why is that? It’s because they haven’t seen the four noble truths.

There are ascetics and brahmins who truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They don’t gaze up at the face of another ascetic or brahmin, thinking: ‘Surely this worthy one knows and sees.’

Suppose there was an iron pillar or an Indra’s pillar with deep foundations, firmly embedded, imperturbable and unshakable.[2676] Even if violent storms were to blow up out of the east, the west, the north, and the south, they couldn’t make it shake or rock or tremble. Why is that? It’s because that Indra’s pillar is firmly embedded, with deep foundations.

In the same way, there are ascetics and brahmins who truly understand about suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. They don’t gaze up at the face of another ascetic or brahmin, thinking: ‘Surely this worthy one knows and sees.’ Why is that? It’s because they have clearly seen the four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”

SN 56.40 Looking For a Debate Vādatthikasutta

“Mendicants, take any mendicant who truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. An ascetic or brahmin might come from the east, west, north, or south wanting to debate, seeking a debate, thinking: ‘I’ll refute their doctrine!’ It’s simply impossible for them to legitimately make that mendicant shake or rock or tremble.

Suppose there was a stone post, sixteen feet long.[2677] Eight feet were buried underground, and eight above ground. Even if violent storms were to blow up out of the east, the west, the north, and the south, they couldn’t make it shake or rock or tremble. Why is that? It’s because that stone post is firmly embedded, with deep foundations.

In the same way, take any mendicant who truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. An ascetic or brahmin might come from the east, west, north, or south wanting to debate, seeking a debate, thinking: ‘I’ll refute their doctrine!’ It’s simply impossible for them to legitimately make that mendicant shake or rock or tremble. Why is that? It’s because they have clearly seen the four noble truths. What four? The noble truths of suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path.

That’s why you should practice meditation …”